<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plaine explanation of the vvhole Revelation of Saint John Very necessary and comfortable in these dayes of trouble and affliction in the church. Penned by a faithfull preacher, now with God, for more priuate vse, and now published for the further benefit of the people of God.</title>
            <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1535-1603.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 248 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4710.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124379</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898948</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898948</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150822</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73707)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150822)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1983:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plaine explanation of the vvhole Revelation of Saint John Very necessary and comfortable in these dayes of trouble and affliction in the church. Penned by a faithfull preacher, now with God, for more priuate vse, and now published for the further benefit of the people of God.</title>
                  <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1535-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 139, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by T.S. for Nathaniel Newbery,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Cartwright--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-S⁴ T² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Congregational Library, Gordon Square, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150822:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PLAINE EXPLANATION OF THE WHOLE <hi>REVELATION</hi> OF SAINT <hi>JOHN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Very neceſſary and comfortable in theſe dayes of <hi>trouble and affliction in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Penned by a faithfull Preacher, now with God, for more priuate vſe, and now publiſhed for the further benefit of the people of GOD.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>There came a voyce from heauen, ſaying: Come away from her, my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſinnes; leſt ye be partakers of her plagues,</hi> 
               <bibl>Reu. 18. 4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <q>
               <hi>Here are they that keepe the commandements of God, and the Faith of Ieſus,</hi> 
               <bibl>Reuel. 14. 12.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Alas, alas, wat great City is in one houre come to deſolation,</hi> 
               <bibl>Reuel. 18. 16. 17.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>The Beaſt, and the falſe Prophets, were aliue caſt into a Lake of fire, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <bibl>Reuel. 19. 20.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Newbery,</hi> 1622,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150822:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:150822:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150822:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hatſoeuer things were written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore time, were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures, might haue hope.</hi> Rom. 15. 4. <hi>And the Reuelation of</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>which God gaue vnto him, to ſhew vnto his Seruants,</hi> Reu. 1. 1. was giuen and written for the comfort of the Church in her lateſt and greateſt troubles, and ſharpeſt afflictions and perſecutions; wherein certes Gods loue and care of his Church, is abundantly manifeſted. For not any of the Primitiue perſecutions, or latter Antichriſtian Seducions, and bloudy Combuſtions, wherewith at this day the Church is turmoyled: But they are foretold, with their Iſſue and Euents in this Booke; that ſo the choſen and elect of God might not be carried to euerlaſting perdition, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelmed with ſorrow and diſpleaſure in their ſeeming inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricable temporary calamities.</p>
            <p>Many Commentaries and Expoſitions of this Booke haue beene publiſhed by very Reuerend and excellent learned men, no doubt to the great comfort of Gods people; and therefore the leſſe need there may be imagined to be of any more: but, (beſides that this is more briefe and plain vpon the whole Book then any other; and ſo is more vſefull for the moſt, that haue moſt vſe of it; if it ſhall ſerue but as a watch-word, euen now to direct Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their perplexities, whether to haue recourſe for comfort and conſolation, and ſo incite them to a more diligent reading, and
<pb facs="tcp:150822:4"/> ſtudious ſearch of this holy <hi>Reuelation,</hi> it will be a ſufficient a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollogy for this publication; eſpecially at this time; when ſo many wauer betweene hope and diſpaire of the good ſucceſſe, of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of Chriſtendome; which ſo nearely concerne the welfare of the Church, as that the Enemies begin to looke bigge againe; daily expecting the ruine of it, as if the hope of Gods people were vaine; or as if by their wicked pollicy and power they made ſure account to diſappoint God of his purpoſe, and decreed deſtruction of the Kingdome of Antichriſt; not conſidering that the more they extend their malicious practiſes againſt the deſolate Woman, the more and greater woes are due vnto them, and the more horrible iudgements ſhall come vpon them, and that happily by meanes of thoſe weaklings whom they now ſo much ſcorne and trample vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For, vpon whom haue they gaped, at whom haue they hiſſed, but at the holy ones, and the annointed of God? Well, I ſay no more, but that God is wonderfull in all his workes, and ſo will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himſelfe in the deſtruction of thoſe his enemies; and in the deliuerance of his faithfull ones out of the hands, and from the rage of the Dragon, and his Inſtruments; the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> with all their Locuſts and Frogs; let them caſt abroad neuer ſo great flouds of deceits and perſecutions to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme the Church, and to extirpate true Religion; onely it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooues the profeſſors of truth, in this expectation to arme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with faith and patience, and to exerciſe themſelues in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Gods holy Commandements; and then they may reſt aſſured of the accompliſhment (in Gods good time) of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes expreſſed in this Booke.</p>
            <p>Wherein to helpe vs, the Author (a man of excellent gifts) long ſince trauailed; and now by the prouidence of God, are his labours in this kinde publiſhed for our comfort. I pray God that we may be directed to make good vſe both of the holly <hi>Reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> it ſelfe; and of his labour in the Explanation of it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150822:4"/>
            <head>A PLAINE AND FAMILIAR EXPLANATION of the whole <hi>Reuelation</hi> of <hi>Saint</hi> IOHN.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>APOCALYPS, CAP. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>The <hi>Reuelation</hi> of <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> which God gaue vnto him, to ſhew vnto his Seruants things which muſt ſhortly be done, which he ſent, and ſhewed by his Angell vnto his ſeruant <hi>IOHN,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> in his time was raiſed vp of the Lord as an inſtrument to reueale to the Church of God in thoſe dayes, the difficulties to come vnto the Church of the Iewes, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Church might be armed againſt thoſe troubles, as alſo to comfort them in the good iſſue thereof. So here the Apoſtle is ſtirred vp as an Inſtrument of the ſame, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church of the Chriſtians, which he doth by the prophecie contained in this Booke.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:150822:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>In the beginning of this Booke is firſt ſet downe the excellencie of the Prophecie herein contained, and the inſtrument of the deliuery of it; which is, the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell,</hi> and of the penning of it, which is <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelfe.</p>
               <p>The excellencie of the Booke is ſet downe by the diuers commendations, to the inflaming of the mindes of the hearers to a diligent obſeruation of the matter contained in it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in that it is called a <hi>Reuelation,</hi> he noteth, that it is ſuch a thing, as that the wit of no man or Angell can attaine vnto it without the ſpeciall manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is that which God giueth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be a moſt excellent thing; and further, as it is Gods gift, ſo it was giuen by God the Father to Chriſt, to giue vnto his ſeruants; namely, as hee was Mediator, and in that regard onely it was reuealed to him: for, as he was God, he was equall to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in knowledge; now God the Father would giue nothing to Chriſt, but that which was moſt excellent.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is commended in regard of the matter to be reuealed, to wit, that which was <hi>to come ſhortly</hi> or <hi>quickly,</hi> namely, in a ſhort time, before the end of the world, both in regard that they ſhould begin out of hand, and eſpecially in regard of God, for though in regard of vs it ſhould ſeeme to be long, yet it is ſhort vnto God.</p>
               <p>The inſtrument by whom God declareth it to <hi>Iohn,</hi> is ſaid to be the Angell, to wit, <hi>the Angell of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> which is Chriſt the Sonne of God, which is here ſaid to be <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> which is alſo a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commendation of the Booke.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150822:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Another argument of commendation is, that it was giuen to <hi>Iohn,</hi> a notable Miniſter, Apoſtle, and Witneſſe of the Miſtery of the Goſpell of Chriſt Ieſus, to whom all the Scriptures are directed.</p>
               <p>Another reaſon of the excellencie of it, is drawne from the effects of it, to wit, that the knowledge of this ſhould make them bleſſed which did heare it, and keepe the things herein contained.</p>
               <p>Further, it is commended in regard of the time wherein it was deliuered to <hi>Iohn,</hi> to wit, when he was <hi>exiled, for the Goſpell ſake, into the Ile of Pathmos,</hi> which argueth that it was a notable thing, ſeeing it was to be a matter of great comfort to him in ſuch a diſtreſſe: And more particularly, that it is ſaid to <hi>be reuealed on the Lords day;</hi> wherein God vſeth to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more excellent things, concerning his will and counſell, then at other times: And as the Sabbath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth commendations, and credit, and authority vnto the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> ſo this <hi>Reuelation</hi> alſo giueth authoritie to the Sabbath.</p>
               <p>And firſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> beginneth with a Salutation, that it might draw attention, and be the more accepted of the hearers. In the ſalutation, hee wiſheth <hi>Grace and peace from the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Father is ſet out to be <hi>Hee</hi> that <hi>was, is, &amp; ſhal be,</hi> that is, <hi>euerlaſting.</hi> The holy Ghoſt is ſet down next, by the name of <hi>ſeauen Spirits,</hi> as hauing relation vnto the ſeauen Churches, making as it were a conformity of the Spirit with thoſe ſeauen Churches hereafter men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, wherein his Miſtery moſt eſpecially lay.</p>
               <p>The cauſe wherefore he did chuſe ſeauen Churches and no other number, it is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the number of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150822:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> for ſeauen is a perfect number: and therefore he ſaith, the holy Ghoſt is as ſeauen Spirits, to poure out his grace effectually in all the Churches, becauſe he is as effectuall in all, as in one, for his ſtrength is not diuided. And by ſeauen Churches he alſo vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth all the reſt.</p>
               <p>Next the holy Ghoſt, is ſet downe the Sonne of God: The reaſon why the ſecond Perſon is ſet after, is, firſt becauſe the Scripture is wont to ſet that in the laſt place, which it vſeth to intreate longeſt of, now therefore the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> being here princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to ſpeake of our Sauiour Chriſt, ſetteth him in the laſt place.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Salutation,</hi> he wiſheth <hi>grace</hi> vnto the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, with the fruit thereof, which is <hi>peace,</hi> which are ſet downe by their end, to wit, that God might be glorified.</p>
               <p>Chriſt is here deſcribed by his offices; firſt, in that he is called the <hi>faithfull Witneſſe,</hi> ſignifying that hee is a Prophet to teſtifie the truth to his people.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he is deſcribed by his Prieſt-hood, in that he is called <hi>the firſt begotten of the dead;</hi> ſhewing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that he was offered vp in ſacrifice for his Church, and was riſen from the dead.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by his kingdome, in that he is called <hi>Prince of the Kings of the earth:</hi> that is, he to whom all power belongeth, and to whom all Princes are ſubiect, as of whom they receiue their Scepters.</p>
               <p>Afterward the Apoſtle ſhewes that he did not ſet downe this <hi>Reuelation</hi> by himſelfe, but by the calling of Chriſt; and therefore bringeth in the author of his calling, which was Chriſt, whom he ſetteth downe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150822:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> by his comming in the clouds; which he ſaith, ſhall be ſo glorious, that euery one ſhall ſee him: and that this authority may be more effectuall, he bringeth in Chriſt, ſpeaking in his owne perſon, ſaying, <hi>I am Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha and Omega.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſtly, the Apoſtle bringeth in himſelfe, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing himſelfe to be a Brother, that is, a member of Chriſt, and one that waited for deliuerance by him. And againe, that hee was a Labourer in the Church, and therefore was perſecuted for the Truths-ſake, for which cauſe hee was now driuen into the Iſle of <hi>Path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos:</hi> And heere hee ſaith, <hi>hee was rauiſhed in the ſpirit, and heard a voice as of a Trumpet:</hi> In that he ſaith he was <hi>rauiſhed in the ſpirit,</hi> he ſignifieth that his minde was withdrawne from all worldly cogitations, and was addicted and bent vnto thoſe holy meditations which it pleaſed the Lord to miniſter vnto him. Where we ſee that hee with-held himſelfe from all other things, to the end hee might better attend vpon all good occaſions, to learne any thing concerning the will of God.</p>
               <p>Which teacheth vs in holy exerciſes, eſpecially which concerne the will of God, to ſeparate our ſelues from any thing that may hinder vs, or withdraw our mindes from the ſame; and more principally ought the Miniſters ſo to doe, when they are to be occupied in the ſtudy of the word of God, and in deliuering the will of God vnto the people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And hee looked to ſee the Voice:</hi> Not that the voice could be ſeene, but he looked from whence it ſhould come, and who ſhould ſpeake it. Then hee ſheweth what hee ſaw (which is the preparation of the two
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150822:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> Chapters following:) that which he ſaw was <hi>ſeauen Candleſtickes,</hi> which note the ſeauen Churches; for the Candleſtickes are of Gold, ſignifying the glory and puritie of them; ſo that wee ſee that albeit the Church in the world ſeemeth to be contemptible, yet with God it is moſt precious.</p>
               <p>Afterward the Apoſtle doth notably deſcribe <hi>Him,</hi> whom he ſaw; and firſt, by his apparell, in that hee had <hi>a long Garment;</hi> noting, that hee was a great Councellor: for, amongſt the Iewes, Councellors v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to weare ſuch manner of Garments. This noteth, that Chriſt is infinitely wiſe, and therefore able to giue counſell to his Church.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>his paps girded,</hi> noting, that as he is wiſe ſo he is ready to helpe his ſeruants ſpeedily with his counſell. A ſimilitude taken from the cuſtome of thoſe Countries of the Eaſt, who when they would make haſt in doing any thing, they would gird vp their Cloathes to their breaſts, leſt they ſhould be any hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance vnto them, that they might more ſpeedily doe that they went about,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His head white;</hi> declaritg his grauity, as gray haires are ſignes of age.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His eyes flaming;</hi> that is, piercing and entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hearts of men, laying open, and ſeeing all things whatſoeuer, though neuer ſo ſecret.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His feete Braſſe;</hi> ſhewing his power and maieſtie, as being able to tread his enemies, and all that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his will, or that oppoſeth it ſelfe to him, in peeces vnder his feete.</p>
               <p>After follow his effects; and firſt, by his <hi>voice,</hi> which is ſaid to be like <hi>the ſound of many waters,</hi> ſetting down
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150822:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> thereby the maieſtie of his voyce; noting, how terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chriſt is to his enemies: Then hee is ſaid to haue <hi>ſeauen Starres in his hand,</hi> which ſignifieth the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who are the lights of the Church: And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they are ſaid <hi>to be in his hand,</hi> it noteth, that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Word, are in the cuſtody of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpheld, maintained, and gouerned by him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Out of his mouth went a ſharpe two-edged ſword;</hi> Which is his Goſpell: And whereas it is ſaid to haue <hi>two edges,</hi> it declareth the double vertue of the word of God, which either cutteth and healeth vnto life, or woundeth to death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His face ſhining as the Sunne;</hi> either ſetting forth the fulneſſe of his Maieſtie, or elſe his enlightning of the earth with the light of the Goſpell, like as the Sunne with his beames.</p>
               <p>Afterward, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, that he <hi>fell downe at the ſight hereof;</hi> which he did partly in reuerence, and partly in feare: But the Lord raiſeth him vp, and vpholdeth him, bidding him not to feare. And in a word, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preteth all the miſtery, and ſetteth downe briefly the ſumme of the whole Booke following, which was then to be reuealed vnto him: namely, that it was either of <hi>things preſent,</hi> or of <hi>things to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The things preſent, were thoſe which were then done, though <hi>Iohn</hi> knew not of them: which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the three firſt Chapters of the Booke.</p>
               <p>The things to come, are thoſe which afterwards ſhould be done vnto the end of the world: and doe follow in the reſt of the Booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:150822:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 2. v. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>Vnto the Angell of the Church of Epheſus write, Theſe things ſaith he that holdeth the ſeauen ſtarres in his right hand, and walketh in the middes of the ſeauen golden Candleſtickes, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe Prophet hauing ſet downe the diuiſion of his Booke, which is, into two parts, concerning things <hi>preſent,</hi> and things <hi>to come.</hi> He now commeth to the firſt; namely, concerning thoſe things that were then done: where, firſt hee ſets downe the Epiſtles which Chriſt ſends to the Churches. In the Epiſtles, we are to conſider thoſe things that are common to them all, &amp; thoſe things that are proper to euery one.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The things common to all, are firſt, that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine titles in them fit for the matter whereunto euery Epiſtle driueth. In the titles it is common to all, that it is directed firſt and principally to the <hi>Angell;</hi> that is, to the Miniſter, as being principall in the Church: Yet ſo as that it belongeth alſo to the whole Church, as appeareth by the Exhortation in the end of euery Epiſtle, <hi>Let him that hath eares heare, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, this is common to all, in that hee either commendeth their good things they haue, or diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth their euill, exhorting them to the good, and dehorting them from the euill, adioyning promiſes vnto their good things, and threatning iudgements againſt their euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, the attention vnto the promiſes which hee ſtirreth them vp vnto: and this hee moueth diuerſly. In the three firſt Epiſtles, he ſeemeth more eſpecially
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150822:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> to moue them with care, by threatnings, in the foure latter, he more expreſly ſets downe their reward: and thereupon hee ſets downe this exhortation vnto at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, <hi>Let him that hath an eare, heare what the ſpirit ſaith to the Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To come to the Epiſtles particularly: In the firſt he writeth to <hi>the Church of Epheſus.</hi> Chriſt deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth himſelfe by that, by which he is ſet downe, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. 13. 16. namely, to be <hi>hee which hath the ſeauen Starres in his hand:</hi> noting, that all good things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer are in the Miniſters, they come from him, and the praiſe thereof is due vnto him. And ſecondly, in that <hi>hee walketh in the midſt of the Candleſtickes,</hi> hee noteth, that hee ſeeth all their doings, and therefore he knoweth their workes and their labours. And here he commends in them, firſt, their <hi>Patience,</hi> then their <hi>Impatience;</hi> the latter he handles firſt, as is the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Scripture; namely, that they could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare thoſe that fained themſelues to be Apoſtles, and yet were not, and therefore they proued them and tried, and found them to be lyars: Secondly, their <hi>Patience,</hi> that they <hi>had borne much affliction,</hi> and <hi>many troubles for the truths ſake,</hi> and did ſtill beare in the maintenance thereof, and were not weary, which is required in true <hi>patience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hauing commended the good in them, hee comes to the reproofe; where hee teacheth thoſe that are to reprehend others, that they ſet downe in the firſt place, the things that are praiſe-worthy in the parties to be reprehended, and then to ſet downe the reproofe: Which condemneth thoſe which vſe to rell the faults, leauing out the remembrance of the good;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150822:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> but the holy Ghoſt here contrariwiſe, doth nominate and commend their vertues, that the better they might be are the reproofe of their vices.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 4. The reproofe is, that hee ſaith, <hi>they had fallen from their firſt loue:</hi> Where hee reprehendeth their want of zeale; ſhewing that the feruencie of their loue which firſt they had, was now decayed and coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, therefore hee exhorteth them to a change, firſt, in their <hi>iudgement,</hi> that they ſhould reforme it, which appeareth in that he ſaith Verſe 5. <hi>Remember.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then in their <hi>will</hi> and <hi>affections</hi> in that hee bids them <hi>repent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, in their <hi>actions,</hi> in that hee commandeth them <hi>to doe their firſt workes:</hi> So that he requireth of them a good and full reformation of all things that were amiſſe, both inwardly and outwardly. And hee ſheweth further, if they will not be reformed, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as he exhorteth them, that hee will <hi>remoue their Candleſtickes,</hi> that is, either caſt them into baniſhment, and ſuffer them to be led into captiuity, or remoue his Goſpell from them. And leſt they ſhould be too much diſcouraged and caſt downe by this ſeuere and ſharpe reprehenſion, hee doth after mollifie the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe by praiſing them againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 6. And hee ſaith, that they haue this good thing, <hi>that they hate the ſinne of the Nicolaitans,</hi> which <hi>he alſo hated,</hi> to wit, both ſpirituall and corporall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. And laſtly, he ſhutteth vp the Epiſtle, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a promiſe, <hi>if they returne and ouercome, they ſhall eate of the tree of life;</hi> that is, be partakers of Chriſt, who was repreſented and figured by <hi>the tree of life in Paradiſe,</hi> of whom, <hi>whoſoeuer eateth, ſhal neuer die,</hi> Ioh. 6.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:150822:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 8. The next is the Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Smirna,</hi> and amongſt them hee findeth nothing but matter of commendation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 9. And here firſt hee praiſeth them for their <hi>patient ſuffering of afflictions;</hi> through which, they were <hi>become poore,</hi> yet ſo as that by the bleſſing of God, that pouertie was turned to their further <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall riches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After, hee comes to ſhew wherein their affliction conſiſted, and was more grieuous vnto them, namely, in that they had ſuch among them, which <hi>profeſſed themſelues Iewes,</hi> that is, children of God, that is, Chriſtians, but yet <hi>were not,</hi> but would maintaine the ceremonies of the Law, and preferre them before the ſubſtance of the Goſpell, and would mingle the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Law with the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 10. And becauſe they were afraide of future euils, hee fore-telleth them of ſuch troubles which ſhould befall them, that they might be the better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared againſt them, and the more comforted in them. And hee telleth them that ſome of them ſhould be <hi>caſt into priſon,</hi> and that they ſhould haue <hi>tribulation,</hi> that is, grieuous afflictions and perſecution, <hi>ten daies,</hi> that is, tenne yeares; euery day being counted for a yeare, according as that phraſe is vſed and expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in <hi>Daniel,</hi> as afterward it came to paſſe, from halfe the raigne of <hi>Traian,</hi> to the time of <hi>Adrian,</hi> for which ſpace the Church ſuffered extreame perſecution.</p>
               <p>And howſoeuer their Perſecutors might ſeeme to doe it in the ſeruice of God, yet he ſheweth them that it ſhould be the onely hand of the Diuell, and through his malice, &amp; therfore they ſhould not be diſcouraged,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150822:10"/> but ſhould rather be comforted; for, ſeeing the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell was againſt them, God was therefore with them on their ſide, to defend them and take their part. And to the end they might be the more confirmed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hee comforteth them with an argument drawne from the hope of their Reſurrection; that howſoeuer here in this life they ſhould be perſecuted, and ſhould ſuffer, euen vntill death, yet they perſeuering vnto the end, ſhould not be hurt at all with the latter death. And for this cauſe alſo he vſeth, in the Title, an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment drawne from his owne perſon, in that <hi>he is firſt and laſt,</hi> and therefore able to deliuer them: As alſo, that <hi>he was dead and is aliue;</hi> and therefore howſoeuer they might ſuffer temporary death, yet they ſhould riſe againe as he did, and liue with him eternally.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 12. After followeth the Epiſtle to the <hi>Church of Pergamus,</hi> where hee findeth ſome good things which hee commendeth: namely, their <hi>conſtancie</hi> in profeſſing of religion, and their <hi>patience;</hi> which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth by two circumſtances, both in regard of the <hi>place,</hi> and of the <hi>time</hi> wherein they liued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 13. Concerning the <hi>place,</hi> it was there <hi>where the Diuell erected his throne,</hi> that is, where hee ſeemed at his pleaſure to raigne, as Prince in his Subiects: Neuertheleſſe, they were conſtant and kept their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>time,</hi> it was <hi>when the faithfull man Antipas was put to death:</hi> that is, in ſuch a time wherein per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution was very hot againſt the Children of God, and yet notwithſtanding they ſtarted not from their profeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 14. Yet for all this, hee hath certaine things
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150822:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> againſt them, which he reprehendeth: namely, that they <hi>permitted certaine falſe Prophets amongſt them,</hi> and did not withſtand them, as the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> did, but ſuffered them <hi>to teach dangerous doctrine of Balaam,</hi> which taught and maintained <hi>bodily whordome and fornication,</hi> whereby the people were brought to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, of which ſort were thoſe amongſt them which held the doctrine of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> to wit, that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and bodily whoredome.</p>
               <p>The reformation whereof hee exhorts them to, in bidding them <hi>repent;</hi> and this hee doth by theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; to wit, firſt, if they would repent, they ſhould be partakers of <hi>the hid,</hi> that is, <hi>ſpirituall Manna,</hi> in the wilderneſſe, which was hidden in the Arke in a pot.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Manna</hi> is meant (as <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 6.) the grace, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and holineſſe of Chriſt, imputed vnto vs, and that Iuſtification by him which came downe from heauen, which none know, but thoſe which haue it. Secondly, another reaſon, that <hi>he that did ouercome, he would giue him a white ſtone:</hi> Which phraſe of ſpeech is a ſimilitude taken from the manner of the Gentiles, (as in times paſt the Prophets vſed to take borrowed ſpeeches from the cuſtome of the Iewes, in the Law,) becauſe now the Church was communicated with the Gentiles, the Goſpell being now ſpread among them. This cuſtome was eſpecially amongſt the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians;</hi> The manner of it was, that when any one was accuſed of ſome criminall matter, he was ſtraight-way put to his triall; if hee were found cleare, hee had a white ſtone giuen him, if otherwiſe he was found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and was to be condemned, hee had giuen him a blacke ſtone, or ſome other colour: So that now in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150822:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> that it is ſaid, that <hi>hee which ouercommeth, ſhould haue a white ſtone giuen him,</hi> hee meaneth that hee ſhall haue nothing laide to his charge, but ſhall be freed from all his ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 18. Laſtly, hee commeth to the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> where he findeth many good things, which he commendeth, as their <hi>loue,</hi> (contrary to the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi>) and the fruits thereof; their <hi>ſeruiceableneſſe,</hi> their <hi>faith</hi> alſo, and their <hi>patience,</hi> and their <hi>workes,</hi> to haue beene more at the <hi>laſt,</hi> then at the <hi>firſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 20. Yet hee hath ſomewhat againſt them, to wit, that they ſuffered <hi>Iezabel</hi> (albeit they themſelues maintained her not) whether one of that name, or ſuch a one as <hi>Iazabel</hi> was, it is vncertaine; yet ſuch a one as calling her ſelfe a <hi>Propheteſſe,</hi> did ſeduce the people with her <hi>whordomes and Idolatries,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he chargeth the Church, becauſe they did let her alone: for it is not enough for the Church of God to doe well themſelues, and to refraine from thoſe that are euill-doers in the ſame, but if it lye in them, the Church of God is to refraine others from thoſe euils, and to puniſh the offenders ſo farre as they may.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 22. Now therefore the Lord ſaith, that hee wil <hi>execute iudgement vpon her,</hi> by <hi>caſting her into a Bed,</hi> that is, laying a moſt grieuous and heauie affliction vpon <hi>her,</hi> and not onely vpon <hi>her,</hi> but vpon <hi>all that committed fornication with her;</hi> that is, which were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with <hi>her</hi> in her ſinnes of <hi>whoredome</hi> and <hi>idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie:</hi> namely, thoſe that were her vpholders &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers. And not onely on them, but this iudgement ſhould alſo be manifeſted vpon her Children; by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150822:11"/> Children, meaning either her Schollers which learne of her, or her poſteritie, and then he ſaith <hi>he will kill,</hi> that is, cleane roote them out of the earth. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they would pretend great <hi>Miſteries</hi> and <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> as to be guided by the ſpirit of Prophecie, (as the Anabaptiſts in our times alſo doe) and to haue Reuelations, yet ſeeing their manners and actions are filthie, abhominable, and deteſtable, therefore the Lord will execute iudgement vpon them. And hee will doe it vpon the tranſgreſſors themſelues, but as for the Church, albeit they had thus ſuffered them, yet he would not puniſh them after this ſort, but hee would hereby (namely by the puniſhment inflicted on the euill doers) be content to call them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for that ſinne of theirs in ſuffering them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 26. Laſtly, he ſaith, <hi>to thoſe that ouercome hee will giue authority:</hi> firſt, to be Kings ouer the Gentiles, and to beare rule ouer the wicked, and to ſubdue them, being ioyned with Chriſt in his Kingdome. And ſecondly, he would make them partakers of his glory, in making them Prieſts vnto God, which hee ſets downe by <hi>the morning Starre,</hi> which Starie, as it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth next to the Sunne, ſo it is next vnto it moſt glorious, ſignifying that the righteous ſhould come neare vnto Chriſt, and be euen ioyned with him in his glory, at his glorious comming.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:150822:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 3. l.</bibl>
                  <q>And write vnto the Angell of the Church which is at Sardis, Theſe things ſaith he that hath the ſeauen Spirits of God, and the ſeauen Starres, I know thy workes: for thou haſt a name that thou liueſt, but thou art dead, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>OF the things that were already done, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth onely that which is contained in this Chapter. Where; firſt, he writeth to the fift Church, to wit, the Church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> where he getteth authoritie by vſing the ſame title which he did to the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> &amp; addeth another, to wit, that <hi>it is hee which hath alſo the ſeauen Spirits:</hi> wherby he noteth the fulneſſe, and exceeding meaſure of his ſpirit, &amp; the abundance of his power and grace, by the which hee doth alſo vphold and gouerne the Starres, that is, the Miniſters of his Church. This Church hee commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not at all, as he did before commend the other Churches; but rather beginneth with reprehenſion, ſaying, that they had a name <hi>that they were aliue, but indeed they were dead,</hi> Verſe 1. that is, they ſeemed to haue that, which in truth they had not.</p>
               <p>And firſt hee exhorterh the Angell of <hi>Sardis</hi> to looke vnto himſelfe, in that he bids him <hi>awake, and be not ſecure and careleſſe;</hi> and then to looke vnto others committed to his charge: And therefore it is that <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth <hi>Timothy</hi> to take heede vnto himſelfe; that ſo he being reformed himſelfe, may be more fit to looke to thoſe who are committed to him. For thoſe that were committed to his charge, he biddeth the Angell to ſtrengthen thoſe things that were ready to dye,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150822:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> that is, to recouer that which was almoſt loſt, and that betime, leſt it dye altogether; a note, that as yet they were not cleane dead, whereby he mollifieth the ſpeech which went before: For he had ſaid before to the Angell of <hi>Sardis,</hi> that <hi>he was ſtarke dead,</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in regard of that they would be, if they refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not themſelues betime: After, hee willeth him to <hi>remember,</hi> that is, conſider diligently what gifts he had receiued, and that hee ſhould vſe them well: namely, thereby he ſhould inſtruct the Church, and that <hi>hee repeat,</hi> for otherwiſe, hee will come againſt them ſodainely, as a thiefe in the night, at vnawares, when he ſhould be vnprepared; and ſo his deſtruction ſhould be moſt fearefull: Yet (ſaith hee) <hi>I haue a few names</hi> (as <hi>Acts.</hi> 1. 15.) that is, a few perſons, <hi>which had not defiled their Garments,</hi> that is, which were found faithfull, and had not beene infected nor defiled with thoſe ſinnes which raigned in that Church for whoſe ſake he yet ſpared them, and fauoured them as hee would haue <hi>Sodome,</hi> if there had beene but tenne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous found therein: And theſe (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall goe with me in white, and be cloathed in white array,</hi> that is, be couered with his righteouſneſſe, and be partakers of his honour; for, <hi>white is a token of honour;</hi> and that they <hi>ſhall not haue their names put out of the booke of life,</hi> that is, ſhould be crowned with immortalitie.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>to thoſe that ouercome,</hi> which confeſſed his name before men, he promiſeth that hee would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their name before his Father, and before his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels; Where he giueth vs to vnderſtand what was the chiefe ſinne of that Church, to wit, that they were afraide to make ſo full a confeſſion of Chriſt before
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150822:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> men, as they ſhould haue done: For, as it ſeemeth, they would profeſſe Chriſtianity indeed, yet ſo, as that they would not diſpleaſe any by it, nor incurre any danger for the ſame: Therefore he promiſeth to him that ouercommeth, that hee will confeſſe him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, in his Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Next hee commeth to the Church of <hi>Philadelphia;</hi> where he deſcribes himſelfe by his offices: Firſt, hee ſetteth downe himſelfe to be <hi>holy,</hi> alluding to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of the Prieſt-hood in the Law, vpon whoſe head was written, <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord:</hi> which was a<note place="margin">Exod. 39. 30.</note> Type and Figure of Chriſt, hee being holy himſelfe, yea, the holineſſe of his Father: By this word, <hi>holy,</hi> is noted vnto vs the Prieſt-hood of Chriſt, whereby we are made holy: He is called <hi>true,</hi> hauing regard to his Propheticall office, whereby he teacheth his people the truth of his will.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in that he is ſaid to haue the <hi>keyes of Dauid, and that he openeth, and no man ſhutteth, and ſhutteth and no man openeth:</hi> it noteth vnto vs his kingdome; and vpon this title the reſt of the Epiſtles runneth, which he proſecuteth, in that he had declared himſelfe to be King indeed herein; namely, in that he ſaith hee had ſet open a dore for his Goſpell among them, ſo that none ſhould ſhut it; ſignifying, that when God will bring the truth to light, and will haue it to preuaile, none ſhall be able to reſiſt it: And (ſaith hee) albeit they were weake, and had but little ſtrength, yet they ſhould not be diſcouraged at it, or at the greatneſſe or multitude of their enemies, (which he vnderſtandeth by the <hi>Sinagogues of Sathan</hi>) but ſeeing they had yet kept this dore of the word open, they ſhould therfore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150822:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> the rather hold it open more conſtantly and coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, and hee would helpe them the more by his power, and maintaine them therein: yea, hee ſaith that if they will thus continue, he will open the doore of the Goſpell ſo farre, as that he will make the moſt grieuous enemies, which called themſelues <hi>Iewes,</hi> that is, the Children of God and profeſſors of Chriſt, which yet were not ſo, as thoſe that ioyned their Law and the Goſpell, he would euen make them to come and fall downe at the feete of the Miniſters, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip before them. Not that here is any thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Papiſts can ground that men are to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped; for hee doth not ſay that they ſhould wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the <hi>Angell,</hi> but they ſhould worſhip God at the feete of the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> to wit, as Schollers, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand at his mouth the will of God: As <hi>Paul</hi> is ſaid to be brought vp at the feete of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> that is, to be inſtructed of him as his Scholler: And the Diſciples in the <hi>Acts</hi> are ſaid to ſtand at the feete of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, that is, to attend to their doctrine, and to learne of them the will of God. Laſtly, hee promiſeth to thoſe that ſtriue and ouercome, that they ſhall be like <hi>Pillars in Gods Temple,</hi> to wit, notable Inſtruments in the Church of God; and namely, ſuch as ſhould both be moſt firme and ſtable, as that they ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be remoued from the profeſſion of the Goſpell; and alſo ſuch as ſhould be beautifull ornaments in the houſe of God, as Pillars wrought with curious workes vſed to be in great houſes; and eſpecially in the Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> for it was an vſuall thing to graue their Pillars, for the beautifying of them, with names and other fine workes, and therefore hee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150822:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> alludeth to that ſame cuſtome, ſaith, that he <hi>will graue vpon them the name of his father,</hi> that is, to be his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: and <hi>the name of the City of God,</hi> that is, the Church of God, <hi>the new Ieruſalem,</hi> the people newly regenerate; and that hee would <hi>write vpon them his name,</hi> that is, make them to be partakers of his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and glory.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place he writes to the Church of <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea,</hi> where he alſo giues himſelfe titles as before, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing himſelfe by his offices; firſt, hee cals himſelfe, <hi>Amen,</hi> namely, he in whom all the promiſes of God are, <hi>yea,</hi> and <hi>Amen;</hi> that is, are fully accompliſhed: whereby he notes his Kingdome, becauſe by it, hee bringeth to paſſe whatſoeuer hath beene ſaid before. His propheticall office, in that he is called <hi>the faithfull</hi> and <hi>true Witneſſe;</hi> namely, he which faithfully teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the truth to his people.</p>
               <p>His Prieſt-hood, in that hee is <hi>the beginning of the Creatures of God:</hi> ſignifying the ſecond creation, which is regeneration: And not (as it is in one place, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.) the worke of the God-head in faſhioning of all the Creatures, as it is there meant; but here it is rather to be vnderſtood of his worke of redemption, as hee is Mediator.</p>
               <p>That which he reprehendeth in them is this, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>they are neither hot nor colde;</hi> that is, they halt betweene two Religions, ſwimming as it were betweene two waters: and this he ſetteth out to be a very deſperate caſe, and therefore ſaith hee, <hi>I would for thine owne ſake thou wereſt either hot or colde,</hi> for, <hi>becauſe thou art neither, but onely luke-warme, it ſhall come to thee as vſeth to befall the luke-warme water in a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150822:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> mans ſtomacke, which will not abide, but muſt be ſpued out,</hi> euen ſo ſaith he, <hi>becauſe thou art neither hot nor colde, it will come to paſſe that I ſhall euen ſpue thee out of my mouth;</hi> that is, I ſhall vtterly abandon thee out of my fauour, and caſt thee cleane from mee, ſo that I ſhall haue nothing to doe with thee any more. Then to declare vnto them the grieuouſneſſe of this ſinne of theirs, hee telleth them the cauſe of that their luke-warmeneſſe in religion, to wit, becauſe ſaith hee, <hi>thou ſaieſt thou art rich,</hi> that is, thou thinkeſt thy ſelfe to be perfect and in good eſtate, but indeed <hi>thou art poore, naked, deſtitute of all grace and haſt nothing at all;</hi> yea, thou art blinde, and canſt not ſee thy want, and therefore thou art ſo much the more miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and thy caſe more dangerous and deſperate. And therefore ſaith he, <hi>I aduiſe thee to looke to thy ſelfe quickly, and to addreſſe thy wants:</hi> And he telleth the meanes how they may doe it, namely, <hi>come (ſaith hee) and buy of mee gold, &amp;c.</hi> But may ſome ſay, how can the Church buy any thing of Chriſt, ſeeing ſhe hath nothing at all, but is altogether poore and deſtitute? The Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> anſwereth, <hi>come and buy,</hi> but he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>for nothing.</hi> And therefore our Sauiour ſaith here, <hi>come and buy of me gold,</hi> that is, onely if thou wilt, come and enrich thy ſelfe with the riches of my graces, <hi>come and buy white apparell,</hi> that is, cloath thee with my Righteouſneſſe, and ſo couer thy ſhame, and get a <hi>Collirium,</hi> an Ointment to annoint thy blinde eyes, that thou maiſt ſee better, and know more perfectly what a grieuous caſe thou art in, and what a fault thou haſt committed. Like vnto this Church is the eſtate of many that profeſſe the Goſpell among vs, who
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150822:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> thinke they are well, and that they haue great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, whereas indeed they haue nothing at all, as their liues doe teſtifie.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, that they ſhould not take in euill part this his ſharpe reprehenſion, he ſaith, <hi>as many as hee loueth he rebuketh and chaſteneth;</hi> and therefore they ſhould take his reproofe in good part, and be brought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance by it; for it was a manifeſt token of his loue and fatherly kindneſſe towards them, if they would profit by it. And he bids them alſo <hi>be zealous;</hi> where he noteth another cauſe of their former ſinne to be want of <hi>zeale,</hi> which he wiſheth them to reforme. And he ſaith, <hi>though he be a King, yea, the King of Kings;</hi> yet he ſtandeth at the doore and knocketh, that is, calleth them to repentance, and promiſeth, if they will let him in, that is, turne from their ſinne, and yeeld to his will, he will come vnto them and Sup with them; ſignifying, what exceeding ioy and comfort they ſhould receiue by him; yea, they ſhould be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the ioyes of heauen: where he alludeth to the comfort that friends haue one of another, when they meete together at their Dinners, Suppers, and Feaſts; which thing if it be comfortable to men, much more comfort ſhall it miniſter vnto vs, to be partakers of the company of Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, in his heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly banquet. A ſecond benefit he noteth, in that thoſe that doe thus receiue him, <hi>and ouercome,</hi> ſhall not onely receiue comfort, but <hi>glory</hi> alſo and <hi>honour in his Kingdome,</hi> and that hee will ſet them vpon his <hi>Throne,</hi> and they ſhould raigne with his Father in his Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150822:15"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 4. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>After this I looked, and behold, a doore was open in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and the firſt voyce which I heard, was as it were of a Trumpet talking with me, ſaying, Come vp hither, and I will ſhew thee things which muſt be done hereafter, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HItherto wee haue heard of the firſt part of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> concerning the things that were then done: Now it remaineth to ſpeake of the things to come, which is giuen vs to vnderſtand in the beginning of this Chapter, in that it is ſaid, <hi>I will ſhew thee things which muſt be done hereafter.</hi> And firſt, here are ſet forth thoſe things, generally, which are afterwards to come vnto the whole world, and this is from this Chapter, to the beginning of the tenth Chapter: Afterwards, the things that befall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to the Church of God, from the tenth Chapter to the end of the Booke: According as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> in his Prophecie did firſt manifeſt vnto the Church the things which ſhould befall vnto the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, and then vnto the Church it ſelfe alſo. The which iudgements it pleaſeth the Lord to reueale vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Church, becauſe they being in the world, though they be not of the world, as our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh, <hi>are yet intereſſed in thoſe outward trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles which come vpon the world.</hi> Firſt, then it is ſaid there <hi>was a dore open in heauen:</hi> Which teacheth vs, that vnleſſe God open a doore vnto vs, all things are hid in his Counſell, and ſhut vp, ſo that none can ſee into them, and eſpecially thoſe things which concerne the ſaluation of Man.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150822:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Againe, it is ſaid, he heard <hi>another voice like a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,</hi> which was to waken him better; for, albeit hee was wakened before, yet he was not ſufficiently wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſtirred vp to behold the things afterward to be deliuered. The like wee ſee in <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Ezechiel;</hi> to ſhew that we had need of new calling on, and new attention, of new ſtirring vp and preparation when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wee are to learne any new thing out of the word of God, euen as <hi>Iohn</hi> had a new preparation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of this new matter to be reuealed; for new things require new attention. After hee was bidden to <hi>come vp:</hi> Which teacheth vs, that vnleſſe wee be lifted vp aboue our ſelues, by Gods power, to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of heauenly things, and of thoſe things eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially which belong to our ſaluation, we can haue no power to vnderſtand them. And whereas hee is here bidden to <hi>come vp,</hi> and not before in the other place; it ſheweth vs that the matters following, which were afterwards to come to paſſe, are more difficult, and haue the more need with greater diligence to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and that we are with more care to labour for the vnderſtanding of them, then of thoſe things that were before.</p>
               <p>And whereas he is ſaid to <hi>be rauiſhed in the ſpirit,</hi> it meaneth, that he was as it were caſt aſleepe, and in a trance, and his ſenſes being with-held from all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of obiects which might hinder him, hauing for a time ſet aſide all worldly things and cogitations, to the end all the powers of his ſoule might be lifted vp, and be more intent, and that ſo hee might hearken more diligently to thoſe things that were ready to be told him.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150822:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Which teacheth vs, when wee goe about holy and heauenly matters, wee muſt be as it were in a new world, and we muſt ſeparate our ſelues from all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, and worldly cogitations, though otherwiſe at other times lawfull; and addict and addreſſe our ſelues wholly to thoſe holy things of our God.</p>
               <p>Then he commeth to the viſion it ſelfe. Where firſt is ſet down the preparation and <hi>preface</hi> of that which is to come, contained in this, and in the next Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>preface</hi> is deſcribed and ſet forth vnto vs the perſon of God the Father, and that diuerſly: firſt, <hi>by a Throne, and one ſitting thereon;</hi> comparing him in likeneſſe to a <hi>Iaſper</hi> and <hi>Sardy Stone,</hi> that is, very glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to behold, and of moſt exceeding valour; not deſcribing him by any forme or portraicture, but by the glory which thoſe moſt precious Iewels that can be, doe repreſent. This glory is declared by the reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which was ſo great, that it made all that was round about the Throne to be like <hi>a Rainbow,</hi> that is, <hi>glorious and excellent:</hi> for as the brightneſſe of the Sunne cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thoſe notable colours which wee ſee in the <hi>Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow,</hi> ſo the glory of God maketh all round about him glorious.</p>
               <p>After he is deſcribed by his Aſſiſtants, <hi>to wit, foure and twentie Elders,</hi> that is, <hi>the Church of God;</hi> the chiefe whereof are in the Scripture, twelue Patriarches in the old Teſtament, and the twelue Apoſtles in the New, vnder which number all the reſt are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended.</p>
               <p>Theſe are ſaid <hi>to haue white Robes and Crownes, and to ſit vpon Thrones,</hi> in forme of Kings; for all theſe are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150822:17"/> things belonging properly vnto Princes; ſignifying, that in Chriſt we are all Kings, being made partakers of his Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Afterward, God is deſcribed by the effects which proceeded from the <hi>Throne,</hi> to wit, <hi>thunders and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and voices,</hi> and their immediate cauſe; in that <hi>they came from the ſeauen Lamps,</hi> which are <hi>the ſeauen ſpirits of God,</hi> namely, the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> whereby God doth all things that he doth. This teacheth, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the thunders, lightenings, &amp;c. come from the Throne of God, that therefore nothing can come by chance or fortune, as men vainely ſuppoſe, but onely by the direction and counſell of God, and from him who is the Ruler and Diſpoſer of all things in the world.</p>
               <p>By <hi>lightnings, thunders,</hi> and <hi>voices,</hi> ſeemeth to be meant the iudgements and anger of God, to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted on the wicked, which doe follow in the next Chapters, <hi>viz.</hi> 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. for it is not vnmeet that in theſe the iudgements ſhould be ſet forth, ſeeing they are the fearefull workes of God.</p>
               <p>And here God the Father is deſcribed to be a <hi>Iudge,</hi> and to fit like a Iudge, as <hi>being Iudge of all the world,</hi> as he is called, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 25. Then he is deſcribed <hi>by foure Beaſts in the middes of the Throne, and round about,</hi> to wit, the chiefe Angels of God, wayting for to execute Gods will at all times: And as Sargeants attend on their Iudge, ſo are they, being alwaies ready to receiue any commandement he enioyneth them. So alſo our Sauiour Chriſt in <hi>Iohn,</hi> is ſaid <hi>to waite ſtill on the will of his Father;</hi> namely, as he is <hi>Mediator.</hi> In that theſe are ſaid to be <hi>foure,</hi> it is not to be thought that there
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150822:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> were no more in number, but hee vnderſtandeth by <hi>foure,</hi> a competent and ſufficient number, able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute any thing which God will haue fulfilled in all the world, in the <hi>Eaſt, Weſt, South,</hi> and <hi>North.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Beaſts are alſo deſcribed <hi>to be full of eyes,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying their prouidence and ſingular direction they goe withall.</p>
               <p>Then they are ſeuerally deſcribed; the firſt of them is like a <hi>Lyon,</hi> declaring their courage; the ſecond, like an <hi>Oxe,</hi> ſignifying their ſtrength; the third, like a <hi>Man,</hi> noting their wiſedome; the fourth, like an <hi>Eagle,</hi> ſhewing their ſwiftneſſe and ſpeedineſſe in doing Gods will. Their <hi>ſixe wings</hi> expreſſeth their readineſſe to goe to all places: their <hi>wings full of eyes,</hi> ſhew that they goe not at all aduentures.</p>
               <p>Theſe were about the Throne.</p>
               <p>Vnder it was a <hi>Sea of Chriſtall,</hi> whereby ſeemeth to be meant the earthly creatures, and all things in this preſent world, compared to a Sea, becauſe of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie of them, likened to <hi>Chriſtall,</hi> becauſe God ſeeth clearely into them, and through them; for as one may ſee eaſily into Glaſſe, and Chriſtall, ſo theſe are euidently ſeene and diſcerned of God, as being continually in his ſight and preſence, hauing beene made by him, and being gouerned by him. After, the foure Beaſts are ſaid <hi>to fall downe and praiſe him day and night,</hi> for all his <hi>Power, Glory,</hi> and <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as it ſeemeth, for thoſe thunders, that is, for thoſe iudgements to bee executed on the world, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging that they were iuſt and right. And albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it they were ſealed vp as appeareth in the next Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet by theſe thunder-claps of Gods anger, they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150822:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> could vnderſtand that there were iudgements to come. The like is in <hi>Eſay,</hi> the ſixth Chapter, where <hi>the Angels alſo glorifie God for his iudgements.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it may ſeeme to man to be a very hard and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous thing, that God ſhould harden the hearts of the people, to the end hee may more fully expreſſe his iudgements on them, yet neuertheleſſe the Angels ceaſe not to magnifie him for the ſame: and ſo they doe here in this place.</p>
               <p>And not onely they, but <hi>the Elders &amp; the Church and Children of God,</hi> do alſo ioyn with the Angels to praiſe the Lord, as for all other his works in his Creatures, ſo alſo for his iudgements; &amp; they doe pronounce that God is worthy <hi>to haue glory</hi> in his iudgements, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom alone all fulneſſe of <hi>Honour, Glory,</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer</hi> doth belong; and therefore they themſelues <hi>fall downe,</hi> and <hi>caſt their Crownes before him,</hi> acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby, that all their glory is due vnto the Lord, and is his, as hauing receiued it by him alone, and that they themſelues are altogether vnworthy of any ſuch dignity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 5. 1</bibl>
                  <q>And I ſaw in the right hand of him that ſate vpon the Throne, a Booke written within, and on the backſide, ſealed with ſeauen Seales, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IN the former Chapter is ſet forth the perſon of <hi>God the Father</hi> in his Maieſty, as principall, from whom all things come. Here in this Chapter is ſet downe <hi>God the Sonne,</hi> the ſecond Perſon, who is Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and meane betweene God and man, of the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150822:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> of theſe iudgements to follow. Which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs, that through Chriſts interceſſion alone, all good knowledge commeth to Gods children. Firſt, in that <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>he ſaw a Booke in the right hand of him that ſate on the Throne,</hi> that is, <hi>of God the Father;</hi> by his right hand is meant his Strength, Power, and Force, whereby he ſo keepeth it, that no power whatſoeuer can winne it, or wreſt it out of his hand, nor can be partaker of it, vnleſſe hee himſelfe will giue it. This Booke <hi>is written within and without,</hi> ſignifying, that the multitude of the plagues which were to come on the world, were ſo many, that the Booke could not containe them: The ſubiect of theſe plagues, vpon whom they ſhould be executed, is the world, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Lord poure out thy wrath vpon the Gentiles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In that <hi>it is ſealed,</hi> it noteth that it is ſeparate from all men and Angels, ſo that none could attaine to the knowledge of it, but God himſelfe According to that which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh; <hi>who hath beene his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 34.</note> that is, who hath beene partaker of Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell? In the Goſpell of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> Chriſt anſwereth, <hi>The Sonne hath reuealed it, which came out of the boſome of his Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After, hee heareth the voice of a ſtrong Angell, which ſaith, <hi>Who can open the Booke? Who is worthy to do it?</hi> Which ſheweth, that the Angels themſelues ſtoope to looke into theſe iudgements, that is, haue an earneſt deſire to behold the things of the Church, and the miſteries of God concerning the ſame, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith.</p>
               <p>In that there was <hi>none found that could open the Booke,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:150822:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> no not ſo much as looke vpon it. It ſheweth that none can haue ſo much as the leaſt meaſure of knowledge thereof. Then <hi>Iohn wept, for that none was found wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy:</hi> It teacheth vs, that when wee ſee our ignorance of thoſe things which concerne vs, wee are to weepe and be grieued at the ſame, eſpecially in thoſe things which concerne our ſaluation.</p>
               <p>After, it is ſaid, <hi>one of the Elders comforted him,</hi> bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him not <hi>to weepe, for the Lyon of the Tribe of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah had performed this;</hi> ſo called, by reaſon of his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, through which hee had ouercome all lets, which might hinder the reading of it, namely <hi>ſinne,</hi> and this he had taken away by his <hi>death,</hi> and ſo had obtained this fauour at Gods hand for vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The root of Dauid:</hi> That is, the cauſe and creator of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the begetter of his faith, in regard of his God-head, as in other places hee is called the ſeed of <hi>Dauid,</hi> in regard of his man-hood, which proceeded of the linage of <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After, he is repreſented in another forme, that is to ſay, of a <hi>Lamb that had been ſlain,</hi> as it ſeemeth bloudy, which appeared in the midſt of the Throne; And he is ſaid <hi>to haue ſeauen horns, &amp; ſeauen eyes,</hi> which are the <hi>ſeauen ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> that is, <hi>the holy Ghoſt,</hi> which is his ſpirit, proceeding from him: By his <hi>eyes,</hi> meaning his infinite knowledge, wherby he ſeeth into all things; By his <hi>ſeauen hornes</hi> is ſignified his infinite power. And he commeth to his Father, &amp; <hi>taketh the Booke</hi> of his Father (to open it, and to vnlooſe the ſeales) who would giue it to none elſe.</p>
               <p>Then followes the effect of this his <hi>taking the Booke,</hi> to wit, <hi>a Song of thankeſgiuing:</hi> Firſt of the chiefe and principall Angels, who ſay, <hi>that the Lambe onely is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150822:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> worthy to receiue this honour, as to haue the Booke, and to open it.</hi> And as the foure Beaſts, being principall of the Angels, and the Archangels, begin, ſo alſo the Elders, which were the principall of the Church, doe ioyne with them in prayſing Chriſt; And after, as the chiefe of the Angels, and of the Saints, begin, ſo the reſt of the Angels follow, euen thouſand thouſands, <hi>viz.</hi> all the other Angels.</p>
               <p>And in their Song, they praiſe the <hi>Lambe,</hi> attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to him all <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Riches,</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> and <hi>Strength,</hi> which are cauſes; and then the effects thereof, <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>Praiſe,</hi> that all theſe belong vnto him. Then followeth the praiſe and thankeſgiuing of the reſt of the Church, and of all the Creatures, which praiſe, firſt, God the Father for vouchſafing to giue the Book vnto his Son, &amp; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God the Sonne for obtaining it at his fathers hands: Laſtly, the chiefe Angels, the foure and twenty El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, are brought in, ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> to the thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing of the inferiour Angels, and of the reſt of the Creatures: As they began the Chapter, ſo they as it were make an end, and anſwere to the reſt in prayſes, ſhewing vs that they neuer ceaſe continually to ſound forth the praiſes of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 6. 1</bibl>
                  <q>After, I beheld when the Lambe had opened one of the ſeales, and I heard one of the foure beaſts ſay, as it were the noyſe of thunder, Come and ſee.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HAuing heard before in the former Chapters of the preparation, to the declaring of the things to come, he now ſpeaketh of the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150822:20"/> that were to follow; and he ſpeaketh of them, as of great Miſteries.</p>
               <p>And firſt, it ſeemeth in this Chapter is ſhewed to the Apoſtle, rather a warning, what things are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall, then any declaration of the befalling of thoſe Iudgements; as the execution of the things themſelues ſet downe in the eight and ninth Chapters doe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly declare: And alſo it appeareth, becauſe in the ſeauenth Chapter, (as it is familiar with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) before the things doe come, he ſheweth matter of comfort to the Children of God, <hi>to prepare &amp; arme them</hi> againſt thoſe iudgements to be executed.</p>
               <p>So here in this Chapter is contained a denuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the iudgements to come to paſſe on the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, vnleſſe there were ſpeedy repentance; as in the next Chapter, a conſolation, <hi>to arme and ſtrengthen</hi> the godly, in that they ſhould not be touched nor hurt with theſe iudgements. And then laſt of all followeth in the eight and ninth Chapters, the declaration of the very execution of the iudgements themſelues. In that he ſaith, <hi>he heard one of the foure Beaſts ſpeaking to him as it were with the noiſe of a thunder,</hi> it ſheweth, that though it were in the ſame viſion, yet hee is faine to be raiſed vp by this mighty voice of the Angell; ſo that one ſtirring vp was not ſufficient. Which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs, that in the ſame Sermon we are often to be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp, if not by the <hi>Angell,</hi> that is, by the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> yet by our ſelues: We are as it were to renew our attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to receiue inſtruction, reproofe, correction, or any other thing which the Lord would haue vs to know.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Come and ſee:</hi> that is, attend diligently and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, with greater attention: Not onely exhorting
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150822:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> him to continuance, but alſo to heare more fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and profitably.</p>
               <p>After that the <hi>firſt Seale</hi> is opened by the Lambe Chriſt, the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, he ſaw a <hi>white horſe, and a man ſitting thereon:</hi> In that he is ſaid <hi>to ſit on a white horſe,</hi> and to haue a <hi>Crowne giuen him,</hi> it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth victory: By the <hi>Man</hi> is vnderſtood, the Miniſters of the Sonne of God, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> ſent forth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the iudgements of God to come vpon the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the neglect of the word.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid <hi>for victory,</hi> it ſignifyeth that the iudgements which they threatned, ſhould haue euent, vnleſſe they repented ſpeedily. The <hi>Bow</hi> which he hath, ſignifieth the eaſineſſe of the victory, <hi>to wit,</hi> noting that the Lord wil ouercome a farre off, becauſe men with a Bow vſe to ſtrike a farre off their enemies without any labour; euen ſo would the Lord doe in the execution of his iudgements.</p>
               <p>In the opening of the <hi>ſecond Seale,</hi> there appeareth a <hi>red Horſe,</hi> which together with the <hi>ſword</hi> that was giuen him that ſat thereon, ſignifieth the great bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed that ſhould come on the world by fighting of one nation with another, or of nations within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as oft times it commeth to paſſe.</p>
               <p>Then the <hi>third Seale</hi> is opened, whereupon appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a <hi>black Horſe,</hi> which noteth great famine to come vpon the earth, becauſe that famine vſeth to make men looke blacke, as the holy Ghoſt interpreteth, and declareth it afterward, namely, when he ſaith that the man that ſat on that Horſe <hi>had Ballances in his hand;</hi> noting, that they ſhould not eate and drinke as much as they liſted, but they ſhould haue their meate
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150822:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> and drinke giuen by meaſure, as it commeth to paſſe in the time of dearth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A meaſure of Wheate.</hi> The word vſed in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, ſignifieth ſuch a meaſure as containeth the eight part of a Strike of Corne; the price is ſaid here, ſhould be a penny, <hi>to wit,</hi> of Romane money, being between foure and fiue pence with vs, which then was the ſtipend of a dayes labour; ſignifying, that a man ſhould be conſtrained to beſtow that in bread alone, which ſhould ſerue him and his houſhold both for bread, and all other kinde of ſuſtenance; noting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the grieuouſneſſe of the dearth.</p>
               <p>Whereas it is ſaid, that <hi>they ſhould not hurt the Wine, or Oyle:</hi> It ſignifieth that it ſhould be as deare as the bread ſhould be; and therefore hee counſelleth them to take heede that they vſe it not ill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> either by miſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it waſtfully, or elſe ſelling it ouer-deare; and therfore would not haue them to ſet too great a price of it, thereby to oppreſſe the poore buyers, but that they ſhould ſell as they might, noting therby a dearth of all other things as well as of bread.</p>
               <p>After, is ſet forth the opening of the fourth Seale, where there comes <hi>a pale Horſe,</hi> noting <hi>Death,</hi> which is he that ſits vpon him, and this ſhall befall to the wicked: And Hell is ſaid to follow him (not Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory as the Papiſts dreame) ſignifying that Hell ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companieth the death of the wicked, <hi>to wit,</hi> thoſe that diſobey Gods commandements. And this death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not onely by the meanes of famine alone, and the ſword alone, as in the former Seales hath appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but by them ioyned together, and other meanes ioyned with them, as namely, <hi>the euill Beaſts.</hi> Which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150822:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> teacheth vs (as we may alſo ſee in the fourteenth of <hi>Ezechiel</hi>) that when particular afflictions profit vs<note place="margin">Ezech. 14. 13. 15. 17. 19. 21.</note> nothing at all, and when by particular iudgements we cannot be brought to repentance; then the Lord muſt needs ſend manifold iudgements; yea, hee will ioyne them all together (as in that place of <hi>Ezechiel</hi>) and he will adde more vnto them, as here he addeth the wilde beaſts vnto the famine and ſword.</p>
               <p>Afterward followeth <hi>the fift Seale,</hi> where there is no mention of any voice calling vnto him to ſtirre him vp as before, for no doubt the Apoſtle was well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to heare whatſoeuer. And here it ſeemeth, the Apoſtle rendreth a reaſon of the iudgements to come, namely, that it was by reaſon of the cry of the ſoules of the Saints which were ſlaine for the truth, on the face of the earth: And theſe hee ſaith are vnder the hollow of the Altar, which <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. is interpreted to be <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and therefore <hi>they are in the cuſtody of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Soules cry for vengeance, ſaying, <hi>How long Lord, holy and true? &amp;c.</hi> Which teacheth vs what is the exerciſe of the ſoules departed, being ſlaine for the truth, <hi>to wit,</hi> they cry for vengeance and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not that they doe it for deſire of reuenge for their owne deaths, nor hauing any regard to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and the iniuries they haue receiued, as our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, being vnregenerate, vſeth: But as their owne words declare, it is for the glory of God; which appeareth in that they call him <hi>Lord,</hi> which is, as if they ſhould ſay, as thou art Lord ouer all, ſo ſhew thy ſelfe to be, and be not Lorded by them, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt thy ſelfe to haue power ouer all, and ſhew thy ſelfe one that will repay their rebellion againſt thee.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150822:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> In that they ſay, <hi>holy and true:</hi> they deſire that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he will expreſſe himſelfe to be holy and true in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which is right concerning reuenge againſt the wicked, as hauing promiſed reuenge.</p>
               <p>In that they ſay <hi>how long!</hi> This they doe in regard of the care, not onely of themſelues, but that they haue of the oppreſſed children of God on earth. Not that there is any ſuch care that hindreth their felicity, but onely a deſire of the helpe and deliuerance of thoſe on earth, as alſo of the conſummation of their felicity. This doth not confirme that opinion of the Papiſts, that <hi>the Saints in heauen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> doe know the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular eſtate of men on the earth;</hi> but this onely they haue remaining of that generall knowledge of the will of God which they had euen before their diſſolution, which they looſe not thereby, yet they ſee no further into mens actions; then by that knowledge they did before.</p>
               <p>Now theſe are bidden <hi>to ſtay till their fellow ſeruants ſhould be accompliſhed,</hi> that is, till the number of the Elect be fulfilled and accompliſhed, and then ſhould their glory be perfected.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it is ſpoken of <hi>the ſixt Seale:</hi> therein are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained terrible things of <hi>Earth-quakes,</hi> the <hi>rowling of the heauens,</hi> the <hi>falling of the Starres like Figs from the Fig-trees when they are full ripe, the Sunne dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſheweth the execution of the vengeance of God on the wicked at the prayers of the Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. So that wee ſee that the children of God did not take it as a full execution of iudgement, vntill the laſt day, when the Sunne ſhould thus be changed, &amp;c.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150822:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> And then by reaſon of the wrath of the <hi>Lambe,</hi> the wicked ſhould be glad to hide themſelues from the ſight of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Lambe,</hi> and deſire the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to fall vpon them: where the Lord teacheth vs, that at <hi>the cry of the Children of God, all this ſhould be executed on the wicked.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 7. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>And after that, I ſaw foure Angels ſtand on the foure cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the earth, holding the foure windes of the earth, that the windes ſhould not blow on the earth, neither on the Sea, neither on any tree, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BEtweene the <hi>declaration</hi> and manner of the <hi>execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the iudgements to come on the world, as a ſnare to betrap them, here is this ſtory inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laced, containing the argument of the mercies of God in ſauing the Godly, as before in the former Chapter were ſet downe the arguments of his iudgement and iuſtice on the wicked.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith <hi>that he ſaw foure Angels holding the foure windes.</hi> They are named foure, in regard of the foure windes that they haue in charge to keepe; yet ſo to be meant as before of the foure Beaſts, <hi>to wit,</hi> a competent number for that worke.</p>
               <p>And theſe Angels hauing receiued their charge, put themſelues in array, for execution of that they had in hand: And they are ſaid <hi>to haue the windes in their hand;</hi> that is, in their power and gouernement. So that albeit the windes be a very ſubtile Creature, yet the Angels appointed to that end, haue them in their hand and power to withdraw them from doing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150822:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> any hurt, to reſtraine them from blowing on the earth on men, or on the trees themſelues, ſignifying, that there ſhould not be the leaſt winde at all, no not ſo much as would ſhake a little ſprigge of a Tree, which of all things will ſooneſt be moued by the windes: Which noteth vnto vs, what a great ſtroke and authority the Angels haue ouer the vnder-creatures. <hi>Then there was another Angell,</hi> to wit, of another manner, namely, not created, but hee which was the Angell of the couenant, being another in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his natures, both of his man-hood, as alſo of his God-head.</p>
               <p>And whereas he is ſaid to come from <hi>the riſing of the Sunne,</hi> the moſt probable interpretations ſeeme to be theſe; that either the returning againe of the Lord toward the Sanctuary, from whence hee was flitted for the ſins of the people (as appeareth in <hi>Ezechiel;</hi>)<note place="margin">Ezech. 11. 23.</note> Or elſe here is alſo ſet forth the <hi>declaration of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> that albeit the ſame be a moſt glorious crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet Chriſt comming from it could not be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed, or his glory any whit diminiſhed by the brightneſſe of the Sunne.</p>
               <p>Againe, in that <hi>hee hath the Sealt to ſeale the Elect,</hi> it ſetteth downe his office, that hee onely, as he alone, knoweth the heart, and who are elected, and none elſe, neither man nor Angell; ſo he alone Sealeth and Marketh the children of God to his Kingdome.</p>
               <p>And further, the Angels of iudgement are <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to execute iudgement vpon any, vntill the Children of God were Sealed,</hi> (the like wee haue in <hi>Ezechiel</hi> 9.) hauing as it ſeemeth, relation to the deliuerance out of <hi>Egypt, where it was commanded that there ſhould
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150822:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> be a marke ſet on the Doore-poſts of the Children of Iſrael,</hi> which when the Angell that was to ſtrike the firſt borne of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſhould ſee, he ſhould paſſe by, and not ſmite them: euen ſo here the Children of God are marked, that when the Angels ſhould goe forth to execute iudgement, they ſhould ſee and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently diſcerne the marke on them, as euidently as if it were on their Foreheads, whereby they ſhould be warned to take heed that they did not annoy them with the iudgements which were to be laide vpon the earth.</p>
               <p>After, it is ſet forth, <hi>who are thus Sealed and Marked,</hi> that they might be deliuered from this deſtruction to come vpon the earth: And theſe are either <hi>Iewes</hi> or <hi>Gentiles.</hi> And firſt of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the number is ſet down to be <hi>a hundred and foure and forty thouſand.</hi> The <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>without number.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which giueth vs to vnderſtand, that albeit this be not the perfect and full number of the <hi>Iewes</hi> which were to be ſaued, yet that their number was ſuch, as that it might be attained vnto, and numbred by men. But the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> howſoeuer with God their number was well enough knowne, yet they are ſaid to be ſo many, as that they could not be numbred by men. According as God promiſed <hi>Abraham</hi> touching his ſeede, <hi>that they ſhould be as many as the ſtarres of heauen, and as the ſands of the Sea in multitude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the particular numbring, the Tribe of <hi>Iuda</hi> is ſet firſt, becauſe of him, <hi>Chriſt</hi> the promiſed <hi>Meſſiah</hi> came.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we obſerue that the Tribe of <hi>Dan</hi> is here left out (not as the Papiſts dreame, becauſe that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſhould come from thence,) but it is partly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150822:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> becauſe it is not an vſuall cuſtome of the Scriptures in the numbring of the Tribes, to ſet downe twelue Tribes only as a fit number: But a greater reaſon ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be, becauſe (as it is in the Booke of the <hi>Iudges</hi>) the <hi>Danites</hi> did withdraw themſelues from the ſeruice of God, and from the other Tribes, and ioyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which <hi>Iacob</hi> alſo maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of in his Prophecie; And therefore in the <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles</hi> there is no mention made of <hi>Dan,</hi> but hee is left out, as one that diſabled himſelfe of that fauour to be accounted in the number of the Church of God.</p>
               <p>Here, hauing ſpoken of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which could be numbred, and of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that they were without number; he commeth to the execution of their <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king;</hi> whereby they ſhould be kept from the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be laid on the earth, and that ſo they might be reſerued vnto the Kingdome of God.</p>
               <p>They are firſt deſcribed, <hi>to ſtand before the Throne of God,</hi> that is, in his ſight, there to miniſter vnto the Lord, and to execute his will in his ſeruice; and it is the cuſtome of the Scriptures ſo to ſpeake: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Miniſters of the word are ſaid to ſtand before the ſight of God, that is, to miniſter vnto God; ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Daniel</hi> is ſaid to ſtand before the King, that is, to miniſter vnto him.</p>
               <p>In that they are ſaid to haue vpon them <hi>white robes,</hi> it noteth the royall eſtate they ſhall be in, in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Palmes in their hands,</hi> ſignifie their victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all their troubles, and ouer all their enemies and Perſecutors.</p>
               <p>After all this is ſet downe a <hi>thankeſgiuing,</hi> which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150822:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> they giue vnto God, whereby the Saints acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that ſaluation belongeth onely vnto God in deliuering them from wicked men, and from all their miſeries; wherein they confeſſe that in themſelues there is no difference betweene them and other men, but that it was the onely good-will and fauour, and mercy of God, whereby hee had choſen them, and vouchſafed them this honour.</p>
               <p>To this the Angels anſwere, and ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying alſo their conſent thereunto, that it is truely performed: and they themſelues reply with another ſong vnto God for the deliuerance of his people, and they further giue all <hi>Praiſe, Glory, Wiſedome, Honour, Thankes</hi> vnto God, which are effects of his power.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, thoſe that were Sealed, are more manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forth by a Dialogue betweene one of the <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> where the <hi>Elder</hi> is ſaid to aske <hi>Iohn</hi> firſt, <hi>What be theſe that are thus arrayed in white?</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>from whence they came?</hi> which hee doth not becauſe he himſelfe was ignorant therof, but to ſtirre vp <hi>Iohn</hi> the more to the conſideration of them. And he himſelfe anſwereth to both the queſtions: To the laſt he anſwereth firſt, according to the manner of the Scriptures, <hi>to wit, Theſe are they</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that are come out of great tribulation and afflictions;</hi> and he ſaith <hi>that theſe afflictions had not made their robes ſo white,</hi> that is, had not brought them to that honour they were in, but it was the bloud of the <hi>Lambe</hi> that brought them to it, and their <hi>robes</hi> were thus <hi>white, becauſe they were dipped in the blood of the Lambe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then hee anſwereth to the other queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> who they be, namely, <hi>Thoſe that ſtand alwaies before
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150822:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Throne;</hi> that is, in the preſence of God, to ſerue him with praiſes for euermore, being ſuch, as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from all euils, and from all teares, that is, all ſorrowes &amp; griefe ſhall be taken away; and they ſhall be led to the <hi>ſweet waters, and tender graſſe,</hi> and continually deliuered and preſerued from all perils.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 8. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>And when he had opened the ſeauenth Seale, there was ſilence in heauen about halfe an houre.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe Apoſtle S. <hi>Iohn</hi> doth recontinue his purpoſe begun in the fift Chapter, being omitted in the ſixt and ſeauenth Chapters; for theſe two Chapters were put in for the comfort of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and to preſerue them againſt the troubles after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to befall. Now he commeth to the opening of the ſeauenth <hi>Seale,</hi> whereat <hi>there was ſilence in heauen for the ſpace of halfe an houre:</hi> ſignifying, that all the Saints and Angels were amazed at the opening of it, marueiling at the Iudgements which followed it, more then at the other wonders which before were receiued, albeit they alſo were very marueilous. The like ſpeech is vſed in <hi>Iob,</hi> for when his friends com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to viſite him, ſaw what a miſerable caſe he was in, they were ſo appalled thereat, <hi>that they could not ſpeake to him for three dayes.</hi> This is to ſet forth vnto vs the wonderfulneſſe of the iudgements contained in the opening of the ſeauenth <hi>Seale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this, is a preparation vnto the Iudgement to come, vnto the ſixt Verſe, where it is ſaid, <hi>that Trumpets are giuen to the ſeauen Angels;</hi> that is, to a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150822:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> perfect and competent number, fit for ſuch a worke, and for the executing of that ſeruice ouer all the world.</p>
               <p>Then he ſpeaketh <hi>of another Angell,</hi> viz. <hi>another in nature,</hi> as being both God and man; <hi>another in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> as being the Angell of the euerlaſting Couenant: And he is ſaid <hi>to ſtand before the Altar,</hi> that is, in his office of Mediation betweene his Father and his Church. And therefore it is after ſaid, <hi>that to him was giuen ſweet Odors,</hi> that is, there was in him things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, <hi>to wit,</hi> his perfect obedience, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was an acceptable receiuing and perfuming of the praiers of the Saints vnto God. So that we ſee, that God accepteth of our prayers at the hands of Chriſt, which at ours he will not.</p>
               <p>By the <hi>Cenſor in his hand,</hi> hee alludeth to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Prieſts in the ceremoniall Law.</p>
               <p>In that hee <hi>taketh coales from the Altar, and caſteth them on the earth,</hi> it ſignifieth the denouncing of his iudgements againſt the wicked on the face of the earth; ſhewing that as he is the meanes of mercy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Godly, ſo hee is the executioner of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the wicked: At the greatneſſe of which his iudgements, there were <hi>Voices, and Thunders, and Lightnings, and Earth-quakes.</hi> Afterward followeth the execution of the iudgments, wherof foure Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets of iudgements are ſounded in this Chapter, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the foure firſt Angels. The firſt <hi>Angel</hi> blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Trumpet, &amp; then it is ſaid <hi>there was hayle, and fire, mingled with blood,</hi> and theſe did deſtroy the trees, and euery greene thing.</p>
               <p>By this he ſeemeth to allude vnto that in the ninth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150822:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> of <hi>Exodus,</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>that in one of the Plagues of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 9. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Egypt, was Haile mingled with Fire,</hi> the like is here mentioned; but in this place there is an addition <hi>of blood;</hi> noting, that all ſhould be conſumed, namely, that there ſhould not onely be a deſtruction of the <hi>trees</hi> and <hi>greene things,</hi> but <hi>of the men alſo,</hi> which came to paſſe euen among the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> for thoſe that were in the fields were conſumed by the tempeſt. After, in the ſecond place, it is ſaid that <hi>the ſecond An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell did blow his Trumpet;</hi> whereupon, there was <hi>a mountaine burning with fire caſt into the Sea,</hi> being ſet on fire by the wrath and anger of God, ſignifying the iudgements to be executed on the Earth, and then vpon the Sea: Seeming to allude to that place in the <hi>Pſalme,</hi> where the Prophet ſaith, that <hi>though the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalme 46. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Mountaines ſhould fall into the midſt of the Sea, yet I will not be remoued:</hi> And this iudgement ſhould be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted vpon the Sea, on the Fiſhes, and alſo vpon the Ships, ſo that not onely the Earth, but euen the Sea ſhould haue iudgements executed vpon them.</p>
               <p>At the blaſt of <hi>the third Trumpet,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>that a ſtarre fell from heauen into the third part of the freſh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Riuers,</hi> ſignifying Gods iudgements vpon them alſo, whereupon the third part of men died. The name of this Starre is <hi>Worme-wood,</hi> from the effect, <hi>to wit,</hi> the <hi>bitterneſſe</hi> which it ſhould cauſe in the freſh waters.</p>
               <p>Where wee ſee, albeit the certainty of the time is not knowne, nor any ſet time wherein this ſhall be effected, yet the Lord doth ſometimes poyſon and infect the Aire, ſometimes the Earth, and ſometimes the Sea and Waters; whereby infection ariſeth to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150822:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> man, and hereby it is ſaid that <hi>the third part of men ſhould dye:</hi> that is, the liues of many men ſhould be ſhortened. And theſe all ſeeme literally to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, ſauing that the <hi>Mountaine</hi> and the <hi>Starre</hi> which fell into the waters, doe ſignifie that the <hi>heauens</hi> ſhould be ſo infected, that they alſo by their infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpoſition ſhould corrupt and infect the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and thereby cauſe death to men.</p>
               <p>The fourth <hi>Angell</hi> hauing blowne his Trumpet, it is ſaid that the <hi>third part of the Sunne, of the Moone, and of the Starres was darkened,</hi> which ſeemeth to be meant of the <hi>ſpirituall darkeneſſe</hi> ſhould be vpon the Earth: For hitherto the Plagues that haue beene ſet downe, haue beene <hi>corporall,</hi> to wit, either pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the things of the nouriſhment of the bodies of men, or vpon the bodies themſelues: thoſe that follow in the reſt of this and the next Chapter, ſeeme to be vnderſtood of the ſpirituall Plagues of the ſoule, that the light thereof, in the middeſt of men, ſhould very much be darkened: for I cannot ſee how thoſe words concerning the darkening of the Sunne and Moone, and the Starres, can literally be vnderſtood, but rather by ſome Allegory, becauſe in the next Chapter, <hi>verſe</hi> 2. it is ſpoken of the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Sunne, that it was altogether darkened, noting the depriuation of all the light and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſoule. And therefore this is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the darkeneſſe of the minde, through want of knowledge, by taking away of the truth in part, as appeareth by the hiſtories; for ſince that Popery came in by meanes of Antichriſt, Sathan had won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully darkened the light of the Goſpell; yea
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150822:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> euen before Antichriſt was at his full height.</p>
               <p>Then hee ſetteth downe, that he ſaw an <hi>Angell flying through the middeſt of heauen, which cryed with a loud voice, Woe, Woe, Woe to the Inhabitants of the earth;</hi> for the plagues which were to come: for albeit thoſe that were before were grieuous, and eſpecially of the darkening of their vnderſtandings; yet theſe that were to enſue ſhould be farre more grieuous and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible. And therefore wee ſhould be ſtirred vp to a more diligent obſeruation and conſideration of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 9. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>And the fift Angell blew the Tumpet, and I ſaw a ſtarre which was fallen from heauen vnto the earth, and to him was giuen the key of the bottomleſſe pit.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe former iudgements in the Chapter going before, are eſpecially, concerning the things which appertaine to men; theſe which here follow, concerne the perſons of the men themſelues.</p>
               <p>And firſt; after the blowing of the firſt Trumpet, it is ſaid there was <hi>a Starre fallen from heauen:</hi> By <hi>Stars</hi> is meant (as the holy Ghoſt interpreteth in the firſt Chapter) the Miniſters of the Word, who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they be vpholden by the hand of God, they fall from their holineſſe of life, and integrity, wherein they ſhould liue.</p>
               <p>To this <hi>Starre is giuen power ouer the keyes of the depth,</hi> that is, of Hell; ſignifying, that to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> this power was giuen, who before were ſometimes as cleare ſtarres and ſhining lights in the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150822:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> Church of God, euen in the time of the Apoſtles, and long after, being perſecuted for the truth; yea, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them being martired: but at the length, by am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, they fell from God, and became exceeding e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. And vnto them the Lord gaue this power (not as they ſay, and arrogate to themſelues, to doe what they liſt in heauen and hell) but ſo much onely ouer hell as is granted them, as namely, in that from thence they drew out, by the procurement of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, many wretched and abhominable things, to the great offence, fall, and ouerthrow of many.</p>
               <p>To him was giuen power <hi>to draw out ſmoake from hell, as from a Furnace, ſo that the Sunne was darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereby;</hi> great darkeneſſe is cauſed ouer all the earth: As before, in the former Chapter in part, the third part of heauen being onely darkened; ſo now it is in whole and altogether darkened. And this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that great blindneſſe and ignorance which ſhould come vpon all the earth by that man of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Out of this ſmoake, <hi>there came Locuſts;</hi> ſignifying, that by reaſon of this ignorance, there ſhould ariſe in the world many Deceiuers, of diuers ſorts, which ſhould be ſent amongſt men for the puniſhment of the ſins of the earth, which ſhould deceiue them and leade them into errors; as namely, the Monkes, the Fryers, and ſuch like vermin, as it hath ſince come to paſſe, which could not haue ſo greatly preuailed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue had ſuch credit, except there had beene ſo great ignorance.</p>
               <p>They are ſet downe and expreſſed by <hi>Locuſts,</hi> in regard of the great number and multitude of them,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150822:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> comming together by troupes, as appeareth by their practiſe; whereſoeuer they be, or haue beene, for they vſe to liue in great companies together, which is yet contrary to the profeſſion of Monkes; whoſe names are giuen them of <hi>ſolitarineſſe,</hi> as wee haue ſeene in this Land, in their Abbies, Fryers, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They had power giuen them:</hi> Shewing, that by reaſon of the ſinnes of men, God in his righteous iudgement giues them power to hurt and deceiue. And yet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by comfort may ariſe vnto the children of God, that they can hurt no more then God enioynes them, <hi>for they haue power onely to hurt Men; the Corne, the Wine, and the Fruits of the earth they cannot hurt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which ſheweth, that in the time of Popery, there ſhould bee plenty of all thoſe, nothing hurt of the greene things, as of the <hi>hearbs,</hi> the <hi>graſſe,</hi> the <hi>corne, &amp;c.</hi> Which confuteth that which is commonly alledged of the Papiſts, who count their worſhip to be good, becauſe in the time of <hi>Maſsing</hi> (as they call it) all things were cheape, and there was ſo great plenty of all outward things: And indeed by this it appeareth that it muſt needs be ſo, for otherwiſe they could not haue beene ſuch as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh of heere. Againe, in that they hurt men, it is onely of thoſe that haue not receiued the Marke of God in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads: And againe, this hurt is not in regard of their liues, by taking away their liues, but this hurt they did them was in their Conſcience, by reaſon of terrour, for they were ſtung by them as with <hi>Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> in that they tooke away from them the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, leauing in them the ſting of an euill Conſcience.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150822:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Their power being thus limited, he after commeth to deſcribe the faſhion of theſe <hi>Scorpions, to wit:</hi> Firſt, <hi>that they were as Horſes prepared to battell;</hi> ſignifying, that they were altogether ready, prompt, and fit for all manner of miſchiefes they liſted, according as God vſed them in his iuſt iudgement.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>They had Crownes;</hi> ſignifying that they ſhould conquere and preuaile, and proſper in that they were ſent for, and which they went about.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>They had faces like men;</hi> noting, that they ſhould be crafty and ſubtile, to bring their deceits &amp; deluſions to paſſe, and that they ſhould be apt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe men, and lead them into errour.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Their haire like womens;</hi> ſhewing their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminateneſſe, in regard of their faces, the ſhearing of their beards, and their long haire on their heads, and eſpecially their effeminate and filthy manners, in that they were womaniſh, filthy, and vncleane, hauing no manly manners any wayes.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, <hi>Their teeth like Lyons;</hi> ſignifying, their gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe and cruelty.</p>
               <p>The time of their continuance to <hi>ſting,</hi> is <hi>fiue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths;</hi> that is, (according to the account in the ſecond Chapter, and as <hi>Daniel</hi> alſo expoundeth it, whom <hi>Iohn</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 2. 10.</note> alſo followeth in this numbring) is for the ſpace of an hundreth &amp; fifty yeares, euery day in the moneth being counted for a yeere: Which is thought to be in the time of <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> called <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeauenth, which was to begin when Sathan was let looſe, after that a thouſand yeeres after Chriſt was runne out, and which beginning then, ended in the time of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi> the ninth, in whoſe time they had gotten the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150822:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Sword, which the blaſt of the <hi>ſixt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> ſetteth forth, &amp; which the blaſt of the fourth <hi>Angel</hi> ſheweth they would not haue during the hundred and fifty yeeres, otherwiſe called fiue moneths.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They were harniſed with habergions, as of iron;</hi> noting, that by their priuiledges and prerogatiues they were ſo defenced, that none could almoſt touch them, by any occaſions; as the Biſhop muſt haue about ſixtie witneſſes againſt him, to accuſe him, otherwiſe hee is not to be conuinced; the Prieſts muſt alſo haue a great number of Accuſers, and they muſt not be iudged by any Maieſtrate of the Temporality, but by one of the Clergie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The noiſe of their wings like the noiſe of Charriots:</hi> ſignifying their great pompe, which appeareth by their ſumptuouſneſſe in riding with many Horſes, and troupes of men attending on them, which make a great noiſe and ruſhing whereſoeuer they come, ſo as euery one may heare and behold them; contrary to the practiſe of our Sauiour Chriſt, who is ſaid not to haue beene heard in the ſtreets.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is the firſt Woe, the two other woes are to come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The other Trumpet followeth to be blowne.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>And firſt, to declare the certainty of it, hee ſaith, <hi>there came a Voice from the corner of the Altar which was in the holy place, which commanded that they ſhould looſe the foure Angels:</hi> by foure, is meant a ſufficient and competent number (as before wee haue heard) to execute Gods iudgements. And theſe are ſaid to be <hi>bound in the Riuer Euphrates,</hi> which was that Riuer that runneth through <hi>Babilon,</hi> where the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were held in captiuity. And it is vſed to ſet
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150822:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> forth that ſpirituall captiuity of the Church of God, whereby the Whore of <hi>Babilon</hi> keepeth in bondage both their ſoules and alſo their bodies.</p>
               <p>Now, theſe foure Angels, the Executers and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Gods fearefull iudgements, were prepared to goe <hi>at an houre, at a day, at a moneth, at a yeare;</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their readineſſe and promptneſſe to execute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny iudgement that God ſets them about; yea, though they ſhould be ſent forth for a whole yeare long, they would be willing to doe it, declaring that they did it without wearineſſe.</p>
               <p>Their effects be farre otherwiſe then the former, for they haue authority to kill the bodies of men.</p>
               <p>This ſeemeth to bee in the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, when the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had gotten the Kings and Princes of the world, and the Emperours to aſſiſt them, and to take their part; and therefore now thoſe that would not worſhip the Beaſt, and yeeld to their ſpirituall Whoredome and Idolatry, ſhould be killed and put to death by the wicked Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, whereas before they had not power to hurt the Bodies, but only to ſting the Conſciences of men.</p>
               <p>Theſe are deſcribed <hi>to haue heads like Lyons;</hi> noting, that they were fierce and cruell. <hi>Their Tayles like Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents;</hi> ſignifying their craft. Which ſheweth, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould promote her Kingdome both by violence and alſo by their craft and ſubtilty.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, is ſet downe a concluſion, wherein is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that for all theſe fearefull iudgements, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the earth (whereas they ſhould haue feared and haue beene bettered by theſe iudgements, and learned to turne vnto God by repentance) yet they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150822:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> continued vnrepentant in their Idolatries, Murthers, Witchcrafts, and all other their abhominable wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 10. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>And I ſaw another mightie Angell come downe from heauen, cloathed with a Cloude, and the Rainbow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his head, and his face was as the Sunne, and his feet as pillars of fire, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>VVEe haue heard after the Preface of this Booke, the diuiſion of it into thoſe things already executed, and which were after to be executed. Thoſe which were to come, are either touching the iudgement of God vpon the world, or thoſe things which more eſpecially did concerne the Church. Hitherto we haue heard of the world; now, the things that more eſpecially belong to the Church, doe follow; to the which in this Chapter is (as before) a Preface, wherein the holy Ghoſt prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and fitteth the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> and in him all vs, to the diligent hearing and obſeruing of all thoſe things which concerne the Church. The whole drift of this Viſion is to giue credit to the hiſtory fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing; and this credit is drawne, firſt, from the Author of the prophecie, which is Chriſt; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly from the Inſtrument, <hi>to wit, Iohn.</hi> In the firſt part, that the thing it ſelfe might be the better eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the credit drawne from the Author is ſet forth by the glory and excellencie of him.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond part, <hi>Iohn</hi> is ſet foorth by what meanes he came to this Prophecie, and from whom
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150822:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> hee receiued it, <hi>to wit,</hi> that hee had it by commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from God the Father, and from God the Son, who commanded him to publiſh this hiſtory, which after is ſet downe in this Booke.</p>
               <p>For the firſt part, he ſaith, firſt, <hi>he ſaw another An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell,</hi> to wit, (as we haue heard before) our Sauiour Chriſt being of another nature, of other offices, and of another glory then any other Angell, as being the Angell of the Couenant, that is, hee in whoſe hand the Couenant is eſtabliſhed betwixt God and his Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Angell is ſaid to come downe from heauen, viz.</hi> not that Chriſt came downe bodily, for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſay euidently, <hi>that the heauens muſt hold him till the reſtoring of all things,</hi> that is, till the end of the world; but here it was onely repreſented vnto <hi>Iohn</hi> in a viſion: For in that wee ſay that Chriſt is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, it is not that wee tye or lincke him there (as the Papiſts charge and ſlander vs wrongfully:) for wee hold that as there is in the heauens infinit roome for him to execute his will; ſo hee hath the heauen as an incomprehenſible place, and is not tyed and kept in as it were like a Priſoner, but is at his owne pleaſure to doe what he will himſelfe: And this which wee ſay, is proued out of the word of God, in the <hi>Acts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts. 1.</note> where we are taught, <hi>that he muſt ſtay there till the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter day.</hi> So that this ſight was onely a repreſentation of the minde, wherin it was giuen to ſee Chriſt thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Strong;</hi> a proper title vnto the Lord, to be the ſtrong God, ſignifying that hee was the mighty God, and therefore this Angell is of another nature, then the other Angels.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:150822:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clad with a Cloud:</hi> that is, to ſet out the glory of our Sauiour Chriſt; euen ſo in the laſt day hee ſhall come attended vpon, &amp; compaſſed with the clouds.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Rain-bow about his head:</hi> the Rain-bow about his head, ſeemeth to expreſſe and to note vnto vs, the gracious countenance of our Sauiour Chriſt towards his Church, for the Rain-bow in the Scripture is a ſigne of the fauour of God (as it is in <hi>Geneſis</hi>) name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>in that he will neuer drowne the world againe.</hi> Or<note place="margin">Chap. 4. 3.</note> elſe to the further ſetting forth of his Glory and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie; for as before in the fourth Chapter, wee haue heard, that God the Father is deſcribed to haue had a <hi>Rain-bow</hi> about his Throne, whereby the glory of the firſt Perſon in the Trinity was repreſented; ſo that may be here noted of Chriſt, in that he is ſaid <hi>to haue a Rain-bow about his head,</hi> and therefore Chriſt is of equall glory with his Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His face as the Sunne:</hi> whereby his further glory is ſet forth in his excellent and al-ſeeing prouidence, in that as the Sunne beholdeth all the earth, ſo hee at one inſtant, and with one eye, as it were, ſeeth all things on the face of the earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He had in his hand a little Booke open:</hi> In this Booke<note place="margin">Chap. 5. 1.</note> is contained thoſe things which were to follow, and to come vpon the Church it ſelfe. As in the fift Chapter wee haue heard of a Booke in the hand of God the Father, which containeth the iudgements which were generally to fall vpon the whole world. The difference betweene this <hi>Booke</hi> and that other, is very plaine; for firſt, wee haue heard, that is ſaid to be a <hi>Booke,</hi> noting that it was of a greater vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume; <hi>this is ſaid to be a little Booke,</hi> namely, of a leſſer
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150822:31"/> volume. Againe, in that it is ſaid <hi>to be in the hand of God the Father,</hi> this is in the hand of God the Sonne. The reaſon is, for that there is a more vniuerſall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the world by God the Father, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by himſelfe alone, then betweene Chriſt and the World, as he is ioyned with the office of Mediation, which concerneth the Church. And againe, there is a more ſimple and immediate gouernement of Chriſt in his Church, then of the Father. Another diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is this, in that it is ſaid <hi>this Booke is open,</hi> the other was ſhut; which ſheweth vs, that through Chriſt onely, theſe things are made manifeſt vnto vs, for, without his mediation, all things in the will of God are hid and ſhut vp from vs, that wee cannot know them: For as the Deitie of God is conſidered in the three Perſons, wee can haue no participation of any good thing from the ſame, but as Chriſt is the Mediator betweene God and vs, all things which concerne vs are opened vnto vs; yea, the knowledge of all things wee are to know: and therefore if hee come betweene vs and God, then the things of our God ſhall be opened and reuealed vnto vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His feet like two pillars of fire;</hi> this is to ſhew his ſtrength and power. The <hi>pillars</hi> declare his ſteadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; <hi>fire</hi> ſignifieth piercing, and therefore where his power ſetteth, there it cleaueth hard. Whereby is ſet downe the incomparable vertue and power of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And whereas one foot is ſet on the Sea, and the other on the Land, it ſetteth forth vnto vs his full authoritie ouer all, and that he is in all places in regard of his Godhead.</p>
               <p>This doth not proue the being of Chriſts natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150822:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> body in many places at once, for he did not ſet his feet of his naturall body at this time on the Land and Sea, neither can it be in diuers places, for then it leeſes the nature of a body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The right foot on the Sea:</hi> This is ſaid after the vſe of the Scripture, by his <hi>right foot,</hi> meaning a greater meaſure of his ſtrength, that ſeeing the Sea is a moſt vnruly and raging creature, he ſets his right foot vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; noting vnto vs, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> as he ruleth all, ſo euen thoſe things more eſpecially which are moſt vnruly, and that which needeth moſt power, he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth moſt to the ſubduing and gouerning of it.</p>
               <p>This is to teach vs not to feare at the great rage of the troubles that are in the world, but to know according as they are more grieuous, and as they doe increaſe, ſo the Lord will ad more helpe and encreaſe his ſtrength the more, to the aſſwaging of them, and when the earth beginneth to turmoile, then will he ſet his left foot on it, and when the Sea beginneth to rage, then will he ſet his <hi>right foot</hi> vpon it. And as in generall, ſo in particular troubles we are to receiue notable comfort, for if more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſorrowes and afflictions doe aſſaile vs, yet the Lord, hauing his right foot on them all, ſhall bee quiet and ſtill with vs againe.</p>
               <p>After, he is deſcribed by his <hi>voice;</hi> whereby hee declareth his <hi>terribleneſſe,</hi> that howſoeuer otherwiſe he was deſcribed to be like a Man, yet becauſe mans voice was too weake to expreſſe the force of it, hee compares it to the <hi>voyce of a Lyon,</hi> to ſtrike the more terror and feare into our hearts. According as it is ſaid, <hi>If the Lyon roare, ſhall not the Beaſts of the field
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150822:32"/> tremble?</hi> How much more when Chriſt ſpeakes, and thunders out his iudgements, ſhall not wee which are filly Lambs (nay, not ſo much in reſpect of Chriſt as Lambs to the Lyon) be afraide? and if our Sauiour Chriſt ſhew forth the tokens of his wrath againſt ſinners, by denouncing and threatning iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt them, ſhould not wee tremble and be terrified for our ſinnes?</p>
               <p>After that he had thus extended his <hi>voice, S. Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>he heard the voices of ſeauen thunders,</hi> and thoſe not ſuch as were confuſed, but there was a diſcerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and plaine ſpeech in the voice of the thunders. Now Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> (as he was before commanded) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to write the things which were ſpoken by the thunders, is notwithſtanding <hi>bidden to Seale them vp;</hi> that is, to keepe them cloſe, as being matters of ſecrecie, for God of his good will was content to ſhew them, and make them knowne to him, for his particular comfort, which he will not haue be reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto others.</p>
               <p>Herein wee ſee how God diſpoſeth of his word, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome he reuealeth vnto his Seruants, ſome hee keepeth hid in his owne euerlaſting counſell.</p>
               <p>To teach vs, that ſeeing God hath kept many things of his to himſelfe, which he hath not reuealed vnto vs; that therefore we ſhould not diſpaire in our troubles, but ſeeing hee hath reſerued ſecret to his owne counſell, euen many things which concerne the ſpeciall good of his Church, and the ſingular comfort of his children, wee are therefore rather to be ſtirred vp by prayer, to come vnto him to intreate him that he would gouerne all things to the good of his Church.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:150822:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Againe, that is here further to be conſidered which <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh elſe-where, <hi>that wee are not able, by reaſon of our careleſneſſe and dulneſſe of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to attaine in any meaſure to the true knowledge of the meaning of this Booke;</hi> how much leſſe if greater matters had beene written downe? nay, rather wee would haue beene quite driuen backe from it: And therefore this is to teach vs to be diligent in the ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out of thoſe things he hath already ſet downe, leauing to meddle (as many fooliſhly and madly doe) with thoſe things that God hath hidden in his ſecret will; And ſeeing we are ſo backward, ſlacke, and dull in the ſeeking out of thoſe things which wee haue, wee ſhould haue beene much more careleſſe of them if all the other had beene ſet downe.</p>
               <p>After, it followeth what our Sauiour Chriſt ſaid, <hi>to wit, that hee ſwore,</hi> wherein is ſet downe, firſt the manner of taking his oath, and then the oath it ſelfe: The manner of the oath of our Sauiour Chriſt is; firſt, in his geſture, <hi>in that he lift vp his hands to heauen,</hi> which was the manner of taking an oath in thoſe times; and therefore he is here after this ſort repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: Then is ſet downe the Perſon by whom hee ſweareth, <hi>viz. by God,</hi> deſcribed by his owne nature, <hi>that he liueth for euermore;</hi> and of his effects, <hi>viz. of creation of heauen, earth, and all things therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His oath it ſelfe is this, that after thoſe things which were to be done vnder the ſeauenth <hi>Trumpet,</hi> and the ſeauenth <hi>Seale</hi> were fulfilled, <hi>there ſhould be time no more,</hi> that is, there ſhould not be diſtinction of time by the day and yeare, as we vſe now to count, according to the courſe of the Sunne and of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150822:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> This is done, firſt, for the declaring vnto vs the aſſurance of the end of the things of the world: And further, for the comfort of the children of God againſt thoſe troubles which were to be endured by them; for that ſpeedily there ſhould be an end of their troubles when that time ſhould end.</p>
               <p>In that hee ſaith <hi>the Miſteries of God declared by his Seruants and Prophets were finiſhed,</hi> he rendreth a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why God ſtayeth and commeth not ſpeedily to end the world, <hi>to wit,</hi> as for the fulfilling of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Elect, ſo alſo for the accompliſhment of his word by his Prophets, Apoſtles, and Miniſters. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt reaſon why God delaieth the conſummati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> rendreth, in that he ſaith, <hi>The Lord is patient towards vs, that none ſhould periſh</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>whom he would haue to be ſaued:</hi> ſo that we ſee it is by Gods great patience, becauſe hee would haue none loſt which belonged vnto him, but would haue them to haue the meanes of knowledge and repentance, and therefore till all that belong to Gods election be called, there ſhould be no end of the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The other reaſon why the world is not finiſhed, is here expreſſed, becauſe all theſe things which the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles haue ſpoken of, &amp; this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie eſpecially, which was deliuered to <hi>Iohn,</hi> is not yet fulfilled, <hi>for one iot or title of the word of God ſhal not fal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the deſcription of Chriſt, hee comes to the calling of himſelfe, that it might be more ſurely ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and confirmed to vs, and that ſo wee might be more aſſured of the certainty of his Prophecie. And to this his calling, there commeth a double authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>to wit,</hi> of God the Father, which was before
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150822:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> deſcribed in the fourth Chapter, and hee is here brought in, bidding <hi>Iohn</hi> to goe to the Angell, and to take the Booke at him.</p>
               <p>Whereby we haue to vnderſtand, that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are taught to haue authority and warrant from God, and out of the word of God, for all thoſe things they doe, eſpecially which concerne the matters and holy things of God.</p>
               <p>This then <hi>Iohn</hi> doth, for he preſently goeth to take the Booke; and when he commeth to the Angell, <hi>hee alſo bids him take the Booke,</hi> hauing thereby a double warrant, not onely of the Father, but euen of the Sonne alſo.</p>
               <p>The Angell bids him <hi>eate it vp:</hi> meaning, that he ſhould ſettle it as it were in his belly, and euen let it ſettle into the very bottome of his heart, and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he ſhould rightly conceiue it, and that hee ſhould haue a full capacity and perfect comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the things herein contained, by hauing a ſound knowledge of the things to be reuealed, and, therefore, that he ſhould with diligence obſerue and marke them. The like thing we haue in <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> who<note place="margin">Ezech. 3. 23.</note> is alſo bidden to <hi>eate a Booke, giuen him by an Angell:</hi> But whereas it is here ſaid, <hi>it ſhould be bitter in his bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſweet in his mouth;</hi> one of theſe onely is ſet downe in <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> namely, <hi>the ſweetneſſe of it in his mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereby the Lord ſeemeth to ſet forth that this Prophecie, as it was bitter to the Apoſtle, who was the Miniſter of it, in regard of the iudgements there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained; ſo it ſhould be alſo ſweet vnto him to deliuer it, as it is expounded in the words following
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150822:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the next Verſe, <hi>whereas hee muſt Prophecie againe among People and Nations, &amp;c.</hi> ſignifying, that hee ſhould not be able to hold it in his belly, that is, to keepe it in, but haue a care and delight alſo to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it, and to deliuer it faithfully, and in that regard it ſhould be ſweet vnto his mouth; for, howſoeuer the things themſelues were ſad and heauy and vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uory to deliuer, yet in regard that God bids him to ſpeake it, he muſt take delight to doe the will of God in the deliuery thereof.</p>
               <p>Here is ſet out the duty of the Miniſters in this caſe, that howſoeuer the denouncing of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God againſt the people be very grieuous and ſorrowfull vnto them, yet they are not to ſpare to deliuer them faithfully, bouldly, and cheerefully, if the Lord command them: And indeed it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, that they ſhould feele the calamities and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of others, and therefore ſhould be grieued at Gods iudgements againſt others, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Who is offended, and I burne not?</hi> Euen ſo ſhould the Children of God haue compaſſion and a fellow-fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the miſeries of their Brethren, but the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters eſpecially; becauſe as all, ſo eſpecially the Miniſters are oftentimes intereſſed in the ſame troubles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:150822:35"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>Then was giuen me a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> vnto a Rodde, and the Angell ſtood by, ſaying, Riſe and mete the Temple of God, and the Altar, and them that worſhip there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>WEe haue heard in the former Chapter, the preparation to the Prophecie, concerning the things that ſhould befall vnto the Church. Now he commeth to the Prophecie it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>And firſt hee ſaith, <hi>there was giuen to him a Reede, and with it, hee was bidden to meaſure the Temple:</hi> Whereas, we are firſt to conſider, that by this ſpeech (borrowed from the fortieth of <hi>Ezechiel</hi>) the Lord ſetteth downe a determination to ſet forth and to meaſure out his Church: For as Arch-builders, firſt in building haue a draught in their heads and after draw it out, and meaſure the place where they build, and then haue inferiour builders to finiſh it; euen ſo the Lord doth both in that place of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo here: For there the Lord after the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and of the Temple, when hee would haue it reſtored againe, ſheweth vnto the Prophet <hi>the meaſuring of it;</hi> ſignifying that the Temple ſhould be re-edified, and that the people ſhould worſhip a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the ſame. And in like manner in this place, whereas now indeed <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and that Temple which was in it, were ready to be deſtroyed and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne; the Lord notwithſtanding bids the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>to take a ſtrait and ſmooth Reede like vnto a Rod,</hi> to wit, fit for that purpoſe, <hi>and to meaſure the Temple
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150822:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> therewithall.</hi> Noting, that albeit <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhould bee laide waſte, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> gather to himſelfe a Church, and that by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And whereas he bids him <hi>meaſure it with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> he meaneth that hee ſhould vnderſtand and comprehend the right and full way whereby the Church of God ſhould be builded. This teachth vs that vnleſſe God preſcribe and giue vnto the Miniſters, the order and manner of building his Church, they are not of themſelues to vndertake the building of the ſame. And againe, vnleſſe he put the <hi>meaſure,</hi> which he appointeth (that is his Word) into their hands, they cannot, neither ought they in any caſe to begin, and therefore not to vndergoe that function, vnleſſe they be called of the Lord. And further being called they muſt build with that <hi>meaſure</hi> and meanes onely which God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth and ſetteth downe. Hee biddeth him to <hi>meaſure the Temple, the Altar, and the Worſhippers, but to let alone the outward Court, and to caſt it out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where the Lord alludeth to the building of the Ceremoniall Temple, in the building of the Church after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the Goſpell. For firſt there was the <hi>outward Court,</hi> being the greater part which ſhould bee caſt out, and then the <hi>Temple, the inner place where the people were, and the Altar, and the holy place, and the holyeſt of all,</hi> which were very ſmall in compariſon of the others: So likewiſe in the Church, the ſmaller number ſhould be referred, the greater number ſhould fall away.</p>
               <p>So that here he is bidden to take <hi>meaſure of the Temple,</hi> and not onely of it, but of the <hi>worſhippers which were in it,</hi> to wit, <hi>of the members of the Church of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150822:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> God:</hi> Which teacheth that the Miniſters are not onely to regard the Church in generall; but alſo to haue a care of the good of euery particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Church.</p>
               <p>By <hi>the altar,</hi> is meant all the meanes ſeruing to the furthering of the <hi>ſeruice and worſhip of God:</hi> whereof a ſpeciall regard is alſo to bee had in the building of the Church.</p>
               <p>In that the <hi>great Court is not meaſured,</hi> but eaſt out to be troden of wicked and prophane men, and the Temple only, &amp; that which was in the midſt of it left, being but a very little in compariſon of the outmoſt Court, it noteth the narrow roome the Church ſhould bee comprehended in, and the ſmall number to be gathered in regard of thoſe which ſhould be caſt out; For, the <hi>Temple</hi> and the <hi>Altar,</hi> in regard of the <hi>great Court,</hi> were as it were the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in regard of a great Circle. Which teacheth vs how great a number ſhould be bandoned from God, and from the ſeruice of God, and how few and ſmall a number ſaued.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Apoſtle is bidden onely to <hi>meddle with the Temple, and not with the outward Court, but to caſt it out:</hi> This agreeth firſt with that doctrine of <hi>Paul, 1 Cor.</hi> 5. 12. Where he ſaith, <hi>What haue we to doe with thoſe that are without? We are to haue reſpect to thoſe that are within.</hi> So that here wee are to obſerue this point, that the Miniſters are firſt and principally to attend vpon thoſe diligently &amp; carefully which are committed to their charge, and to endeauour and exerciſe themſelues onely in thoſe things which God hath enioyned them. Secondly, concerning
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150822:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> thoſe things whereof they haue receiued no charge from God, they are not in any caſe to meddle in them, nor to deale at all with them. Which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth the ſinne which now adayes is vſual, when they will take vpon them thoſe offices which God hath not appointed them, and which they are not able to performe.</p>
               <p>The outward Court is to be caſt out, to be tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder foot of the Gentiles, for the ſpace of forty two moneths, whereof we haue heard the meaning, both as it is vſed by <hi>Iohn,</hi> and expounded by <hi>Daniel, viz.</hi> to be one thouſand two hundred and ſixty yeeres, for a day is referred to a yeere; a weeke of dayes is ſeauen yeares: ſo that hereby it appeareth, that the time of this great hauocke of the Church was to continue one thouſand two hundred and ſixty yeeres: Which as by account that falleth out, appeareth to begin after the aſſention of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt,</hi> when the Apoſtles began to preach, &amp; counting from that time, it ſhall appeare by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable times that befell afterward vnto the Church of God, in that ſpace, namely, when the beaſts that roſe vp out of the earth, ſet vpon the people and Church of God, and perſecuted and oppreſſed them grieuouſly.</p>
               <p>Here alſo in regard of the ſmall number to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, we may eaſily vnderſtand how vaine a thing the Papiſts brag of, when they brag of their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallity and multitude, for we ſee here that the great Court, that is, the multitude onely, <hi>is caſt out</hi> to the wicked and prophane men, and the <hi>Temple</hi> with the <hi>worſhipers</hi> onely, and the <hi>Altar,</hi> noting a ſmall number, is reſerued.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:150822:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Againe, in regard of the circumſtance of time: in that it is ſaid, that <hi>the wicked ſhould preuaile for the ſpace of one thouſand two hundred and ſixty yeares:</hi> we are to obſerue againſt them, that whereas they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect againſt vs, and ſay, that this new Goſpell of ours began in the time of <hi>Luther,</hi> or <hi>Wickliffe,</hi> we anſwere that it appeareth manifeſtly out of this place, that there ſhould be a maruellous contempt of the Word from the Apoſtles time, vntill theſe one thouſand two hundred and ſixty yeeres were expired.</p>
               <p>Now for the further declaration of this, it is ſaid, the <hi>Lord raiſed vp two witneſſes in theſe yeeres,</hi> betweene the Apoſtles time, and the time expreſſed, to preach the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>By the number of two, may be meant (not to preiudice better expoſitions) the ſmall number of faithfull witneſſes, yet ſuch a number as ſhould be able to proue any cauſe, ſufficient for the teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any truth, or ouerthrowing any falſehood, &amp; though they ſeemed to be but two, that is, a few in number, yet they ſhould be able enough for that purpoſe, and ſufficient to conuince them of their wickedneſſe, and to beare witneſſe of the truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In ſackcloth;</hi> meaning that they ſhould be heauy, ſorrowfull, and grieued at the troubles, ſtrife, and hard-dealing which they ſhould haue at the hands of the wicked, which would not yeelde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the truth: lamenting alſo for that they had no better ſucceſſe of their Miniſtery: and further by reaſon of the pride of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> when as they did behold how many euen of thoſe which ſhould haue
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150822:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> beene the ſtarres of the Church, and faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, did ſtriue and heaue for preheminence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any care of Gods Church, as it was in the daies of <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7. and <hi>Gregory</hi> the 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe are the two Oliue trees, and the two Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes;</hi> A ſpeech borrowed from the Prophet <hi>zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> where it is ſaid, that being returned from capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, the Lord gaue them Miniſters, which as <hi>O liues ſhould Miniſter Oyle for the light of the Church:</hi> Euen ſo in the wretched &amp; curſed dayes, albeit the Church of God waxed fewer and fewer, yet there ſhould be ſome <hi>Oliue trees</hi> to giue <hi>Oliues,</hi> that is, ſome Miniſters to preach peace vnto the children of God, the <hi>Oliue</hi> being a ſigne of peace, as alſo to drop in <hi>Oyle</hi> (as <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> ſaith) into the <hi>Candleſticks,</hi> alluding to the vſe of the <hi>Candleſticks</hi> in the Temple, which hauing <hi>Oyle</hi> put in them, did giue <hi>light</hi> in the Temple, burning before the Lord continually: euen ſo he ſaith, that euen in thoſe dark times, there ſhould notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding be ſome which ſhould be able to giue <hi>light</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, by the Miniſtery of the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>Afterward it is ſaid that theſe two Prophets, that is, this little number of Miniſters, ſhould haue <hi>fire goe out of their mouthes, whereby they ſhould deuoure all their enemies:</hi> Which ſheweth vnto vs the power of the Word of God, which is like a <hi>fire,</hi> by the <hi>light</hi> wherof, the godly ſhould be enlightned, by the heat whereof, the <hi>wicked ſhould be conſumed,</hi> ſo that ſith they would not be enlightned by it to their ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it ſhould ſend them to the darknes of hel, to their deeper condemnation. So that here we ſee the Word hath a contrary effect, in regard of the godly and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150822:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> the wicked. And therefore it is compared in the firſt Chapter, to a <hi>two edged Sword,</hi> which on the one ſide cutteth and healeth to life, and on the other ſide, woundeth and killeth to death: According as the Apoſtle ſaith in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians, We are the ſauour of God vnto your ſaluation that beleeue, vnto others vnto condemnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By this deuouring then of their enemies;</hi> is meant the deſtroying and conuincing of thoſe that would not yeeld vnto their preaching, to their further deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and deeper condemnation. Where wee ſee, that the Prophet here ſetteth forth, that howſoeuer the Miniſters of God ſhould haue great ſtrife in thoſe dayes, and grieuous enemies, yet they ſhould not preuaile againſt the truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe ſhould haue power to ſhut the heauens, to make the heauens braſſe, that it ſhould not raine in the dayes of their Prophecie, to reſtraine the fruit of the earth, to turne the waters into bloud, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where hee alludeth, partly to the Miniſtery of <hi>Elias,</hi> at whoſe prayer, <hi>the earth was barren, and there</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Kings 17.</note> 
                  <hi>was no raine for the ſpace of three yeares.</hi> And partly to the Miniſtery of <hi>Moſes, who brought bloud in al the land</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 7. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>of</hi> Egypt, <hi>by turning the water into bloud:</hi> ſignifying, that where the Miniſtery of the word, in the denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of iudgements was contemned, there the Lord would ſend Plagues and Peſtilence, and Flouds, and ſuch like vpon them.</p>
               <p>In that which remaineth of the ſixt Plague, there is firſt ſet forth, that the two Prophets, theſe two <hi>Oliues</hi> and <hi>Vines</hi> ſhould make an end of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, <hi>and the Beaſt ſhould ouercome them.</hi> Before it was
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150822:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaid, <hi>that at their pleaſure, and at their owne liking, they ouercame others, and reſtrained the dewe of heauen,</hi> and did execute and bring to paſſe whatſoeuer they had to doe, by the direction, by the word and will of God: Here now it is ſaid, that after the accompliſhing of their worke, and finiſhing of their teſtimony, <hi>the Beaſt ouercommeth them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To teach vs, that the Lord doth ſo maintaine his Miniſters and ſeruants, that vntill they haue finiſhed and accompliſhed the worke of their Miniſtery, which he hath appointed them to execute, they ſhall not be hurt by Sathan or any of his Miniſters, or wicked Inſtruments.</p>
               <p>Which may be a ſingular comfort to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and children of God, that howſoeuer they be hated of many men in the world, yet they ſhall haue no power to hurt them, till the time God hath limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them be expired. And here wee are alſo to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that in regard of their Miniſtery, theſe two Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did ouercome; but in regard of their liues one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are ouercome; herein had their enemies leaue to hurt them, they were able to doe nothing elſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
               <p>The time of this, appeareth by limitation of this one thouſand two hundred and ſixty yeares, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall about the dayes of <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight, who was a wretched and cruell perſecuter of the Saints of God; for by the account of the hiſtory it ſelfe, it fals iuſtly on the one thouſand two hundred and ſixty yeare after Chriſt; the very yeare of that Beaſt, <hi>Boniface,</hi> who after he had killed the Saints of God, would not ſuffer their bodies to be buried; which thing, the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150822:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> hiſtory particularly witneſſeth, making mention, that the bodies alſo of the Saints were carried about the City of <hi>Rome</hi> in triumph, and might not be ſuffered to be buried.</p>
               <p>After, it is ſaid that the wicked ones, in the token of their ioy, make great feaſts, and ſent preſents one to another; which manner of ſpeech ſeemeth to bee taken from the Booke of <hi>Heſter,</hi> wherein comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement is giuen, that for their victory and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, a Feaſt ſhould be celebrated for euer. And of this alſo the hiſtory maketh mention, that in regard of their ioy and gladneſſe for the deſtruction and death of Gods Seruants and faithfull Martyrs, there was a Feaſt of Iubily celebrated, which afterward they continued; wherein alſo as much as in them lay, they did annihilate the comming of Chriſt, who gaue an end of all theſe ceremonies.</p>
               <p>And this is ſaid to be done in the great City, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually called <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where the Lord was crucified, whereby the Apoſtle moſt plainely deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth <hi>Rome,</hi> as being the greateſt City then in the world, there being none at that time for fame and greatneſſe to be compared to it.</p>
               <p>In that it is called <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> it is ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as he ſaith) to be vnderſtood: It is called <hi>Sodome,</hi> in regard of the filthineſſe and abhominations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; by reaſon of their Sodomitrie, their whoredomes, and abhominable vncleannes of men with men, and all manner of all other ſuch like wretchedneſſes. <hi>Egypt,</hi> in regard of the perſecutions of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, alluding to the perſecutions whereby the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians</hi> kept the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in bondage. The
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150822:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> place where Chriſt was Crucified, <hi>to wit, Ieruſalem,</hi> ſo called and attributed to <hi>Rome,</hi> in that <hi>Rome</hi> brags of it ſelfe, as <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> did, to be the moſt excellent profeſſor of Chriſts religion; the onely <hi>Sion,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> and beloued of the Lord; albeit indeed it be nothing leſſe; nay, it is rather hated of God, as <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> was, crucifying the <hi>Lord Ieſus:</hi> So that theſe things doe notably agree with <hi>Rome,</hi> the great City, that Sodomiticall perſecuting Church, yet preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to be the true Church of God.</p>
               <p>After, it is ſaid, <hi>that their bodies lying three dayes and an halfe,</hi> that is, three yeares and a halfe vnburied, that is, a mocking-ſtocke, and triumphed-ouer by the wicked, they are <hi>then raiſed vp by the Lord,</hi> to wit, not thoſe that were ſlaine, but others in their ſpirit. As <hi>Iohn</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>Elias,</hi> becauſe he came in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Elias,</hi> as it is ſaid, <hi>to wit,</hi> with the ſame bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and zeale that <hi>Elias</hi> did.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They are taken into heauen:</hi> that is, ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the reſt of the Sonnes of men, which were wicked and worſhipped the Beaſt, going into ſuch places where they might ſerue the Lord.</p>
               <p>Then followeth immediately, <hi>a fearefull Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,</hi> by which, <hi>the great City was ſhaken, and the tenth part of it ouerthrowne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond <hi>Woe</hi> being paſt, the third inſueth, which followeth after the blaſt of the next Agell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The laſt Angell blew the Trumpet,</hi> which ſhall be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled at the diſſolution of the world in the latter day, when all ſhall be raiſed from the dead, when all the Kingdomes of the world are committed into the hands of Chriſt, &amp; then ſhall be the accompliſhment
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150822:40"/> of his Kingdome, when hee ſhall giue reward vnto his ſeruants the Prophets, to his Saints, and to all that feare his name, and ſhall render deſtruction vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his enemies; and then ſhall hee giue vp his power vnto his father, and God ſhall be all in all. And after this, <hi>there ſhall be time no more: Then we ſhall haue Sunne no more,</hi> that is, we ſhall haue no neede of the Sunne, the time ſhall not be diſtinguiſhed by it, we ſhall not be directed by the light of it, for God himſelfe ſhall be our Sunne, God ſhall be our light for euermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 12. l.</bibl>
                  <q>And there appeared a great wonder in heauen: A wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man cloathed with the Sunne, and the Moone was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her feete, and vpon her head a crowne of twelue Starres, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HEre in this Chapter is ſet downe a deſcription of the Church, of which it is ſaid, <hi>there was a great ſigne:</hi> noting the great eſtimation that God hath of his Church; which his great eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, is ſet forth, in that ſhee is ſaid <hi>to be cloathed with the Sunne,</hi> which is the moſt glorious creature, declaring and expreſſing her exceeding glory in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shee had the Moone vnder her feete:</hi> ſignifying her rule and authority ouer all the things below that are ſubiect to change, in that ſhe onely hath receiued of God power to ſubdue them, and ſhee doth of right poſſeſſe them; the wicked are vſurpers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vpon her head ſhee had a Crowne of twelue Starres:</hi> ſhewing her Queenely Maieſtie, ſhee being the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150822:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> Spouſe of Chriſt, as alſo her victory ouer all her ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, <hi>ſhee trauelled:</hi> her trauell is meant of the Church of the <hi>Iewes;</hi> of whom this is teſtified in the Euangeliſts, the 9. of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, how great reſiſtance there was againſt our Sauiour Chriſt, againſt the Apoſtles &amp; the reſt, what great and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous perſecutions they then ſuſtained for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell-ſake, in the beginning of the primitiue Church, becauſe they went about to beget, to bring, and to draw Children vnto God out of the ſeede of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Afterward, another great wonder is ſeene, <hi>to wit, a great Dragon;</hi> namely, the Diuell, compared to a Dragon, and called the great Dragon, becauſe of his great ſtrength, and exceeding fierceneſſe; for ſuch is the ſtrenght of a Dragon, as that he is able to gripe with an Elephant.</p>
               <p>He is deſcribed to haue <hi>ſeauen heads and ten hornes;</hi> by ſeauen <hi>heads</hi> noting his great wiſedome, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and vnderſtanding of things; as alſo it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his wit, and ſubtiltie to reſiſt the Church, and to make more miſchiefe againſt the ſeauen Churches, that is, all the Churches of God: And his <hi>tenne hornes</hi> ſignifieth his will and power to doe much hurt to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Crownes</hi> ſignifie his victory, in preuailing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the world, <hi>to wit,</hi> ouer thoſe whom God hath not ordained to ſaue, whoſe names are not written in the Booke of life, and for this cauſe he is called the <hi>Prince of the world,</hi> becauſe he hath the greater part of the world vnder his obedience.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:150822:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>What his tayle he ouerthroweth many Starres;</hi> noting, that there are many like vnto Starres in outward ſhew, being graced with notable gifts, and being as it were lifted vp to heauen by the knowledge they had, and the notable profeſſion they made of God, hauing ſome feeling alſo, being yet not Sealed, are by the <hi>tayle of the Dragon,</hi> that is, by ſmall power and light temptations, pulled backe from the ſame, and fall from the faith.</p>
               <p>After, he ſaith, <hi>He ſtood before the Woman;</hi> noting, that he ſetteth himſelfe very fiercely and ſharpely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>woman,</hi> that is, the Church and Children of God, whoſe names were written in the Booke of life: And therefore hee is ſaid to <hi>wait on the woman,</hi> firſt, to hinder her that ſhee ſhould not bring forth, and then to deuoure them at the leaſt when they were brought forth, that is, when they haue beene called, and made profeſſion of the truth, and are made members of Chriſt by faith; euen then is hee ready moſt ſtrongly to aſſault them, to ouerthrow, if it were poſſible, the foundation of their faith. Where hee compareth the Diuell to an <hi>enuious Mid-wife,</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him to a good Mid-wife; for as ſhe is carefull to helpe the woman in trauell, and to ſaue the Childe; ſo the Diuell contrariwiſe is ready to hinder and hurt the Church, and to deſtroy her ſeede.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Church is ſaid <hi>to bring forth a Man-Childe;</hi> it is firſt meant of Chriſt, and then of his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and ſeruants in the beginning of the Church, whom now hee hath ioyned vnto him in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but principally it is to be vnderſtood of Chriſt, that valiant one, who albeit hee was ſtung on the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150822:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> Croſſe by the Serpent, yet euen thereby hee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came, and after was taken vp to heauen, and had victory, triumphing ouer the diuell, ouer ſinne, and ouer all his enemies, and the enemies of the Church.</p>
               <p>Then it is ſaid, <hi>there was a battell in heauen;</hi> by <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> he meaneth the militant Church of God, vnder the Goſpell, which is the part of Gods kingdome, for the kingdome of God which is begun euen in earth. The principall in this battell is firſt <hi>Michael,</hi> to wit, Chriſt, and with him his Angels; namely, the godly Saints, with the good Angels on the one ſide, and on the other ſide, the Dragon with his Angels; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the wicked ſpirits and wicked men. But the godly ouercome the Dragon and his Angels: the meanes whereby they ouercome, is through the bloud of the <hi>Lambe,</hi> which is their principall armour; being ſuch, as that albeit they themſelues were killed, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding by reaſon hereof, they were made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours, and were now receiued into the kingdome of heauen, and Sathan is throwne out of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Which thing when Sathan ſaw, as namely, that now he had loſt all his aduantage, as it were, and that hee could haue nought to doe with them any more, they being now triumphing in the kingdome of God, hee waxeth mad as it were, and rageth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the earth more fiercely then before.</p>
               <p>And hereupon, the Elders, and the reſt of Gods Children in heauen are brought in, reioycing at this victory, and ſaying, <hi>peace in the heauen;</hi> that is, to the Children of God, that were then deliuered, but <hi>woe to the earth;</hi> that is, to the inhabitants of the earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that they ſhould haue much to doe, and ſuffer
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150822:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> great trouble, for ſeeing Sathan by the conſtant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during of thoſe that had giuen their liues in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>truth,</hi> perceiued that hee had got ſuch a foile, he therefore rageth againſt thoſe that remaine, and for this cauſe it is ſaid, <hi>woe to them on the earth;</hi> not that they ſhould periſh, but onely ſhould bee greatly afflicted through the malice of Sathan and his inſtruments.</p>
               <p>Now then it is ſaid, <hi>that hee perſecuted the woman;</hi> that is, the Church: in perſecuting the Church, ſhe hath a place appointed her in the Wilderneſſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe flyeth for one thouſand two hundred and ſixty dayes, the time we haue heard before to haue beene during the ſpace of the hard dealing with the two Prophets, wherein they prophecied which wee ſhewed to containe ſo many yeares.</p>
               <p>By this flight of the woman into the Wilderneſſe for one thouſand two hundred and ſixty dayes, ſet downe in the ſixt verſe, and the perſecution where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Dragon purſued her that ſpace, is meant thoſe perſecutions in generall which followed againſt the whole Church during the continuance of thoſe yeares, which in the next verſes hee ſetteth downe particularly and ſeuerally.</p>
               <p>And firſt he ſetteth downe the particular perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church of the <hi>Iewes</hi> in the thirteenth and fourteenth verſes, and then of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteenth Verſe. For the Church of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the perſecution thereof is expreſſed in that it is ſaid, that he perſecuted <hi>her that brought forth the man-childe,</hi> but the Lord deliuered her from being deuoured of the Dragon.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:150822:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>In that it is ſaid, <hi>ſhe being thus purſued, hath for her deliuerance, wings giuen her to flye away into a Deſert for two times, a time, and halfe a time;</hi> it notably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth that ſtrange deliuerance of the Children of God which were in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> before the ouerthrow of it, who (as the ſtory witneſſeth) being warned by the voice of God from heauen, did withdraw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for a time into a City called <hi>Pella</hi> beyond <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> in the Wilderneſſe, where they did continue for the ſpace of three yeares and a halfe, vntill <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> were deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>Whereas the <hi>Dragon is ſaid to caſt out waters againſt the Church,</hi> it noteth the great multitudes of people, for ſo it is often vſed in the Scriptures, (as alſo after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards)<note place="margin">Cap. 17. 1. 15.</note> which afterwards the Diuell raiſed vp to deuoure and conſume the Church of Chriſt in the infancie of it. But in that the <hi>earth</hi> is ſaid to helpe the <hi>woman,</hi> it noteth, that howſoeuer the Lord ſuffereth the Diuell to raiſe and ſtirre vp many enemies and aduerſaries againſt his Church, yet alſo hee hath his meanes for the deliuerance of his children by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of their enemies, deſtroying them in the middeſt of their fury, and caſting them into their graues.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, the Dragon hauing done the worſt he could againſt the Church of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> againſt Chriſt himſelfe, his Apoſtles and Diſciples, he followeth and proceedeth with mortall enuie and indignation to purſue their ſeed, that is, the Church of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who were called by their miniſtery, and are alſo of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> though not according to the fleſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:150822:43"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 13. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>And I ſaw a Beaſt riſe out of the Sea, hauing ſeauen heads, and tenne hornes, and vpon his hornes were tenne crownes, and vpon his heads the name of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe Prophet hauing ſpoken before, that the ſeed of the <hi>woman,</hi> to wit, the Church of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> was perſecuted of the Dragon: hee now declares the manner and meanes of the perſecutions and the troubles which befall the Church. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall cauſe is here ſet out to be the Beaſt, which is the Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> who is ſet forth by him, comming out of the Sea; whereby is meant the great ſtormes, troubles, and tempeſts that the Beaſt ſhould raiſe vp: By which tempeſts, are expreſſed and meant the great tumults which ſhould ariſe both betweene the wicked themſelues, as it came to paſſe in the Empire of <hi>Rome,</hi> for they had amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues many and long warres, and grieuous troubles and diſſentions, as appeareth in the hiſtories; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it noteth the troubles and afflictions, which the Church ſhould receiue by them, for the Church muſt needs be partaker of this miſery (though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture it be not immediately alwaies tended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them) yet they liuing vnder the Empire where theſe troubles were principally, could not but needs alſo feele the ſmart thereof. Afterwards the troubles are alſo immediately directed againſt the godly them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, particularly by the ſword, by fire, and by ſore perſecutions, which are declared to ariſe and come from the Beaſt.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:150822:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>A <hi>Beaſt,</hi> ſo he is tearmed, being here deſcribed and repreſented vnder the forme of a Beaſt, becauſe of the furiouſneſſe and madneſſe of the Empire of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Emperors; ſignifying that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing almoſt of humanity in him, but that hee was euen eſtranged from all courteſies of men.</p>
               <p>Secondly, hee is more particularly noted, what manner of Beaſt he was like vnto, <hi>to wit,</hi> he was like a <hi>Leopard;</hi> noting his marueilous ſwiftneſſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to doe miſchiefe to the Church, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it; as alſo ſhewing his cruelty towards the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Pawes of a Beare;</hi> noting his rauenouſneſſe, as being ready, ſo, able to catch, to apprehend and lay hold of the things he deſired.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The mouth of a Lyon;</hi> ſhewing that he was cruell and ſtrong to deuoure and to deſtroy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He had the power of the Dragon giuen him;</hi> that is, of the Diuell, ſignifying the greatneſſe of his crueltie, for (as it is in the twentieth Chapter) the Lord that he might ſaue his people, being now in their cradle, from being ouer-runne and deuoured of Sathan, had firſt ſhut vp the Diuell into the bottomleſſe pit, that hee might not practiſe that hee would againſt the Church, which thing the Diuell perceiuing, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe thus ſhut vp, that as it were in his owne perſon, hee could not as hee deſired be employed in the deuouring of the Church at his pleaſure, hee caſts as much of his owne power as he can vpon an other, <hi>to wit,</hi> vpon the <hi>Romane Emperour,</hi> who was as it were, his deputy, to the end he might doe that iniury he could, in proſecuting the Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:150822:44"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seauen heads;</hi> ſignifying his exceeding wiſedome and pollicie to doe hurt, which ſhould be very great, according to his authority, whereby hee ruled ouer the whole world. His <hi>hornes</hi> ſignifie his power to doe that hurt: And his <hi>Crownes</hi> ſignifie that great effect which that great wit and power of his ſhould take, in preuailing againſt men, <hi>to wit,</hi> that hee ſhould vanquiſh and ouercome in his miſchiefes: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there is great difference betweene his <hi>Crownes</hi> and the Dragons, for the Dragon had them on his heads; that is, the Diuell hath this power of himſelfe properly to doe hurt, exerciſing it as from himſelfe: the Beaſt hath them vpon his <hi>hornes,</hi> that is, the Emperour doth not exerciſe his authoritie and power againſt the Church immediately from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but doth borrow his power from the Dragon. Which is ſpoken after the cuſtome and manner of thoſe Kings and Princes, which hauing abſolute au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, weare their Crownes on their bare heads, thoſe that be Viceroyes, and haue an abſolute autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, weare Coronets indeed but on their Caps, as it is vſed in forraine Countries, and as it was the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in thoſe dayes.</p>
               <p>After, he is ſaid to haue the name of <hi>Blaſphemie,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, that the Emperours ſhould be ſuch as ſhould blaſpheme God, in calling themſelues Gods, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the worſhip of God vnto themſelues, as <hi>Caligu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> and others moſt wretchedly and blaſphemouſly did, like to <hi>Alexander</hi> the great in the Monarchy of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> which did arrogate this title to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to be called God.</p>
               <p>In that hee ſaith, <hi>he had vpon his head the name of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150822:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> blaſphemy written;</hi> hee oppoſeth to that contrary cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Prieſt, who had written vpon his head, <hi>honor to the Lord;</hi> ſo contrariwiſe, this Beaſt had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on his head <hi>blaſphemy againſt God.</hi> And hee did not onely blaſpheme the name of God, but alſo his Tabernacle, that is, did ſpeake euill of the Church of God, and contemned it. And whereas it is ſaid, he <hi>blaſphemed thoſe that dwell in heauen;</hi> it noteth, that not onely in generall hee did ſpeake euill of Gods Church, but he did euen maligne the particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which make profeſſion of the truth of God, as appeareth in the hiſtories.</p>
               <p>After, this Beaſt is ſaid to <hi>haue a wound in one of his heads;</hi> that is, thought to be accompliſhed in the time of <hi>Nero,</hi> who was the laſt of the chiefe Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of that race, which was wounded, being euen cut off by their euill and wicked liuing, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by the cruelty of <hi>Nero,</hi> inſomuch that they thought their Empire was like to come to confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which indeed had come to paſſe, if it had not beene vpheld and maintained by the diſcreet coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of thoſe that followed, which were more wiſe, politique, and ſubtill then the other, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they were wicked men: So that by theſe it was reſtored againe, yea, though it were euen almoſt paſt hope; yet it was ſuddenly reuiued, and that in ſuch ſort, that all men wondred at it; and hereby they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſuch credit as they did, for it was maruellous in the iudgement of men, that a Kingdome ſo neere the fall, was ſo ſoone and ſo ſtrongly fortified, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>they are moued to worſhip the Beaſt, and to ſay, who is like the Beaſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:150822:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>And theſe that wondred, are drawne away to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Beaſt; which are deſcribed to be thoſe which were liuing in that time, <hi>whoſe names were not written in the Booke of life of the Lambe, which was ſlaine,</hi> which Booke is from the beginning of the world: not that it is here meant of Chriſt, <hi>to be ſlaine from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> for that cannot be ſo directly gathered out of this place.</p>
               <p>Theſe things thus deſcribed, hee warneth them of the iſſue, and firſt hee moueth attention; <hi>If any man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath an eare to heare, let him heare;</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them thereby, to take heed to that which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and which after he is to ſpeake, to the terror of the wicked, and the comfort and good of the Saints, and of the godly. And he ſaith, <hi>if any leade into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity, he ſhall be led into captiuity, &amp;c.</hi> to ſhew, that what meaſure they haue meted to others, the ſame ſhould be meaſured to them, and as they haue dealt with others, ſo they ſhould be dealt withall them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
               <p>And in this point (ſaith he) ſtandeth the <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>patience</hi> of the Saints; <hi>faith,</hi> to beleeue that God will bring this iudgement on the wicked; their <hi>patience,</hi> in that vpon this aſſurance of this iuſtice of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wicked, they ſhould patiently beare thoſe corrections and troubles which ſhall befall them, and patiently alſo wait for the accompliſhment of thoſe iudgements of God vpon their oppreſſors.</p>
               <p>And thus farre of the iudgements which the Church of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhould ſuffer by the crueltie of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire.</p>
               <p>Afterward follow the troubles that befall the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150822:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> Church, by the Biſhop of Rome, who is hereby no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſet forth vnto vs: namely, in that it is ſaid, <hi>there appeared another Beaſt like a Lambe;</hi> ſignifying, that howſoeuer this other Beaſt of <hi>Rome</hi> be moſt brutiſh and voide of humanity and vertue: And this is to be vnderſtood of the Pope, for he profeſſeth himſelfe to be the ſeruant of ſeruants, but in deed and practiſe he maketh himſelfe Lord of Lords, and this is not onely to be vnderſtood of one in that ſeat, but of all that ſucceed him, and that take his part, and which are of his Hierarchy.</p>
               <p>His effects doe follow, <hi>to wit,</hi> firſt <hi>that hee ſpake like a Dragon;</hi> noting, that the chiefe miſchiefe which ſhould come to the Church by him, ſhould be by his teaching and inſtructing them in that falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which hee ſhould receiue from the Dragon, which ſheweth that he is a falſe and lying Prophet, as receiuing his office and doctrine from the father of lyes, which is the Diuell. In that hee cauſed the earth to worſhip the firſt Beaſt, is meant, that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection which he did pretend to the Empire in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew, and ſo farre forth onely as his profit would ſerue, albeit indeed he doth exalt himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Emperours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And he did all that the firſt Beaſt could doe before his face,</hi> ſignifying, that he makes but a ieſt and mocke at the <hi>Romane Empire;</hi> for towards the end, the <hi>Romane Empire</hi> ſhould fall before him and decay; ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit in ſhew they would pretend to giue ſubiection to it, yet the Emperour had onely the name and title of authority to be called Lord, which we ſee indeed is, and was, but of ſmall reckoning; for the Pope
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150822:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſeemed rather to be Lord to himſelfe, as wee ſee in the Hiſtories, that the Emperours tooke many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches and abuſes of the Pope; yea, the Pope did tread on the necke of the Emperours, vſurping that ſaying of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Thou ſhalt tread on the Ader and the Aſpe, &amp;c.</hi> yea, the Pope and thoſe that were vnder him, did as it were make an Anatomy of the Empire, for as the Anatomiſts doe firſt take away their fleſh and then ioyne the bones and the other parts of the body together, &amp; ſo make him like a man againe, euen ſo did the Pope deale with the Empire.</p>
               <p>This Beaſt alſo made an <hi>Image in fauour of the firſt Beaſt;</hi> to which hee put a ſpirit, and the dead image did ſpeake: As it hath appeared to haue beene done by them, that the Diuell ſometimes did ſpeake in their images, to the illuding of the wicked: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by other deceits and illuſions to beguile the ſimple.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He alſo brought fire from heauen;</hi> alluding as it were, to the two good Prophets before, who are ſaid to haue cauſed fire to come downe from heauen, which is verrified of this falſe Prophet; who did and doth for the confirming of their falſe doctrine, worke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny counterfeit and fained miracles in the world.</p>
               <p>And laſtly it is ſaid, <hi>he ſhould ſo preuaile in the world, that none ſhould traffique, but ſuch as ſhould haue the marke of the Beaſt;</hi> which ſeemeth to be the ſigning in the forehead at their Sacrament of confirmation, which the Papiſts doe ſo eſteeme of, as that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it before the Lords Sacrament: or elſe they ſhould haue the name of the Beaſt, which is thought to be their confeſſion which they make to their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Prieſts.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:150822:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The ſingleſt thing is the number of the Beaſt, wherein is the ſpeciall wiſedome of Popery, and it is ſaid to <hi>be the number of a man;</hi> that is, hee muſt be a learned man among them that muſt come to the knowledge of it. Of which, diuers are of diuers opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; as namely, that it ſignifieth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>latinus,</hi> but that is too Caballiſticall, the meaning whereof being not as certainely yet attained vnto, though very probably gueſſed at by many, is to be pretermitted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 14. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>Then I looked, and lo, a Lambe ſtood on mount Sion, and with him an hundreth, fortie and foure thouſand, hauing his fathers Name written in their foreheads, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe Prophet hauing declared the fearefull iudgements to be executed on the earth by the man of <hi>Rome,</hi> hee doth here arme Gods Children by the promiſes of mercie in the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, then to giue credence to that which was to be ſpoken, here is ſet forth the deſcription of Chriſt, and his Church militant.</p>
               <p>Chriſt is here compared to a <hi>Lambe,</hi> both becauſe of his meekeneſſe and humilitie, and eſpecially by reaſon of his ſuffering, and his offering of himſelfe to death vpon the Croſſe for vs.</p>
               <p>Hee is ſaid to <hi>ſtand;</hi> ſignifying his readineſſe to helpe his Church. As <hi>Stephen, Acts</hi> 7. ſaw Chriſt ſtand at the right hand of God: not that Chriſt doth alway ſtand in heauen, but it noteth out vnto vs his
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150822:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> proneneſſe and willingneſſe to doe good to his, and to reuenge their aduerſaries.</p>
               <p>In <hi>mount Sion;</hi> that is, his Church, <hi>to wit,</hi> the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to the good &amp; helpe of his Church, to deliuer them from their enemies.</p>
               <p>Then is ſet downe his <hi>traine,</hi> in the ſame number that is ſpoken of in the ſeauenth Chapter, <hi>viz.</hi> one thouſand foure hundred and forty, ſignifying the great number of Gods Children on the face of the earth in that time; yet not ſo great, but that it might be tolde. And this ſame number of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in theſe times of perſecution, is noted to be as many as of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that were ſealed vp to life euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>And therefore it is a certaine thing that the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Gods children in the time of perſecution is but ſmall, in regard as at other times, for then they are without number, as it is ſaid in that ſeauenth Chapter.</p>
               <p>Theſe are deſcribed by their effects, <hi>to wit, that they had a ſong,</hi> and their voice is ſaid to be like <hi>the voice of many waters;</hi> that is, was a very great voice, and made a great ſound, yet ſo comfortable, as if it were the <hi>voice of harpers;</hi> which ſheweth the notable har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and mellodious voice of the Children of God, and their vnity and conſent in the prayſes of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A new ſong;</hi> that is, paſſing the capacitie of mans inuention, as being onely the worke of Gods ſpirit, and onely giuen them by the worke of their regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; for they onely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that are regenerate can ſing new ſongs, acceptable to God, ſo that no other man whatſoeuer, though neuer ſo wiſe, neuer ſo witty, neuer ſo cunning in Muſicke, can ſing pleaſantly
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150822:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> vnto God, vnleſſe they haue the ſpirit of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Virgins;</hi> that is, thoſe that were kept vndefiled from ſpirituall fornication, and corporall vncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which had no guile in their mouth, and were vnblameable in the ſight of God; not that they were altogether without guile and ſinne, but that they were accepted as righteous in Chriſt, that as Chriſt was without ſpot, ſo were they, as hauing the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of the <hi>Lambe</hi> imputed vnto them, and their ſinnes to him.</p>
               <p>Afterward, to draw credit to the Prophecie, hee ſaith, <hi>he ſees another Angell flie through the midſt of heauen,</hi> euidently, with the <hi>euerlaſting Goſpell;</hi> ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that after that, in that one thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty, the Goſpell ſhould not be cleane hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, but that there ſhould be an Angell, <hi>to wit,</hi> ſome Miniſters that ſhould fore-warne them to take heed of the Beaſt, and not to be defiled with his vncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>After, another Angell followeth, which foretelleth the deſtruction of <hi>Babilon;</hi> ſaying, <hi>Babilon is fallen;</hi> which noteth, that euen in thoſe times there ſhould be ſuch, which by the Miniſtery of the word ſhould denounce the ouerthrow and ruine of <hi>Babell,</hi> that is, of <hi>Rome,</hi> that howſoeuer it ſeemed ſtrong and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable in the ſight of the world, yet it ſhould fall and come to deſtruction: and it is twice repeated, to ſhew the certainty of it.</p>
               <p>A third Angell denounces the iudgements of God againſt the worſhippers of the Beaſt, &amp; of his image, <hi>to wit,</hi> thoſe that did yeeld themſelues to the Idolatry of the Beaſt.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:150822:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Theſe three meſſages are done by diuerſe kindes of Meſſengers and Miniſters; ſhewing that the gifts of God are diuerſe in his Miniſters; as namely, ſome of exhortation, ſome of denouncing iudgements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the vngodly; of which ſort this laſt is. In that he ſaith <hi>they ſhould drinke of the Wine of the wrath of God;</hi> it ſignifieth (as he expoundeth it) that they ſhall be tormented with Fire and Brimſtone, they ſhall be burned in hell, and that euen before the holy Angels, and before the Lambe, ſignifying the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of that iudgement in hell, as alſo that it ſhould be ſuch, that it might eaſily be diſcerned, and was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident to be ſeene of the <hi>Lambe,</hi> and of the <hi>Angels.</hi> The time of this is ſaid to be for <hi>euermore,</hi> not for a ſhort ſpace, or for a definite time; but it ſhould bee without ceaſing and without end.</p>
               <p>After, hee commeth to declare to the Church of God, the comforts that ſhould come to them by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing their eſtate in this world, and in the world to come; and then ſhewes the execution of the iudgements vpon the vngodly.</p>
               <p>For the Children of God, it is ſaid, that in this life there belongeth vnto them <hi>patience,</hi> and <hi>faith,</hi> which their <hi>faith</hi> bringeth forth obedience to Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and cauſeth their <hi>patience</hi> to continue.</p>
               <p>After this life it is ſaid, <hi>there ſhould come reſt from their labours, and their good things ſhould follow them;</hi> that is, their afflictions, perſecutions, their patience and holineſſe of life ſhould not ſtay behinde them, but ſhould follow them; that is, they ſhould haue them recompenced to the vtmoſt in heauen.</p>
               <p>Concerning the wicked, their iudgements follow.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:150822:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Firſt, it is ſaid, <hi>there comes an Angell out of a Cloud in white;</hi> ſignifying his zeale which he had in Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in the execution of his iudgements.</p>
               <p>He is a created Angell, not the Angell of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, as appeareth in that he is ſaid <hi>to be like a man;</hi> and alſo for that he is commanded by another, which was the Sonne of God: And hee is commanded to <hi>put in his ſharpe Sickle,</hi> (which is the word of God, being the power of God vnto deſtruction to all thoſe that beleeue not) into the world, becauſe the time is come, for (ſaith he) <hi>the harueſt is ripe, and the corne,</hi> (that is, the world) <hi>is dry.</hi> Where the world is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to drye Corne, for as Corne when it is dry, is then ready for the Sickle; ſo when the wicked are come to their full ripeneſſe in ſin, they are then ready to be cut off by the Sickle of Gods vengeance: And as dry ſtickes are fit for the fire, euen ſo they that are dried and dead in their ſinnes, are fit matter for Gods iudgements to burne to deſtruction; which noteth the fearefull iudgement to be executed on the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for worſhipping the Beaſt.</p>
               <p>Another iudgement followeth, more fearefull, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit in ſhew it be like the former, and that is of the other Angell that hath a ſickle, <hi>wherewith hee is bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to cut the Grapes downe:</hi> Hee is not bidden to cut them with a little knife (as is the vſe of pruning the Grapes) but with a Sickle; noting a more fierce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. And when he had cut them, he is bidden, <hi>he ſhould preſſe them in the Vine-preſſe of Gods wrath:</hi> A ſimilitude taken from the vſe of thoſe, who when they haue gathered their Grapes, caſt them into the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe to be trodden and preſſed out, euen ſo ſhould
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150822:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> they be trodden downe, and cruſhed with the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and wrath of God: And this muſt be done hand by hand, and one Cluſter by another; which ſignifieth a more notable iudgement: In reaping Corne, men vſe to gather many together, but theſe Grapes muſt be gathered one by one; ſhewing the fierceneſſe of this iudgement to be exalted vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of them particularly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Troden out of the City;</hi> that is, among the wicked, out of the Church, alluding to the cuſtome in thoſe Countries, where they had their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> preſſes to tread their Grapes without the City: And here hee allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth alſo to the execution of offenders, which vſeth to be done without the City: ſo this iudgement ſhould be done without the Church. Noting, that this onely was to be executed vpon the vngodly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners.</p>
               <p>The greatneſſe of this iudgement is aggrauated, in that the bloud ſhould be in ſuch abundance, and ſo deepe, <hi>that a man riding in it, it ſhould reach to the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles of the Horſes, for the diſtance of one thouſand and ſixe hundred furlongs,</hi> which is about three hundred of our miles, or more: Noting, the exceeding great wrath of God vpon thoſe offenders, and the fearefull iudgement which they ſhould ſuffer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:150822:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 15. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>And I ſaw another ſigne in heauen, great and maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, ſeauen Angels hauing the ſeauen laſt plagues: for by them is fulfilled the wrath of God, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THere hauing beene ſet before in the former Chapters, as well the fauour to Gods Children, as iudgements againſt the contemners of the Goſpell, hee proceedeth here in the declaration of the ſame.</p>
               <p>And firſt of the iudgements againſt the Beaſt and his worſhippers in the firſt Verſe, the executioners whereof are in that Verſe ſaid to be <hi>ſeauen Angels, to wit,</hi> a perfect number to performe that worke; they are ſaid to haue the <hi>ſeauen laſt plagues;</hi> that is, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and power was giuen them to execute that full number of iudgements which remained to be pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on the earth.</p>
               <p>And hauing ſpoken of the Miniſters of Gods iudgements, he ſpeaketh alſo of the furniture and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the iudgements of God; which he hath as it were in ſtore againſt them.</p>
               <p>And he calleth it <hi>a Sea mingled with fire;</hi> alluding to the Lauary of the Prieſts in the Temple, whereto he ſeemeth to compare this, which was called a Sea in regard of the greatneſſe of it.</p>
               <p>And it is called <hi>a Sea of Chriſtall, or a glaſsie Sea,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it might be throughly looked into, and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently diſcerned of the Children of God through Chriſt. In the Sea is <hi>fire,</hi> which is the wrath and curſe of God, the matter of Gods fierce indignation,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150822:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> and the iudgements which ſhould be taken out of this Lauer of Gods wrath, for as in the Lauer, in the time of the Law, there was water to waſh the Prieſts, and to make them cleane; noting the cleaneneſſe and vprightneſſe that ſhould be in the Prieſts, and which all that ſhould be Prieſts vnto God ſhould receiue from Chriſt; euen ſo in this Lauer and Sea of Gods wrath, fire is ſaid to be; noting, that from hence ſhould come matter of iudgement to conſume and deſtroy the enemies of God.</p>
               <p>After, it is ſaid, that the Children of God which had gotten the victory ouer their enemies, did ſtand by this Sea; namely, to ſee and behold theſe fearefull iudgements of God againſt the wicked; and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>to wit,</hi> on this occaſion are ſtirred vp to praiſe the Lord, <hi>and they ſing the Song of Moſes and of the Lambe;</hi> namely, a Song of thankeſgiuing for their deliuerance by the <hi>Lambe,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Great and maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous are thy workes, &amp;c.</hi> as if they ſhould ſay, <hi>who is it that would not magnifie ſo mightie a King, ſo holy and ſo iuſt a God, who for the glory of his name, and the reuenge of his Saints, hath ſuch a treaſury of iudgements againſt his enemies, which now in Chriſt he had made manifeſt vnto them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After, it is ſaid, <hi>that theſe ſeauen Angels come out of the Temple;</hi> that is, out of the preſence of God, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that they come by the authority and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, and therefore that their ambaſſage was certainely and neceſſarily to be accompliſhed. And they <hi>are cloathed with white;</hi> ſignifying their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity and vprightneſſe, ſhewing that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which they executed vniuſtly or wrongfully,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150822:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> but that it was right and iuſt, howſoeuer it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto the ſonnes of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They were girded;</hi> that is, prompt, ſit, and ready to execute their meſſage, whereunto they were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, for (as the cuſtome was in thoſe dayes) thoſe that had their cloathes girded vp to them, were fitter for any worke or buſineſſe they went about.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To theſe Angels are giuen Vials;</hi> ſignifying, that as theſe inferiour Angels are innocent and holy ſpirits vprightly performing that which is inioyned them, and as they are ready thereunto, ſo they doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without the ſpeciall calling or commandement of God, and without a particular Ordinance from God, for their charge and function is laid vpon them either immediately from God himſelfe, or elſe by the Arch-Angels and thoſe which are the chiefe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
               <p>Further, it is ſaid, <hi>that the Temple was filled with ſmoake, that none could enter in vntill the ſeauen Plagues of the ſeauen Angels were accompliſhed:</hi> The glory of God ſo filled that place, that the Angels themſelues could not enter into it; for by this ſmoake is meant the fulneſſe of Gods preſence, and the full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect glory and maieſtie of the ſame, as was in the Temple in the time of the Law, when that it was firſt finiſhed, <hi>the glory of the Lord ſo filled the Temple with a ſmoake, that none were able to abide therein;</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that he was well pleaſed with the building of it: euen ſo here the Angels being ſent forth to execute, the preſence of God was ſo exceeding glorious, that the Angels could not be able to returne thither, till they had finiſhed and fulfilled the iudgements which
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:150822:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> they were ſent forth to doe: noting alſo that this execution of theſe iudgements of God, was accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto him; as alſo that they were irreuocable, and altogether inauoideable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 16. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>And I heard a great voice out of the Temple, ſaying to the ſeauen Angels, Goe your waies, and poure out the ſeauen Vials of the wrath of God vpon the earth, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IN the ſetting forth of the iudgements of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Beaſt and his worſhippers, wee haue heard in the former Chapter, that mention was made of the Miniſters and Executioners of theſe iudgements, as alſo of the matter of the ſame. In this Chapter followeth the Execution of the Miniſtery of theſe ſeauen Angels.</p>
               <p>And firſt it is ſaid by the Apoſtle, <hi>that hee heard a voice out of the Temple, to the ſeauen Angels, which gaue ſpeciall authority vnto them, commanding them to poure out their Vials.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That they came forth of the <hi>Temple;</hi> it noteth their full authority and ſtrength to doe that worke they were called vnto, and alſo that the iudgements which they executed were irreuocable.</p>
               <p>And whereas the <hi>Vials</hi> being giuen them before, yet they would not poure them out before they were commanded; more particularly it ſheweth the great and ſingular obedience of the Angels. One would haue thought, that hauing the Vials once giuen them,, they ſhould preſently haue proceeded to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, but they would not, till they had ſpeciall
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:150822:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> commandement. Teaching vs not to doe any thing without ſpeciall authority, commiſſion, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement from God.</p>
               <p>Euen as a ſword, being committed into the hand of a Souldier by the Captaine generall, hee is not to ſmite before he be commanded to fight, and before the Trumpet be ſounded to battaile; ſo though a man haue excellent graces giuen him, yet he is not to execute any function, eſpecially publiquely, before he receiue a particular warrant and calling from God thereunto. <hi>Sampſon,</hi> though hee had ſtrength giuen him that he was able to haue defended the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and reuenged them of their enemies, yet he could not take vpon him the gouernement of the people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord had called him vnto it: In like manner, the Miniſters of the word, albeit they haue neuer ſo notable gifts of Knowledge, Vtterance, &amp;c. yet they are not in any caſe to intrude themſelues into the Miniſtery, vnleſſe they haue a particular calling from the Lord.</p>
               <p>Theſe Angels are bidden firſt in generall to caſt their <hi>Vials</hi> vpon the earth; that is, on the whole frame of all the Heauen, Earth, Sea, and all in them, in the execution: yet ſome are more ſpecially comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be poured on the earth, becauſe theſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are intended againſt the wicked on the earth.</p>
               <p>The firſt Angell is ſaid to haue <hi>poured his Viall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth;</hi> whereupon <hi>there fell an exceeding great ſore of Biles on them that had the marke of the Beaſt, and which worſhipped his Image.</hi> The Plagues of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter haue great agreement with the Plagues ſet downe in the eight and ninth Chapters, they being like in
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:150822:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> the matter of the plagues, ſo alſo in the number: the difference is, that theſe were headed with more fierce tokens of Gods wrath, and with a more heauie indignation, becauſe thoſe were executed on all the earth; not on the Perſons onely, theſe on the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and that on the principall offenders onely, namely, on the worſhippers of the Beaſt.</p>
               <p>So that here wee ſee the Lord executes his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by degrees; firſt by <hi>Biles,</hi> not killing them, but vexing them outwardly, if happily thereby they might be brought to repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond Angell poured his Viall on the Sea, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the colour of it was turned, ſo that it looked like black blood of death:</hi> So that God proceeded in iudgement, they not profiting, hee now goeth on forward to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh with death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third Angell poured his Viall on the freſh waters;</hi> to declare that God left notes of his wrath on all the creatures of the world: ſo that the earth and waters themſelues being thus iudged, did beare witneſſe of their ſinnes againſt them.</p>
               <p>On theſe two latter executions, the Angels of the Waters take occaſion to acknowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that Gods iudgements againſt the wicked, <hi>are true, and holy, and iuſt,</hi> as after followeth. <hi>For as they had ſhed the bloud of Gods Saints, ſo their bloud alſo was ſhed,</hi> and they are faine (as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> did, to whom they were alluded) <hi>to drinke of the bloud of the Riuers,</hi> for ſo (ſay they) <hi>are they worthy;</hi> as before, hauing taken delight in the bloud of the Saints.</p>
               <p>Another Angell, that is, the third Angell which was in the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> doth approue that which the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:150822:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> other two had confeſſed; for their office was ouer the Waters: noting, that the Angels of God haue their particular places of gouernment, wherein they execute their functions enioyned them of God. And leſt the wicked ſhould ſeeme to thinke that God was too ſharpe and ſeuere in iudgement againſt them, therefore not onely the Angels of the Waters, that is, of the freſh and ſalt waters, doe acknowledge, that the ſinnes of thoſe wicked men had deſerued this and more; and therefore the iudgement was iuſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as that they might ſee their very ſinnes in the ſame, as it were in capitall letters: but euen alſo that other Angell, out of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> doth affirme, that which theſe two had ſaid, and acknowledgeth Gods righteous iudgement herein.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fourth Angell caſts his Viall on the Sunne;</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that the iudgement was not onely on the earth, but in the heauen, by the diſtemperature thereof, through the intemperate weather, as namely, the extreame heat which ſhould proceed <hi>from it, which ſhould ſcorch the earth, and the men that were in it, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould come dearth, famine, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here the Euangeliſt notes, that theſe worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the Beaſt, whether they had receiued the marke of the Beaſt vpon the foreheads, that is, were open profeſſors of the worſhip of the Beaſt, or recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it in their hands, that is, were priuate fauourers of the Beaſt and his Idolatries, namely, whether they did openly or priuately or any way yeeld to the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry of the Beaſt of <hi>Rome; yet they repented not:</hi> ſignifying, that whereas as yet, Gods iudgements were in his hand to remoue them if they repented,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150822:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> or to double them if they did not repent: <hi>They not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding for all theſe degrees of Plagues, doe ſtill continue obſtinate; yea, they proceed to blaſpheme God,</hi> ſo farre are they from repenting and glorifying God. And hitherto it ſeemes God began with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people; for as in his Plagues, he vſeth to begin firſt with his Church, then with the wicked; ſo in the wicked hee begins firſt with the lower and inferiour ſort, and then followes with the more grieuous and principall offenders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fift Angell poures out his Viall on the ſeate of the Beaſt;</hi> which is to be vnderſtood of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> whereupon <hi>followes darkeneſſe, to wit,</hi> anguiſh, and trouble, and paine: which appeared in that they are ſaid to <hi>bite their tongues,</hi> as the malignant and enuious perſons vſe to doe, who being troubled or croſſed any way, will for anguiſh vexe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſixt Angell poures out his Viall on the Riuer Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates; viz.</hi> that defence wherewith this ſpirituall <hi>Babilon</hi> is enuironed and compaſſed about; for by <hi>Babilon</hi> is vnderſtood <hi>Rome;</hi> for as in <hi>Babilon</hi> the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were kept both in ſpirituall and bodly ſeruitude; ſo by the ſinnes and Idolatries of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> it hath beene ſhewed that the Church of God ſhould be tormented with ſpirituall bondage. And this Riuer <hi>Euphrates</hi> was a riuer which compaſſed and defended <hi>Babilon</hi> from their enemies: and therfore by <hi>Euphrates</hi> here ſeemeth to be meant, the fort, ſtrenght, and munition of the City and Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Whereas then he poureth his <hi>Viall vpon Euphrates, whereby it was dried vp;</hi> it noteth that
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:150822:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſtrength and fort of <hi>Rome</hi> was hereby greatly abated, and as it were taken away.</p>
               <p>The reaſon of this is rendred, namely, that their might be way made for the Kings of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> who ſhould come for the aide and reliefe of this Beaſt of <hi>Rome;</hi> for whereas by this Iudgement, and by theſe Plagues, they ſhould haue turned vnto repentance, yet they would not, but in their diſtreſſe would make rather all friends they could to be at one with the Kings of the earth, and vſe all meanes of reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelues vnto them; and ioyning to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the Kings which were from farre, making them their defendants and maintainers.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid, <hi>that from the Dragon,</hi> that is, from Sathan; <hi>from the Beaſt,</hi> that is, from the Empire; <hi>from the Prophet,</hi> that is, from that man of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Pope, <hi>are ſent forth three ſpirits:</hi> It noteth, that when they ſhould ſee themſelues thus deſtitute, made na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and depriued of their defences and ſafeguards which they had before, there ſhould be a certaine number of falſe Prophets raiſed vp by the Pope and his adherents, which ſhould ſtirre vp and ſolicite the Kings to ioyne to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Theſe Prophets are compared to <hi>Frogs,</hi> partly becauſe of their loud voice, and of that great noiſe which they ſhould make, and whereby they ſhould be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally crying in the eares of the Princes; which thing wee ſee effected by the Monkes, Fryers, and the reſt of thoſe curſed Prophets, who are alwaies perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoſe whom they would haue to ioyne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto them, by theſe arguments; by defending their holy Father the Pope; of helping their holy
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150822:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> Mother the Church, &amp;c. thereby ſtirring them vp againſt Chriſt and his ſeruants. Partly alſo theſe falſe Prophets are compared to <hi>frogs,</hi> by reaſon of their great multitudes, wherein they come.</p>
               <p>And here Chriſt comforteth and vpholdeth his Seruants, and warneth them to take heed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that howſoeuer the Beaſt, with his Prophets, thus proceeded, and made themſelues ſtrong, by ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to them the Princes of the earth; yet hee ſaith, <hi>hee will come vpon them as a Thiefe;</hi> namely, at vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares to them. And therefore hee admoniſheth the Children of God <hi>to watch; and keepe vpon them their cloathes and their armour, leſt hee comming in the night, ſhould finde them naked, both to their ſhame, and to their deſtruction, they being naked to his iudgements:</hi> allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a Souldier, who being naked and without Armour, when the enemie commeth muſt needs be ſlaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And as they gather the Kings for their aſsiſtance;</hi> ſo he alſo gathereth great companies together, and the place he gathereth them to, is <hi>Harmageddon;</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the mountaine of deſtruction, which was the place where <hi>Ioſiah</hi> was ſlaine, and a great ouerthrow was giuen to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> by the King of <hi>Egypt;</hi> which fearefull and grieuous ouerthrow, the wicked bragged at, and vſed to obiect it againſt the people of God, which here he ſeemeth to aime at: as if hee ſhould ſay, that they ſhould bragge no more againſt the Church of God, becauſe they had ſo ſore an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow at that time, for which, there was ſo great a lamentation, as it is ſaid, <hi>that there was neuer the like heard;</hi> for euen as that place, was a place of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150822:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> to them, ſo this ſhould be to theſe enemies of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſeauenth Angell poures his Viall on the Aire,</hi> then there is ſaid <hi>to come a voice from the Temple,</hi> which was the voice of God: the effects whereof were won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull; for it is ſaid, <hi>that there followed in heauen, moſt fearefull thunders, lightnings, and voices,</hi> in the earth <hi>a great Earth-quake;</hi> whereby the earth trembled and ſhaked, which is ſaid to be ſo fearefull a one, as neuer was before. Which noteth the fearefull maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and terror of God againſt his enemies, and his mightie power whereby hee is able to ſcatter and to deſtroy them. The words which the Voice vttered, are theſe; <hi>It is done:</hi> to wit, the conſummation of the victory of Chriſt ouer his enemies, the parts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are expreſſed, ſome in the words following, to the end of this Chapter, and the reſt follow in the other Chapters.</p>
               <p>Then in the next words, it is ſaid, that the victory of Chriſt is in part wrought by the <hi>Earth-quake,</hi> the effects whereof are, firſt, <hi>that the great City was ſhaken,</hi> to wit, <hi>Rome;</hi> called the great City, by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, in that it was counted the greateſt in the world, being the greateſt in account, in fame, and eſtimation: according to our vſuall cuſtome, who call the moſt famous and chiefe City, by the name of <hi>The City.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it is not onely ſhaken, and many Houſes throwne downe, but alſo it is <hi>diuided into three parts;</hi> that is, their power is ſcattered, the City being diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and rent into many peeces by the Earth-quake: and not onely this City, but many Cities of other
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150822:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> Nations, and the Iſles alſo, to wit, other Countries are hereby ouerthrowne, <hi>and the Mountaines were not found,</hi> which vſeth to come to paſſe in great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, their power likewiſe and ſtrength being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away.</p>
               <p>Afterwards it is ſaid, <hi>that there fell great Haile-ſtones like Talents vpon men:</hi> and theſe come, when by the Earth quake they were terrified and ſcared out of their doores: for when they were diſlodged of their Houſes and all refuge, then the Lord poured out his iudgements on them, to breake their heads, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing whereof before could not breake their hearts: ſuch was the Haile which fell on the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that whoſoeuer were without the doores, ſhould be killed therewith: but here the Lord dealeth more ſeuerely, for firſt he driueth them out of their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from all refuge, and then poures the Hayle ſtones vpon them: the effect hereof in them is, <hi>that they blaſphemed God by reaſon of the greatneſſe of the Hayle.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 17. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>Then there came one of the ſeauen Angels, which had the ſeauen Vials, and talked with mee, ſaying vnto mee, Come: I will ſhew thee the damnation of the great Whore that ſitteth vpon many waters, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>OF the things that were reuealed in the laſt <hi>Vial,</hi> that which followeth is a part. Wee haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready heard of the ſumme of Chriſts iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on the City, and the men thereof. Now the Prophet proceedeth to declare the contents which further enſue of that <hi>Viall.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:150822:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Firſt he ſaith, that an Angell (which was one of them that poured out the Viall) <hi>came to tell</hi> Iohn <hi>what ſhould befall the Harlot.</hi> Which teacheth vs, that the ſelfe ſame Angels that are Executioners of Gods iudgements vpon the wicked, are alſo Miniſters of Gods mercie for the comfort of his Children.</p>
               <p>He expounds the iudgement of the <hi>Harlot, which is the Whore of Rome;</hi> who is called a Harlot, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of her abhominations and whoredomes, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſpirituall, in her Idolatries, as alſo bodily in her beaſtly fornication: that City being the very pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and ſinke of all filthineſſe and vncleaneneſſe.</p>
               <p>She is called <hi>the great Harlot,</hi> becauſe all the Kings of the earth ſhould goe a whoring to her, eſpecially by committing ſpirituall fornication, which is Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. And all the people alſo of their Nations, and all the inhabitants of the earth ſhould alſo take part in her filthy abhominations: and therefore Shee muſt needs be a notable Strumpet, with whom all the Princes of the world, with their people and ſubiects muſt commit adultery, vncleaneneſſe, and all kinde of villany.</p>
               <p>In that <hi>Iohn</hi> was carried againe <hi>by the ſpirit into the Wilderneſſe;</hi> is meant, that albeit hee had receiued all theſe things (which were reuealed to him before) by the ſpirit, yet for the further aſſurance of the things now to be deliuered, he ſaith, <hi>that he is carried againe in the ſpirit;</hi> that is, hee is lift vp by a more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular hand of God, that he might the more notably vnderſtand and attend, by the ſpeciall direction of Gods ſpirit, to the things now to be reuealed.</p>
               <p>And he ſaith, <hi>he ſaw a woman ſit vpon a Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:150822:56"/>
               <p>By the <hi>woman</hi> is meant the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Beaſt</hi> ſignifieth, firſt the Emperours only which were ciuill gouerners: and ſecondly, the Pope, which tooke vpon him both ciuill and eccleſiaſticall gouernement: ſo that vpon <hi>this Beaſt ſhee is ſaid to fit;</hi> and therefore whereas he ſaith, <hi>he ſees the Harlot ſitting on the Beaſt,</hi> it is meant, that the honour of the City and Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was to be maintained and vpheld by the Emperours, the gouernours ciuill, and by the Pope, which had both Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall authority, for both theſe are in this place ſet downe to be but one <hi>Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Beaſt is ſaid to be <hi>coloured like Scarlet;</hi> ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, either he was aduanced to great honour, or elſe nothing his crueltie in murthering the Saints: but this thing afterward, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> more notably ſetteth downe, in that the <hi>Whore</hi> her ſelfe is ſaid to be <hi>red with the bloud of the Saints;</hi> noting, that as this was her Liuery, ſo the chiefeſt colour wherin this Church and this Beaſt delighteth, is Scarlet, as appeareth by their vſage; for they vſe to weare this, that they might be knowne to be bloudy and cruell.</p>
               <p>It is further ſaid, that this <hi>Beaſt is full of names of blaſphemie;</hi> it is meant, that whereas before it was ſaid, that the firſt Beaſt had a name of blaſphemy, that is, was very cruell &amp; very blaſphemous, when he firſt roſe out of the Sea, which was verified by the example of <hi>Caligula</hi> and others, that tooke on them the honour of God; yet this doth farre exceede him, for he is full of the names of blaſphemie, <hi>viz.</hi> blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous throughout, ſignifying an high degree of blaſphemie.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:150822:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>He ſpeakes alſo of the Harlot her ſelfe, whom hee ſaith <hi>to be arrayed in Purple and Scarlet;</hi> ſignifying, that ſhe was clad royally, <hi>purple</hi> being a moſt coſtly and Princely apparell; <hi>her Scarlet bedecked with gold, precious ſtones and Pearles;</hi> note the exceeding great riches of that Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then followes that which ſhee did, <hi>viz. Shee had a cup of Gold in her hand, but within full of abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and filthy whoredomes and fornications;</hi> noting, that without ſhe had a gorgeous ſhew, &amp; was beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to behold, but within full of al vncleanenes, as our Sauiour Chriſt ſaid of the Phariſies, <hi>that they cleanſe the out ſide of the cup, but are all filthy within;</hi> which we ſee in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> that without they haue moſt faire ſhewes to looke to, but looke into them, and into their actions, there is nothing but vncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shee had in her forehead a name written, a Miſtery;</hi> ſignifying, that the chiefe thing <hi>ſhee</hi> profeſſeth, is a Miſtery, namely, that <hi>ſhee</hi> hath the Miſteries and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of God; yea, <hi>ſhee</hi> profeſſeth that all knowledge and vnderſtanding of Gods will is ſhut vp onely in her breaſts, as in a cloſet: and therefore (ſay they) the Pope can change the Articles of the faith; yea, that he can alter the Scriptures, and make them no Scriptures, and that he can make the Euangeliſts to be no Euangeliſts, and thoſe that are not, to be.</p>
               <p>She is called <hi>great Babilon,</hi> becauſe of the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of that <hi>Babilon</hi> in the Eaſt, to this in the Weſt, principally in regard of her great cruelty againſt Gods Children.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Mother of Harlots;</hi> that is, the chiefe Harlot of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:150822:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> all, ſetting out her abhominable fornications, both ſpirituall and bodily.</p>
               <p>After, in that ſhe is ſaid <hi>to be drunke with the bloud of the Saints;</hi> is ſet forth her cruelty and barbarouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt the witneſſes of Gods truth, in that ſhe is defiled, beſpotted, and embrued with the bloud of the Saints: As Chriſt is ſaid to come out of <hi>Edom, coloured with the bloud of his enemies;</hi> noting thereby the reuenge he ſhould take of the <hi>Edomites;</hi> euen ſo the Whore of <hi>Babilon</hi> is dyed with the bloud of Gods children; yea, ſhe is ſaid <hi>to be drunke with their bloud, as with drinke;</hi> ſhewing, that ſhe makes no more account of ſhedding the bloud of the ſeruants of God, then the drunken man makes of pouring in drinke, or the fiſhes water.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn wonders at her; to wit,</hi> not after that ſort which thoſe doe which follow after, whoſe names were not written in the Booke of life; but hee wonders after another manner; namely, at the ſtrangeneſſe of the thing, and at the ſtrangeneſſe of her abhominations. But the Angell askes him, <hi>wherefore marueileſt thou at it? I will</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>tell thee the miſtery, viz.</hi> the meaning of the Harlot, and of the Beaſt. And taking in hand to handle and declare the miſtery of them both, hee begins (after the manner and cuſtome of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi>) with that which hee named laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the Beaſt, and ſaith, <hi>that he was, and is not:</hi> It is ſaid he is not, which hath been declared by the wound he receiued, accompliſhed in the time of <hi>Nero:</hi> after whoſe time, the manner of gouernement, in regard of the familie which then ruled, was no more, all that family being worne out, and therefore the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:150822:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> was ceaſed; and yet notwithſtanding ſhould riſe againe out of the depth, out of the bottomleſſe pit, <hi>viz.</hi> out of hell, by the ſubtiltie and pollicie of Sathan and his craftie inſtruments: and ſhould goe to deſtruction, that is, ſhould for all this ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and not haue a continuall gouernement. And it is ſaid, <hi>that at the Beaſt all ſhould wonder,</hi> not as <hi>Iohn</hi> did, but with an admiration of it, the reaſon is, becauſe <hi>it was, and is not, and yet is;</hi> that is, albeit it ſhould haue ſo many changes and alterations, in that the Emperours ſhould be ſo often put downe and ſlaine (as appeareth by the hiſtories) and others rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp, neuertheleſſe, the gouernement ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill; wherfore the men of the world, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods prouidence in the ordering of theſe things, ſhould hereby be drawne with admiration of the Beaſt to cleaue vnto it, conſidering that albeit hee had receiued ſo many wounds and ſo great puſhes, as it were, to deſtroy him and ouerthrow him, and yet did continue and was able to ſtand, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it was by his own power, they ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſay, <hi>who is like to the Beaſt?</hi> So that wee ſee that this Empire which is here vnderſtood by the Beaſt, was the ſame, but in other families, as is ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>Then it is ſaid, <hi>here is the minde that hath wiſedome;</hi> that is, here is matter wherein thoſe that are wiſe ſhould occupie their wits and vnderſtandings.</p>
               <p>After, he declareth what the ſeauen heads are, <hi>to wit, ſeauen hils;</hi> namely, that place where the City of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſituated, and amongſt all writers, both <hi>Latine</hi> &amp; <hi>Greek,</hi> which ſpeake of it, it is called the City of the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:150822:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>ſeauen hils,</hi> and none but it, is ſo named in any, either old or new, <hi>Latine</hi> or <hi>Greeke</hi> Author. And therefore howſoeuer the Papiſts would poſt it ouer to <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> where the Turke is, as hauing thirty hils, yet that was of no account in the dayes when this was written: Againe, that was neuer gouernour of the world as this is called, and as it was in thoſe dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſeauen heads</hi> haue another expoſition giuen them by the Angell, to be ſeauen Kings, that is, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Gouernours and Emperours of the City, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is ſaid, <hi>fiue are fallen,</hi> that is, were dead: <hi>one was then,</hi> that is, <hi>Domitian,</hi> who at that time had bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <hi>Iohn</hi> into <hi>Pathmos;</hi> and he that <hi>was to come,</hi> was the next after <hi>Domitian, and he ſhould indure but a ſmall time:</hi> and therefore thoſe that liued in thoſe dayes might eaſily ſee the truth of it. And this therefore ſet forth thus, that men prouing and ſeeing this to be true, might giue the more credit to the reſt.</p>
               <p>And the Beaſt <hi>that was and is not</hi> (that is, is not of the ſame ſort as he was, being now changed by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther family) is the <hi>eight, to wit,</hi> in number, which was the <hi>ſeauenth</hi> alſo, for hee was admitted by the <hi>ſeauenth,</hi> while the <hi>ſeauenth</hi> was aliue; for the other being aliue, this eight in his dayes was choſen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and was ioyned in gouernement with him, as was the cuſtome of Kings, when that Kingdomes were doubtfull, the Kings tooke their Succeſſors, whom they would to haue raigne next in their roome, and would in their owne life eſtabliſh them in their Kingdomes, as did <hi>Dauid</hi> with <hi>Salomon,</hi> who while he yet liued, ſetled his Sonne in the Kingdome, taking him as it were, and ioyning him in ſocietie
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:150822:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> with him, and ſetting him by him as it were on the Throne.</p>
               <p>Hauing thus expounded the <hi>ſeauen heads,</hi> hee comes to tell what is meant by the <hi>tenne Hornes;</hi> which are ſaid to be <hi>tenne Kings,</hi> which had not as yet receiued their power; which ſhould ioyne with the Beaſt, <hi>to wit,</hi> ſhould not raigne there where the Beaſt did, but ſhould onely lay their power and authority with his, but while he had the ciuill authority alone in the rule of the Emperour, as alſo afterward when the Pope ariſing, ſhould ioyne the ſpirituall iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the temporall gouernement; and theſe tenne Kings it is ſaid ſhould ioyne with this Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall Beaſt.</p>
               <p>By theſe <hi>tenne,</hi> it is no great matter whether wee vnderſtand a certaine or vncertaine number, but it ſeemeth rather to note an vncertaine number: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it were, true it is, that theſe, the Beaſt ſhould ioyne with him to take his part, <hi>to wit,</hi> they ſhould giue their power to him, to ride and runne at his pleaſure. <hi>And theſe fight againſt the Lambe, who ſhould ouercome them by the power of his word:</hi> for hee muſt needes, being <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> and therefore cannot but breake thoſe Hornes that ſet themſelues againſt him; for they receiue of him, and hold but of licenſe their Kingdomes from him.</p>
               <p>The Waters are plainely expounded by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, to be the great <hi>multitudes of people,</hi> and diuers Countries that ſhould be ſubiect to that City and Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further, he declares, that as there was a time that the Kings of the earth ſhould ioyne themſelues with
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:150822:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Beaſt to maintaine it; ſo time ſhould come, that thoſe Kings and Gouernours as they had ſuffered themſelues to be as it were trodden on by the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and to be ſubiect to the <hi>Whore,</hi> ſo they ſhould fight againſt the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and againſt <hi>her,</hi> and moſt bitterly venter themſelues in fight againſt <hi>her;</hi> yea, <hi>they ſhall eate her fleſh,</hi> that is, be in mortall hatred with <hi>her</hi> to conſume <hi>her,</hi> and <hi>ſhould burne the Harlot;</hi> that is, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy her vtterly, and ſo puniſh her as a Harlot; for burning was the vſuall death for a Harlot.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, in that hee ſaith <hi>the woman is the great City that had dominion ouer the Kingdomes of the earth;</hi> hee ſheweth plainely that it is the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeeing there was no ſuch great Monarch as that ſince the time of <hi>Iohn,</hi> but onely <hi>Rome,</hi> and Shee was euen then the chiefe Citie in the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 18. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>And after theſe things, I ſaw another Angell come downe from heauen, hauing great power, ſo that the earth was lightened with his glory, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe Prophet hauing entred into the deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> as of the ſpirituall <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> doth on that occaſion diſpute what ſhall be done of <hi>her:</hi> for notwithſtanding, the deſtruction of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> ſhould come before, and the ouerthrow of the City ſhould follow, yet the ouerthrow of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is handled in the firſt place, &amp; of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> is ſet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vnto the end that he might more fully ſet down the deſtruction and notable ruine of the ſame.</p>
               <p>And firſt hee declareth the deſtruction of the <hi>City,</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:150822:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> and that it may haue the more authority, the Angell that deſcribeth it, is <hi>ſaid to come from heauen;</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the certainety thereof, namely, in that this meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage came from heauen, euen from God himſelfe, and therefore the City of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould certainely be deſtroyed, and razed vtterly from the face of the earth.</p>
               <p>And this authority is more fully ſet forth, in that the Angell is deſcribed to haue <hi>come with ſuch glory, that the earth was enlightned therewith;</hi> and therefore that ſhould be a moſt euident and vndoubted mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: which alſo appeareth in the mightineſſe of his voice.</p>
               <p>Hee ſaith, <hi>it is fallen,</hi> and the ſecond time, <hi>it is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len;</hi> which repetition hee vſeth, firſt to raiſe vp men from their drowſineſſe, which cannot at the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of Gods iudgements, nor conſider them as they ought, and therefore they muſt haue diuers repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſame thing concerning the iuſtice of Gods iudgements. Secondly, to ſhew the certainty of it, as before, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. 8. According as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> interprets <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dreames of the <hi>ſeauen leane Kine, which did deuoure the ſeauen fatte; and the ſeauen thinne eares of Wheate, that did conſume the ſeauenfull;</hi> that they both did ſignifie one thing, and that the dreame was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doubled to ſhew that that which was ſignified thereby, ſhould certainly come &amp; that ſpeedily: Euen ſo the repetition of the denouncing of theſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is for this cauſe, namely, as to waken the drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of man, ſo to ſhew the certainty and ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the iudgements to be executed.</p>
               <p>Then is ſet forth the ſtate of this <hi>Babilon,</hi> the City
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:150822:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> of <hi>Rome,</hi> in that it is ſaid, <hi>it ſhould become an Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Diuels, and of vncleane Birds;</hi> ſignifying the great deſolation of it, according as it is the vſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who to expreſſe the exceeding deſolations of any place, ſay that thoſe Birds which flye moſt farre from all reſort of men, as the Shrike-Owle, and the Pelican, &amp;c. ſhould continue there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To Diuels;</hi> noting that thoſe places that haue bin abuſed to the diſhonour of God, are giuen by Gods iuſt iudgement, to be not onely deſolate, but euen haunted of Diuels themſelues, as wee ſee oft times it commeth to paſſe in Abbyes, and ſuch like ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous houſes.</p>
               <p>The cauſe is ſet downe, <hi>to wit, by reaſon of the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Saints, and her pride,</hi> who vaunted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of her riches and good eſtate, ſaying, <hi>that ſhee was Queene, and ſhould neuer be Widdow;</hi> that is, ſhould neuer be deſolate, but ſhould alway haue her louers and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers to take her part.</p>
               <p>And a principall cauſe is this, <hi>that ſhe had played the Harlot through her Idolatrie with the Princes of the earth.</hi> Then he ſetteth downe the markes of her deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both which goe before, and which come after.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Before:</hi> that God would giue his children that were there warning before, whereby they might know of it, that ſo they might come forth, leſt they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhould fall in that great deſtruction, as before we heard hee did to the Saints in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> by giuing them warning to auoide from thence, which they did, flying into the City of <hi>Pella</hi> in the wilderneſſe.</p>
               <p>The markes following the deſtruction, generally, the lamentation of the friends of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:150822:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> and principally the Kings of the earth, when they ſhall <hi>ſee the ſmoake of her, mount vp to heauen;</hi> by ſmoake, is meant the continuall remembrance of that deſtruction: for albeit, after it is ſaid by the Angell <hi>that threw the ſtone into the Sea, that it ſhould neuer be remembred any more;</hi> hee meaneth not that it ſhould be cleane forgotten to haue beene, but onely ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten as it ſhould neuer haue place again, by which it might be remembred; like as it came to paſſe in <hi>Sodom,</hi> howbeit the memory thereof ſhould other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be perpetuall.</p>
               <p>Afterward is reported more particularly the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of the <hi>Merchants, which had ſerued for the pleaſure of her, by Land and by Sea:</hi> The Merchants by land which had ſerued <hi>her with ſine meates, purple, ſilke, gold, ſiluer, precious ſtones, &amp;c. for their Veſtiments;</hi> namely, for the apparell of their Prieſts, Prelates, Cardinals, &amp;c. (which vſed to be moſt gorgeous and coſtly.) And they ſhould alſo bring to her, <hi>ſoules of men,</hi> that is, <hi>bond-ſlaues:</hi> meeting with that which ſhould come to paſſe &amp; be performed of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as we ſee experience of. Then the Merchants by Sea, the Ship-maſters, and Ship-men alſo make their lamentation ouer her.</p>
               <p>For the more certainty of this deſtruction of the City, there is brought in an Angell, <hi>taking a great ſtone, and caſting it into the bottome of the Sea,</hi> ſaying, that in like manner <hi>Babilon that great City ſhould be throwne downe with violence, and ſhould be found no more;</hi> noting that it ſhould be ſo vtterly deſtroyed, that it ſhould neuer be recouered, neither ſhould it be built any more, neither <hi>ſhould the light of a Candle
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:150822:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> be ſeene in it, neither the voice of a Bridegroome heard therein;</hi> ſignifying that it ſhould not be againe inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited of any, becauſe ſhee had deceiued all nations, and becauſe in her was found the <hi>bloud of the Saints and Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 19. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>And after theſe things I heard a great voice of a great multitude in heauen, ſaying Hallelu-iah, ſaluation, and glory, and honour, and power be to the Lord our God, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe Apoſtle hauing ſpoken of the deſtruction of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> noted by the name of an <hi>Harlot:</hi> he now comes to ſet forth the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Beaſt, and of the falſe Prophet;</hi> which are the vngodly Emperours, and the Popes, ſucceeding in that power, hauing gotten not onely ciuill iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, but Eccleſiaſticall power alſo ioyned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
               <p>And firſt of al before he handleth that, he bringeth in all the children &amp; ſeruants of God, <hi>praiſing &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying God for the notable works he had ſhewed vpon the earth.</hi> And herein eſpecially doe the Angels &amp; Saints of God in heauen, &amp; the Saints in earth, magnifie and praiſe the Lord, namely, for the iudgement and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the <hi>Whore,</hi> which is the City of <hi>Rome.</hi> The cauſes of her deſtruction are ſet downe, to be, firſt, becauſe ſhe had made all the Kings of the earth and their people to goe a whoring after her filthy ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations. And ſecondly for that ſhee had mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the Saints of God.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:150822:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>After that they had ſung this ſong of thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for that mercy receiued in the deſtruction of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Lord calleth them, and citeth them as it were by a <hi>voice from the Throne,</hi> to a further thankeſgiuing for the mercies to come, in the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and of the falſe Prophet, and for particular benefits which the Church it ſelfe was to be partaker of: and therefore he doth call all the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the Lord by name as it were, which did feare the Lord, <hi>both ſmall and great to praiſe the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then he ſhewes how this <hi>voice</hi> was obeyed, in that he ſaith, <hi>there was a voice as of a great multitude, and like the voice of many waters, and like the noiſe of a thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> which ſignifie both the conſent and zeale, and earneſtneſſe of the Saints in praiſing God. Which teacheth vs, that we are ſo to beleeue, and be aſſured of Gods promiſes and mercies to come, as that wee doe praiſe him for them, as for thoſe which we haue receiued, and as if wee had receiued them already.</p>
               <p>The mercies for which they praiſe God are two, firſt, the <hi>marriage of the Church to the Lambe,</hi> becauſe the Church in this life, being made the Spouſe of Chriſt, yet ſeparated in part from him, ſhall at length inioy and haue the full fruition of Chriſt, and of his glorious preſence.</p>
               <p>And alſo for that <hi>ſhe is arrayed with pure fine linnen;</hi> noting either the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt wherewith ſhe is cloathed, or elſe that ſanctification which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in part begun in this life in Gods children, ſhall be perfected in Gods kingdome when that ſpirituall marriage of Chriſt with his Spouſe ſhall be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:150822:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>And further it is ſhewed, that ſuch is the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Church of God in this marriage, that not onely the Bride and the Bridegrome, ſhall be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his happineſſe (as vſually commeth to paſſe in our marriage feaſts, the married perſons onely, not the gueſts being counted happy) but alſo thoſe are bleſſed and happy, that are bidden to this feaſt, for by the Bride, is to be vnderſtood in generall, the Church vniuerſall, by the perſons <hi>called,</hi> is meant the particular perſons in the Church.</p>
               <p>Another cauſe of thankeſgiuing for the things to come, is in regard of the iudgement vpon the wicked, and the execution thereof. And firſt he ſaith, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute this, hee ſeeth Chriſt <hi>comming with his army, hee being the chiefe;</hi> for as the Beaſt gathers his armies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, ſo in like manner, he bringeth his hoaſt againſt them to deſtroy them: And hee is deſcribed by his properties, namely, firſt, in that <hi>he ſitteth on a white Horſe;</hi> noting, that he was a Iudge, alluding to the manner of Iudges in thoſe times, (as we ſee in the Booke of <hi>Iudges</hi>) that in token of honour, they did vſe to ride on <hi>white Aſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſword which went out of his mouth;</hi> ſignifieth, that he would ſlay them onely by his will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Crownes on his head;</hi> note that his will ſhould preuaile againſt his enemies, and that hee will haue the victory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His eyes as a flame of fire;</hi> ſignifying his infinite knowledge of all things that were done, and his pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſight into all the coaſts and ſecrets of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſo that they could hide nothing from him. <hi>With his feete he ſhould tread and preſſe downe all his enemies
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:150822:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the Vine-preſſe of Gods wrath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then, as by his properties, ſo alſo he is deſcribed by his nature, in that his name is called <hi>The word of God.</hi> By his office, in that he is the <hi>King of Kings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Garments dipt in bloud;</hi> noting the ſharpe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge he will take vpon his enemies in their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>Further, he is ſet downe by his <hi>company</hi> and <hi>traine</hi> that followed him, <hi>to wit,</hi> the Angels and Saints, who are ſaid to ride alſo <hi>on white Horſes,</hi> ſignifying that they were conquerours ouer all their enemies by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Angell in the Sunne;</hi> to wit, which was able to order the Sunne, by cauſing it to giue light vnto the ſeruants of Chriſt, and withdrawing the light there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to depriue the enemies of the vſe of it, by ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting darkeneſſe vpon them, ſo as they could not ſee one another, much leſſe to fight againſt him; which ſignifieth and ſetteth forth the glory and power of Chriſt, that ſeeing one of his Angels was able to doe this, how much more wonderfull was his power, both in himſelfe, and in all the reſt of his Angels, to deſtroy thoſe his enemies?</p>
               <p>This Angell makes a proclamation of defiance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them before the battell, as it is the vſuall cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome in warres: And here he doth not, (as in wars Princes vſe to doe to their forraigne enemies) by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming open warre againſt them, to warne &amp; chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge them vnto fight, for hee needeth not, neither will hee, ſeeing they are not forreiners, but his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and rebels againſt him, being <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords:</hi> But in ſtead of ſending embaſſage or
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:150822:63" rendition="simple:additions"/> a Herauld of Armes vnto them, in ſcorne of them, hee makes proclamation vnto the Birds, and bids them <hi>come to eate of the fleſh of his enemies.</hi> And here he ſhewes the certainty and ſurety of his victory, in that before the battell he cals the Birds to deuoure, as if they were already ſlaine.</p>
               <p>Chriſt being thus deſcribed, as hee is in himſelfe, and alſo by his <hi>retinue</hi> and <hi>attendants,</hi> after followeth the euent and execution of the iudgements.</p>
               <p>And firſt, in that it is ſaid, <hi>the Beaſt, and the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> (which went out from the Beaſt) <hi>were taken;</hi> it noteth, that Chriſt as it were in a rage, ſeemeth to lay hold on thoſe his principall enemies, the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet, taking them, in contempt as it were, by the neckes, euen as a ſtrong man in his fury, in ſcorne taketh his weake enemie (with whom he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth to fight) by the Collar of the necke, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth him away; euen ſo Chriſt violently taketh them and caſteth them quicke into a Lake of fire &amp; brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The remnant are ſlaine with the ſword;</hi> to wit, the Kings and the People, noting the difference of their iudgement, from the iudgement of the Beaſt, and the Prophet; not that they were not alſo to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as well as theſe, but it is onely to ſhew, that their condemnation ſhould not be ſo terrible as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet: for as it is in earthly iudgements, according to the hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſſe and greatneſſe of the fact, ſuch is the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſneſſe of the puniſhment, the more heinous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders being to be burnt to death, thoſe that are leſſe grieuous offenders, to be ſlaine with the ſword, or
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:150822:63"/> with ſome leſſe violent death: euen ſo it ſhall be in this iudgement of Chriſt, the Beaſt and falſe Prophet being chiefe offenders and ring-leaders in this rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, ſhall haue a more terrible iudgement, and dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per condemnation.</p>
               <p>Which teacheth vs, that according to the degrees of ſinne, ſo ſhall be the degrees of puniſhment to the wicked in hell.</p>
               <p>In the midſt of the Chapter, there is ſet downe an accident which befell <hi>Iohn,</hi> which hee here inſerteth for the comfort and inſtruction of Gods Children; which is, <hi>that Iohn,</hi> though an excellent man, yet by the glory of the Angell, and the excellencie of the things by him ſhewed, was ſo amazed and ouertaken, <hi>that hee fell downe to worſhip the Angell;</hi> which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the great weakeneſſe of men, and their prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to Idolatry, for ſeeing that <hi>Iohn</hi> who was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a ſeruant of God, did thus forget himſelfe, much more others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which are not indued with ſuch graces. The Angell (as a faithfull ſeruant of God) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth that honour, and forbids him, ſaying, <hi>that hee himſelfe was his fellow-Seruant,</hi> and therefore not to be worſhipped. But (ſaith hee) <hi>worſhip God;</hi> noting, that all worſhip belongeth to God alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:150822:64"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 20. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>And I ſaw an Angell come downe from heauen, hauing the key of the bottomleſſe pit, and a great chaine in his hand, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IN this Chapter, there is ſet forth vnto vs, two vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories that God and our Sauiour Chriſt haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Dragon, the firſt and the laſt. Then is ſet forth the latter iudgement that ſhall be in the day of the Lord, the great day, the day as it were of the great aſſize. That which is contained in the firſt part of the Chapter, is ſomewhat diſplaced, belonging to the end of the twelfth Chapter, but reſerued to this place, that there might be a better declaration of the ſtory of the Dragon. To the better vnderſtanding of this, we are to remember that which was before in the 12. Chapter, where it is ſaid, <hi>that the Dragon perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the Woman:</hi> which noteth (as wee haue heard) that great perſecution which befell the Church of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that ancient Church of God. For when as the Dragon ſaw that he was caſt from heauen, and that the woman had wings giuen her to flye from him into the Wilderneſſe, and now hee could not haue his will againſt her; hee after that, rageth excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly againſt the ſeede of the <hi>woman, to wit,</hi> the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> for the Church of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> being begotten by the preaching and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Apoſtles, are called their ſeed. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it is ſaid, <hi>that he is faine to be bound,</hi> after that he beganne thus to rage, which was about ſixe and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares after Chriſt, being the time that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:150822:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> was ouerthrowne, about that time was the Diuell ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, for hauing purſued the Church of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and hauing ſet himſelfe fiercely againſt the Church of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> God euen then ſeazes vpon him by an elect Angell; for the good Angels of light are not onely ſo ſtrong as he by creation, but alſo by the power of God, commanding them to doe it, they are made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to deale with the Diuell, to chaine him, and to doe with him whatſoeuer it pleaſeth the Lord to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne them.</p>
               <p>It is then ſaid, that this good Angell commeth and bindeth him <hi>with a great chaine;</hi> to wit, not with a materiall Chaine; for the Diuell, being a ſpirit, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be bound with any ſuch Chaine, but ſpeaking to our capacitie, hee noteth by the Chaine, that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell was tied ſtrongly &amp; ſafely. And hee is <hi>caſt into the bottomleſſe pit;</hi> namely, <hi>Hell,</hi> where the Diuell and his Angels ſhall be throwne for euermore. <hi>And he ſealed the doore;</hi> that is, he made him ſure, as wee ſee in the Scripture, the cuſtome of thoſe times, that when they would keepe any in faſt hold, they would ſet a Seale on the doore, that ſo it might be ſeene whether any came to the parties cloſed vp: as namely, when Chriſt was buried, the Tombe wherein hee lay was ſealed vp: noting, that he was ſo ſurely ſealed, and ſo faſt tied vp, as that no ſtrength, power, or pollicie of his whatſoeuer, was able to looſe or deliuer him. The ſpace hee was ſhut vp in hell, was <hi>a thouſand yeares.</hi> The reaſon of his ſhutting vp is, that he ſhould not deuoure the Church of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> nor haue his will in hurting the nations, which were called to the knowledge of the truth, at that time in the beginning
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:150822:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Church: for ſeeing hee began ſo fiercely to ſtorme and rage, hee would haue deuoured and conſumed the Church, if hee had not beene reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. So that we ſee in this reſtraint of his, howſoeuer he had ſtill power to doe hurt, and to deceiue, yet he could not doe it in his owne perſon, and therefore not ſo dangerouſly, nor ſo vehemently, as otherwiſe he would, neither yet ſo craftily, effectually, &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily as hee did before; and yet notwithſtanding hee did it as maliciouſly as then hee could, but this was onely by his deputie the Beaſt. After, it is ſaid, that when thoſe <hi>thouſand yeares</hi> are ended, <hi>hee muſt be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;</hi> which howſoeuer it was a heauie prophecie, and a great threat of God, and grieuous to the Church, that the Diuell ſhould be <hi>looſed,</hi> yet it is ſomewhat leſſened, in that it is ſaid, it ſhould be but for a <hi>little ſeaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An effect of this <hi>binding</hi> and <hi>ſhutting</hi> vp of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, is ſet downe, namely, in that there were <hi>Thrones,</hi> that is (as he expoundeth it afterward) that life, and that glory which the Children of God had, namely, to <hi>liue and raigne with Chriſt,</hi> which is not meant of the life to come, but onely vnderſtood of that life of God which conſiſteth in godlineſſe, righteouſneſſe, and true holineſſe; of thoſe honours, and that credit which the Children of God ſhould haue: who are deſcribed what they are, namely, <hi>thoſe that ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for the Goſpell,</hi> for the <hi>witneſſe of Ieſus, which had not worſhipped the Beaſt, neither receiued the marke of the Beaſt; to wit,</hi> profeſſed ſeruice to the Beaſt, either publiquely or priuately, and theſe are they that liued the life of God. Where wee ſee that God prouided
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:150822:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> for his Church in the beginning, leſt it ſhould be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercharged and ouerthrowne at the firſt: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore howſoeuer they, euen then, by the malice of the Diuels ſubſtitutes, ſuſtained great troubles and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, yet God moderates them ſo, as they might notwithſtanding be able to ſtand, ſuffering them to haue no greater troubles, then he vouchſafeth them ſtrength, and giues them meanes of ſtanding, <hi>to wit,</hi> by withdrawing the power and force of Sathan from purſuing them: for according to their ſtrength, ſo God ſends triall to his Children.</p>
               <p>The reſt which were dead in thoſe <hi>thouſand yeares,</hi> hauing not the firſt reſurrection, are ſaid <hi>to haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> though they were not in ſo dangerous dayes, as afterward enſued when the Diuell was looſed: And theſe are ſaid, <hi>that they ſhall not liue,</hi> to wit, <hi>vnto Chriſt, to become Chriſts, during the thouſand yeares, vntill the thouſand yeares were ended,</hi> that is, <hi>neuer:</hi> for if they were not Chriſts, liuing holily and vprightly before Chriſt, in Sathans binding and impriſonment, which were milder and more eaſie times; much leſſe would they be his afterwards, to walke faithfully and pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in more dangerous times of perſecution and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And this is ſaid to be <hi>the firſt reſurrection;</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when men are renewed by the ſpirit of God, and ſo walke in newneſſe and holineſſe of life, and in a faithfull and conſtant profeſſion of the truth of God. And thoſe <hi>are bleſſed that haue part in the firſt reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> for they ſhall be made partakers of the ſecond reſurrection, and the ſecond death ſhall haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with them, but they ſhall be Prieſts of God, and of Chriſt, to offer ſacrifice of praiſe and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:150822:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> thankeſgiuing vnto him: And theſe <hi>ſhall raigne with him a thouſand yeares,</hi> that is, for euermore; for thoſe that once taſt of the fauour of God, ſo that they are ſeaſoned with it, ſhall neuer leeſe it: according as our Sauiour Chriſt in the Goſpell of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that drinkes of the water of life, ſhall neuer thirſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After, it is ſpoken of the Diuels <hi>looſing,</hi> for hee ſhould not alwayes be ſhut vp in the place of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, but being looſed, is ſuffered to range a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, to doe what hurt hee could; which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding God doth in great wiſedome and care ouer his Church, ſo as howſoeuer he ſendeth more afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to them by Sathans libertie, then before, yet hee will giue them greater ſtrength then before: for as in the thouſand yeares before, God hauing giuen his ſeruants leſſe ſtore of ſtrength, he mittigateth alſo the meanes of their tribulations, by binding the Diuell, the chiefe worker of miſchiefe againſt them. So now Sathan being let looſe, and their troubles thereby augmented, he alſo increaſeth grace and ſtrength in them to vndergoe them.</p>
               <p>The effects of <hi>Sathans looſing</hi> follow; as namely, <hi>that he went about euery corner of the earth, to deceiue, and to doe miſchiefe;</hi> according as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>that Sathan goeth about like a roaring enemy, ſeeking whom he may deuoure.</hi> And he called together, <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and infinite numbers, <hi>as many as the ſands of the Sea,</hi> which filled the face of the earth, to battell againſt the Church of God. Here by <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> he alludeth onely to a place in <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> not interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting<note place="margin">Ezech. 38</note> it; <hi>Gog</hi> was a Country in <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe, whoſe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:150822:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> firſt King was called <hi>Gog,</hi> whereupon the Country tooke that name; in heathen writers hee is called <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> not differing from the letters in Hebrew. <hi>Magog</hi> was a name giuen to the <hi>Syrians:</hi> both theſe were neere vnto the <hi>Iewes,</hi> whoſe enmitie (as <hi>Daniel</hi> recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth) was moſt vehement againſt the people of God: wherupon the <hi>Iewes</hi> called their moſt bitter &amp; ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full enemies, by the names of <hi>Gog,</hi> and <hi>Magog.</hi> So that here is not meant (as ſome doe imagine) any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Country of <hi>Germany, England,</hi> &amp;c. ſaying, that as the Goſpell came out of the Eaſt into the Weſt, ſo it ſhall returne out of the Weſt into the Eaſt, and then (ſay they) theſe Weſt Countries falling from the truth, ſhall ſet themſelues againſt the Church, which thing can haue no allowance at all from hence: But here onely is meant, thoſe moſt bitter enemies of the Church, which being ſtirred vp by Sathan, ſhall come with all might and malice that can be, and ſhall fight againſt the Church, compaſſing about it to deſtroy it.</p>
               <p>But it is ſaid, the Church ſhall haue victory, and that by Chriſt, for <hi>fire,</hi> that is, <hi>the wrath of God,</hi> ſhall come downe from heauen and conſume them.</p>
               <p>After, he ſaith, that the Diuell is <hi>taken,</hi> for hauing ſpoken before of the <hi>Whore,</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and of the falſe <hi>Prophet;</hi> he now ſheweth what ſhall be done to the Diuell, who was laſt to be deſtroyed; and it is ſaid, <hi>that he was caſt into a lake of fire and brimſtone, there to be tormented with the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet for euermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond part of the Chapter, is of the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the laſt iudgement: where firſt it is ſaid, <hi>there
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:150822:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> was a white Throne;</hi> which of what matter it ſhall be, no man knoweth, yet ſeeing Chriſt is man as well as God, he ſhall haue no doubt, a royall and reall place, wherein he ſhall ſit moſt euidently.</p>
               <p>His glory is further expreſſed, in that <hi>the heauens and the earth ſhall flye away from before his face,</hi> and ſhall paſſe away, and ſhall burne with fire.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſhall the dead be raiſed vp, <hi>and all, both great and ſmall, ſhall be ſummoned before God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Bookes were opened;</hi> that is, the Bookes of euery mans conſcience ſhall be laid open and diſcloſed; wherein is nothing but guiltineſſe of conſcience to condemne euery one.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, there is another Booke open, which is the <hi>Booke of life; to wit,</hi> the Booke of Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination, which euery one ſhall be iudged by, as he is elect or reprobate: yet ſo, as that election and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation doe not take away workes, for it is ſaid, they ſhall be iuſtified or condemned according to their workes; for they that are elected to life, are alſo elected to ſanctification; the reprobate contrariwiſe.</p>
               <p>The iuſt haue <hi>reward,</hi> not for their good workes ſake, but according to their good workes wrought; and that not before their calling, conuerſion, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, but which afterwards were done in faith, and this onely for his owne mercie and promiſe ſake in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The wicked are condemned, according to their workes, and for their workes ſake, their name being not found in the Booke of life.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it is ſaid, <hi>that death &amp; hell were caſt into the lake,</hi> that is, were ſwallowed vp in immortality, there being now no more danger of death &amp; hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:150822:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 21. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>And I ſaw a new heauen, and a new earth: for the firſt heauen, and the firſt earth were paſſed away, and there was no more Sea, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>VVEe haue heard heretofore of the ſtraits of the Church militant, being in warfare in this preſent world, ſubject to many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and perſecutions: yet being defended and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by God, was not ouercome by any of them. Now followes the ſtate of the Church triumphant after this world.</p>
               <p>And firſt, here Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſets forth the ſtate of all the world, then of the Church: Euen as <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Booke of <hi>Geneſis</hi> deſcribes firſt the beginning and creation of the whole world, and then ſets downe the condition and ſtate of the Church.</p>
               <p>The ſtate of the world is declared in the firſt verſe, in that it is ſaid, <hi>there was a new heauen &amp; a new earth;</hi> that is, the heauens being partly corrupted and dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened by ſinne, and hauing loſt ſomewhat of their glory they had before, ſhall not onely haue that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, but a better glory then the firſt: ſo likewiſe ſhould the earth, and the ſea alſo; for in that it is ſaid, <hi>the Sea ſhall be no more,</hi> it is not to be vnderſtood, that it ſhould not afterwards be, but that it ſhould not then be the ſame that now it is; namely, raging, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous, and diſturbed, as now wee ſee it to be; but it ſhould be ſtill and quiet, the waters and the fiſhes remaining ſtill, yet without roaring, ſwelling, and that diſtemperature which now it hath.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:150822:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>As for the Church, it is deſcribed generally in the firſt ſeauen Verſes; particularly in the reſt of the Chapter; as alſo in ſome of the next.</p>
               <p>In generall, hee compares the Church to a <hi>braue Spouſe, prepared and trimmed for a King;</hi> Chriſt being her Huſband, ſignifying the glory and beautie of the Church of God: for as in the dayes of the ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of marriage, Brides vſe to goe beyond their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary cuſtome and kinde of apparell, ſo the Church is now decked and beautified with full and perfect glory.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is compared to a <hi>City comming downe from heauen,</hi> that is, a beautifull City, hauing all her honour, glory, and good frame of building, not from her ſelfe, but from God: not as the Cities which are builded by men, but as one that is builded by God himſelfe: for as earthly Cities builded by men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their title from them; ſo this City being built by God, hath her name alſo from God: Neither is here meant (<hi>in that it comes downe from heauen</hi>) that it ſhould be in earth, but onely that it is altogether heauenly.</p>
               <p>Afterward, the ſtate and bleſſedneſſe of it is ſet forth, in that <hi>God ſhall dwell in it continually,</hi> as the Scripture teſtifieth, that he ſhall more fully remaine and dwell with them then before: for as it is ſaid in the Scripture, that in this life hee will Dine and Sup with them, ſo now it is ſaid, he ſhall abide with them for euermore.</p>
               <p>Then is ſet forth what they ſhall haue by the dwelling of God with them; namely, all happineſſe; firſt, in that they <hi>ſhall drinke of the Well of life;</hi> that is,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:150822:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhould receiue all pleaſure, and al comfortable, good, and deſirable things. Secondly, <hi>God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes;</hi> that is, all things naught, grieuous, corrupt, and painefull, ſhall be taken from them.</p>
               <p>And albeit to fleſh and bloud this may ſeeme a ſtrange thing, and altogether impoſſible and incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in regard of theſe miſeries we now are in, and of our ſinfulneſſe and wretchedneſſe, yet to take away that infidelity of ours, it is ſaid, <hi>that God himſelfe ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it,</hi> and bids <hi>Iohn write, that all things ſhall be new;</hi> for he will make all things new, howſoeuer now they be troubleſome and old.</p>
               <p>And in that he biddeth <hi>Iohn,</hi> for the further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Church of God, <hi>to write,</hi> that all old things are done, and that new things are come, and in that he ſaith, <hi>that to him that thirſteth, he will giue of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life, and that he which ouercommeth, ſhall inherite all things;</hi> yet hee ſo ſaith it, that none ſhall haue it without holineſſe of life; for as for thoſe that were <hi>fearefull, vnbeleeuing, abhominable adulterers, idolaters, &amp;c. they ſhould be caſt out of the Kingdome.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee teacheth, that none ſhould preſume of this mercie of God which liue wickedly and prophanely, but thoſe onely ſhould inioy it, which ſhould liue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily and vprightly.</p>
               <p>More particularly, hee deſcribeth the Church in the ninth Verſe, where firſt hauing noted it in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall (as before) that it ſhall be as a <hi>Spouſe,</hi> and as a <hi>Citie:</hi> he ſecondly in particular, purſues the <hi>City</hi> more at large.</p>
               <p>And firſt he ſets downe the ſituation of this <hi>City</hi> (it
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:150822:69"/> being a notable commendation for a City to be well ſituated) and this City he ſaith, <hi>is ſituate vpon an hill;</hi> that is, both in a faire and pleaſant, as alſo in a ſtrong place, according as Cities ſo ſituate vſe to be, noting hereby, the excellent ſituation of it, both in regard of the pleaſantneſſe, as alſo of the ſtrength of it.</p>
               <p>Then hee deſcribes it firſt in the eſſentiall parts of it, and then by the properties and qualities, the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges, and good things, belonging thereunto.</p>
               <p>For the eſſentiall parts of them, hee mentions to be, <hi>the Wals, the Gates, the Streets, the foundations of the City, and of the Wall.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <label>And of them he ſets forth the</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>matter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>forme.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The <hi>matter</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>gold, precious ſtones, &amp;c.</hi> to wit, the moſt precious things that can be.</p>
               <p>The <hi>forme,</hi> that they are moſt glittering, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſhining, chriſtall-like, and laſtly in moſt excellent order.</p>
               <p>In the matter of the Church, there are ſet downe the Children of God particularly, for as in generall the Church is ſet downe by a City, ſo by theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, are meant the Children of God particularly, they being called in the Scriptures, <hi>the ſtones of Gods houſe, and of Gods City.</hi> By theſe earthly things, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our weake capacity, by reaſon of our ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance) hee ſets downe their excellencie, that by theſe things that are better knowne vnto vs, we may as by ſteares come to the view of the heauenly glory, and therefore by theſe matters which are moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent on earth, hee ſetteth forth that heauenly beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:150822:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The forme of the City, is <hi>foure-ſquare;</hi> noting, a moſt excellent forme: To the meaſuring whereof, the Angell is ſaid to haue <hi>a golden Reede;</hi> where hee takes a ſimilitude from cunning Artificers, who to lay euery part euen, haue their lines and ſquares, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying, that here euery thing is in perfect order.</p>
               <p>In that the meaſure is ſaid <hi>to be the meaſure of a man,</hi> that is, of an Angell, it meaneth that it was the meaſure of this Angell that appeared to <hi>Iohn</hi> in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It had twelue Gates, and on the Gates the names of the twelue Tribes of the children of Iſraell written:</hi> By the twelue Tribes, are vnderſtood all the Children of God, which are the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, the ſeede of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> according to the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Their names written on the Gates, which are on euery ſide of the City;</hi> doe note thus much, namely, that as a City hath Gates on euery ſide, to the end, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may haue recourſe vnto it, from all coaſts round about, ſo the Church of God is ſaid to haue twelue Gates round about, with the names of the twelue Tribes of the Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> in them, to ſignifie that all the Children of God ſhould come vnto it, out of euery part of the world.</p>
               <p>Hauing ſpoken of the City, and of the particular parts thereof, he comes to ſpeake of the priuiledges, and firſt he ſaith, <hi>they haue no need of any Temple, for God ſhall be their Temple;</hi> that is, God ſhall be all in all in the Church, without meanes of the outward exerciſes of religion, as of the Sacraments, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the word.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>there is no neede of the Sunne and of the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:150822:70" rendition="simple:additions"/> Moone,</hi> becauſe <hi>the glory of God ſhall giue it light;</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof, the Sunne ſhall haue no light, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of that light, nor any other light; for God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infinitely more light, ſhall inlighten them. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſignifying both by the <hi>Sunne</hi> and the <hi>Temple,</hi> that both ciuilly and eccleſiaſtically God ſhould be all in all, without any outward meanes of gouernement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The glory and honour of the Nations ſhall be brought vnto it;</hi> that is, they ſhall haue glory and ioy, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Nations comming thither, <hi>to wit,</hi> they ſhould not onely haue ioy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Gods preſence, which was principall, but alſo in regard of the preſence one of another, in that the people of God in all Nations ſhall come thither.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Gates ſhall not be ſhut in the day, for night there is none:</hi> In that <hi>there is no night,</hi> hee meaneth that there is no alteration of ioy, but there is light alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p>In that <hi>there is continuall day;</hi> hee noteth that there is all comfort for euermore, for the day is comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
               <p>Againe, <hi>the Gates not ſhut;</hi> ſignifying, that there ſhould be no feare of danger now, nor terrour of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but all peace, ſafety, and ſecurity.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it is ſaid, <hi>no vncleane thing ſhall be there;</hi> that is, holineſſe onely, and thoſe things that are holy ſhall be there perpetually, becauſe thoſe onely that are written in the Booke of life ſhould be there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:150822:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Apoc. Cap. 22. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>And hee ſhewed mee a pure Riuer of water of life, cleare as chriſtall, proceeding out of the Throne of GOD, and of the Lambe, &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IN this Chapter are ſet forth to vs, firſt the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of the effects of Gods preſence, and of the preſence of our Sauiour Chriſt towards the Church in the world to come, partly ſet forth in the former, partly in the beginning of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, containing the comforts they ſhould receiue thereby, <hi>to wit,</hi> that they ſhould be throughly and perfectly bleſſed, not onely with neceſſary things, but with all manner of delights and pleaſure, and with much glory and honour.</p>
               <p>And firſt it is ſaid, <hi>there was a Riuer which ranne throughout the midſt of it;</hi> ſignifying firſt the pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the City: for as that City is notably ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated which ſtandeth ſo as that it hath a Riuer run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning through it, to carry away the filthineſſe and vncleaneneſſe from it, ſo this City is ſo placed, as that it is voide of all noyſomneſſe and vncleaneneſſe. And alſo it is ſaid <hi>to haue a Riuer going through it,</hi> in regard of thoſe Countries which vſed to drinke of the water of the Riuer; which if it were neere, was an excellent commodity, which notwithſtanding, was oft times farre off from the City; but here it is not ſo, for this Riuer is neere at hand, being a riuer of freſh water; yea, of water of life: and they neede not to goe out of the City to fetch it; as did the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan</hi> Woman, it being euen at the doores.</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:150822:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the middes of the Streete, and on both ſides of the Riuer, was the tree of life;</hi> which ſignifieth our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, who is called <hi>the Tree of life,</hi> in regard of thoſe moſt excellent and liuely graces, which as moſt comfortable fruits, hee bringeth forth, and miniſtreth vnto his Church. And as by the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was ſet downe their drinkes, ſo alſo by the Tree of life, is expreſſed their meat; not that there ſhall be in the Kingdome of heauen any corporall meate or drinke, but onely noting a ſufficiency and fulneſſe of all good things, which there Gods Children ſhould haue. In that the <hi>Tree of life</hi> bringeth forth fruit euery moneth, (<hi>to wit,</hi> twelue times in the yeare) and it bringeth forth alſo ſeuerall kindes of fruit, it noteth all meaſure and kindes of delight, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not onely plentifull, but alſo full of all variety. Euen as men vſe to doe, which making a feaſt, will not content themſelues with one ſort of meat, but will labour to haue what variety they can, of moſt dainty meates, that it may bring more delight vnto the gueſts: ſo here it is noted, that in Chriſt there ſhould be all ſufficiency and variety of pleaſures and delights. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> here chooſeth to ſet forth the ioyes of heauen by <hi>fruits,</hi> rather then by <hi>Oxen and Fatlings,</hi> (as our Sauiour Chriſt expreſſeth it <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> 22.) becauſe our Sauiour hath regard to vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all marriages of Kings and Princes, who vſe againſt their Marriage-feaſts, to kill great ſtore of Beeues and ſuch like prouiſion: the holy Ghoſt here in this place, hath relation to that firſt kinde of liuing in the beginning, in mans innocencie, when he onely liued of the fruits of the earth,</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:150822:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The leaues of it are to heale the ſores:</hi> ſignifying, that there could be no ſickneſſe there, ſeeing they had health at their doores, and that of the ſame tree whereof they had their meat.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They had no neede of light; becauſe God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and Chriſt, was their light;</hi> which doth adde to that felicitie: for as darkeneſſe in hell aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uates the miſerie of the wicked; ſo contrariwiſe, the fulneſſe of light the godly ſhall haue, doth augment their happineſſe, and more, in that that light ſhall exceede the light of the Sunne.</p>
               <p>And further, to ſhut vp their ioy, he ſaith, one ſingular and notable comfort and felicity to Gods Children, <hi>is to ſerue and worſhip God,</hi> for howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer now, by reaſon of our corrupt nature, it ſeemes a burthen and a trouble to worſhip God, yet then it ſhall be one of our chiefeſt ioyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They ſtand in Gods preſence;</hi> that is, haue moſt excellent priuiledges of Gods ſauour, and bee principall ſeruants vnto God, as thoſe are in moſt honour with Princes, which are ſaid to ſtand in their preſence, and attend vpon them in their Courts. As <hi>Daniel</hi> is ſaid to ſtand in the preſence of the King: ſo theſe ſhall ſtand in the Courts of God, and haue the full fruition of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable preſence; and therefore on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſide, the vngodly are herein accurſed (2. <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians.</hi> 1. 9) in that they are ſhut from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, <hi>to wit,</hi> his gracious preſence, for otherwiſe, all things whatſoeuer are in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, they ſhall raigne and rule for euermore,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:150822:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> being ioyned with Chriſt, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</p>
               <p>Thus much of their comforts in the Kingdome of God: Now followes the cloſe of the Booke, to giue more credit to it, and to ſtirre vp others to looke more diligently into it, and to regard to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate, and practiſe it more carefully.</p>
               <p>Here then is ſet downe firſt the teſtimony of the Angell; then of <hi>Iohn;</hi> laſtly, of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Of the Angell, who ſaith, that all theſe things are <hi>faithfull and true:</hi> which he proueth by the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe, which is <hi>God,</hi> by the inſtrument to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer it to <hi>Iohn,</hi> which was <hi>himſelfe,</hi> being ſent of God, and by the <hi>time,</hi> which is, that they ſhall <hi>ſhortly come to paſſe.</hi> And therefore heauen and earth ſhall ſooner paſſe, then one of theſe ſhall fall to the ground.</p>
               <p>By the teſtimony of <hi>Iohn,</hi> which ſaith, <hi>that it was hee which ſaw and heard theſe things;</hi> and therefore could teſtifie of them: whereupon hee taketh occaſion to repeat his former fall, for ſaith he, ſuch were the ſtrangeneſſe of theſe things, <hi>that when I ſaw them, I fell downe and worſhipped the Angell;</hi> where hee confeſſeth his grieuous fault in worſhipping the creature in ſtead of the Creator, for which, hee is reprehended of the Angell, for drawing this viſion to a wrong end, and making a contrary vſe of the ſame, namely by worſhipping him which was a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God, <hi>to wit,</hi> an Angell, who was his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Seruant, and therefore not to be worſhipped,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:150822:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> and hauing reprehended him for the abuſe, hee teacheth him the right vſe and end of the ſame; namely, firſt, that hee ſhould hereby be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp to worſhip God: and ſecondly, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and teſtifie it to others: And therefore hee biddeth him <hi>not to ſeale the words of this Prophecie;</hi> noting, that hee ſhould ſhew and manifeſt it to the Church of God: To the end, that firſt they might keepe and practiſe the things therein contained.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that they might vnderſtand the certainty of the things therein contained: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee meeteth with an obiection that might be made. For (might ſome ſay) if they muſt come certainely, why then ſhould men trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelues about it, in ſtudying for the knowledge of the vnderſtanding of that Booke, eſpecially ſeeing it is ſo hard and darkely ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? and that many would abuſe the things of this Prophecie, and wreſt them to another end then the Apoſtle meant them, being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in a ſtile ſo vnwonted; as <hi>Peter 2. Pauls</hi> ſayings are ſaid to be <hi>hard.</hi> But the Angell anſweres, that it muſt not be ſealed vp, but publiſhed. And howſoeuer it may be, ſome may take occaſion to be wicked and careleſſe by it, yet Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, it makes no matter for that, for though the wicked ſtumble at it, yet it is giuen for the comfort of the righteous, and for the Children of Gods ſake, and they ſhall profit, and be bettered by it, and made more iuſt, by taking heed of theſe iudgements
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:150822:73" rendition="simple:additions"/> herein contained. And for the wicked, hee ſaid, <hi>if any will be euill, let him be euill ſtill.</hi> And laſt of all, hee ſaith, that though it ſhould not make either for the furthering of the wicked in their wickedneſſe, or to further the godly in their godlineſſe; yet it is to be left vnſealed for the glory of God, to manifeſt him to be true, and his word true, when all theſe things ſhall come to paſſe.</p>
               <p>Then is Chriſt himſelfe brought in, ſpeaking, ſaying, <hi>Behold, I come quickly, &amp;c.</hi> In which words of our Sauiour, hee confirmeth alſo to vs the truth of this Prophecie, and the teſtimony of the Angell, his titles whereby hee is deſcribed, are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of before.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, hee ſhutteth vp the Booke with an exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration againſt the wicked, and a promiſe of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing towards the godly: And becauſe <hi>Iohn</hi> was the laſt writer of the Scriptures and word of God, it may well be referred vnto the whole new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and the old. And hee ſaith: <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer doth adde or take away, let him be accurſed.</hi> For Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſeeing wicked men labour to corrupt the writings of the Apoſtles, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men of God, by adding, detracting, and chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as is the common practiſe in other writings of men of fame, hee doth therefore meet with that corruption, and addeth this curſe vnto them, that either adde any thing vnto it, or diminiſh any thing here-from. But ſome will obiect, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods word cannot be corrupted, wherfore then doth he goe about to forbid the corrupting of it?</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:150822:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>It is anſwered, howſoeuer the word of God cannot in any point be corrupted, yet God would alſo haue the meanes vſed whereby hee would haue the ſame preſerued, by ſetting downe the threatnings of curſe to the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of it, and promiſes of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the keepers and preſeruers of it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
